<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5563" whole_study_id="5563" phs="000094" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-05-18T18:29:33-05:00" modDate="2019-09-25T08:59:33-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-09-25T08:59:33-05:00" handle="GENEVA_OralClefts" num_participants="7599"><StudyInfo accession="phs000094.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000094.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75513" entrez_id="75513" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75515" entrez_id="75515" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>International Consortium to Identify Genes and Interactions Controlling Oral Clefts</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType></StudyTypes><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Oral clefts represent the most common group of craniofacial birth defects in humans, and include cleft lip with or without  cleft palate (CL/P) and cleft palate (CP).  Oral clefts have a complex and heterogeneous etiology, with strong evidence for  both genetic and environmental causal factors.  Candidate gene studies and genome wide linkage studies have yielded compelling  but inconsistent evidence that multiple genes control risk, and several studies have shown evidence for interaction between  genes and environmental exposures, especially maternal smoking and nutrient intake.  This consortium pulls together a  very large collection of cases and their parents from multiple populations, and offers a unique opportunity to expand  the search for genes controlling risk to the genome wide level.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The specific aims are:   &lt;ol&gt;    &lt;li&gt;To conduct a genome wide analysis on 2000+ case-parent trios ascertained through a case with isolated, non-syndromic    CL/P or CP to test for linkage and disequilibrium.  Initial analysis will consist of individual tests for gene effects    while simultaneously testing for GxE interaction with common maternal exposures including vitamin supplementation,    cigarette smoking and alcohol consumption (which have all been implicated as environmental risk factors for oral clefts).&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;To use haplotypes in tests for GxE interaction incorporating population specific estimates.  Since haplotype frequencies    vary among populations, trios will be assigned haplotypes in a stratified estimation and then a pooled test statistic will    be constructed.&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;To test for interaction between SNPs in different genes showing evidence of influencing risk in a test for GxG interaction.&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;To test for interaction between genes and maternal biomarkers using trios from Utah where measures of plasma folate,    vitamin B-6, homocysteine and zinc in mothers are available.&lt;/li&gt;   &lt;/ol&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;This study is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies initiative   (GENEVA, &lt;a href="http://www.genevastudy.org" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.genevastudy.org&lt;/a&gt;),   which was developed through the trans-NIH Genes, Environment, and Health Initiative (GEI). The overarching goal   is to identify novel genetic factors that contribute to oral clefts through large-scale genome-wide association   studies of well-characterized cases and their parents from multiple populations. Genotyping was performed at the   Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR). The study was supported by the National   Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR). Data cleaning and harmonization   were done at the GEI-funded GENEVA Coordinating Center at the University of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;This consortium was formed in 2006 in response to the Genes and Environment Imitative (GEI), a NIH wide initiative.  The  participants are all experiences researchers in the genetics and genetic epidemiology of oral clefts, and each has foreign  collaborators contributing samples to this study.  Case-parent trios were recruited from over 12 separate populations  under similar research protocols, and individual IRBs at each institution reviewed and approved submission of coded data  to dbGaP as part of this research project.  The primary US research groups are:  &lt;ul&gt;   &lt;li&gt;Johns Hopkins (Beaty, TH, PI) which brought in samples from a multicenter international study supported by R01-DE-014881   with participating recruitment sites in Singapore (Chong, S and Yeow, V, site PIs), Taiwan (Wu-Chou, YH, site PI), and 3 sites   in Peoples&amp;#39; Republic of China (Wang, H, site PI, Shandong Providence; Huang, S, site PI and Ye, X, Wuhan; and Shi, B, Chengdu),   plus Korea (Jee, SH).&lt;/li&gt;   &lt;li&gt;University of Iowa (Murray, JC, PI) which contributed samples from Denmark (Christensen, K) and the Philippines.&lt;/li&gt;   &lt;li&gt;Utah State University (Munger, RG, PI).&lt;/li&gt;   &lt;li&gt;University of Pittsburg (Marazita, ML, PI).&lt;/li&gt;   &lt;li&gt;NIEHS and University of Bergen (Wilcox, A and Lie, RT).&lt;/li&gt;  &lt;/ul&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Terri H. Beaty</AttrName><Institution>Johns Hopkins School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>U01-DE-018993</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping"><AttrName>HHSN268200782096C. "NIH contract High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease"</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>U01 DE018993-02</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="10" name="NIDCR" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="TBEATY" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="TBEATY" fname="Terri" mname="H" lname="Beaty" email="tbeaty1@jhu.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012723203" aid="1" auth="cit" login="harrisel" fname="Emily" mname="L" lname="Harris" email="harrisel@nidcr.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011943984" aid="1" auth="cit" login="steink" fname="Kathryn" mname="Kreimborg" lname="Stein" email="steink@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for the study entitled &#8220;International Consortium to Identify Genes and Interactions Controlling Oral Clefts&#8221; was provided by several previous grants from the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR). Data and samples were drawn from several studies awarded to members of this consortium. Funding to support original data collection, previous genotyping and analysis came from several sources to individual investigators. Funding for individual investigators include: R21-DE-013707 and R01-DE-014581 (Beaty); R37-DE-08559 and P50-DE-016215 (Murray, Marazita) and the Iowa Comprehensive Program to Investigate Craniofacial and Dental Anomalies (Murray); R01-DE-09886 (Marazita), R01-DE-012472 (Marazita), R01-DE-014677 (Marazita), R01-DE-016148 (Marazita), R21-DE-016930 (Marazita); R01-DE-013939 (Scott). Parts of this research were supported in part by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (Wilcox, Lie). Additional recruitment was supported by the Smile Train Foundation for recruitment in China (Jabs, Beaty, Shi) and a grant from the Korean government (Jee).  

The genome-wide association study, also known the Cleft Consortium, is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies (GENEVA) program of the trans-NIH Genes, Environment and Health Initiative [GEI] supported by U01-DE-018993. Genotyping services were provided by the Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR). CIDR is fully funded through a federal contract from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) to The Johns Hopkins University, contract number HHSN268200782096C. Funds for genotyping were provided by the NIDCR through CIDR&#8217;s NIH contract. Assistance with genotype cleaning, as well as with general study coordination, was provided by the GENEVA Coordinating Center (U01-HG-004446) and by the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI).

We sincerely thank all of the patients and families at each recruitment site for participating in this study, and we gratefully acknowledge the invaluable assistance of clinical, field and laboratory staff who contributed to this effort over the years.

Datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/study.cgi?study_id=phs000094.v1.p1 through dbGaP accession number phs000094.v1.p1.
</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>Limited to genetic research on cleft lip/palate or other craniofacial anomalies.</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (GSR are sensitive according to the Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="85" CGType="" title="Craniofacial Anomalies" name="CFA" dac_uid="78" dac_name="NIDCR" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Limited to genetic research on cleft lip/palate or other craniofacial anomalies.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>