<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5500" whole_study_id="5500" phs="000092" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-03-11T11:05:49-05:00" modDate="2020-01-21T13:41:13-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-01-21T13:41:13-05:00" handle="GEI_AlcoholDependenceAddiction" num_participants="4121"><StudyInfo accession="phs000092.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000092.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75449" entrez_id="75449" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75451" entrez_id="75451" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>GENEVA Study of Addiction: Genetics and Environment (SAGE)</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;This study is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies initiative (GENEVA) funded by the National Human Genome Research   Institute. The overarching goal is to identify novel genetic factors that contribute to addiction through a large-scale genome-wide   association study of DSM-IV alcohol dependent (and frequently illicit drug dependent) cases and non-dependent, unrelated control   subjects of European and African American descent.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The focus of this proposal is a case-control design of unrelated individuals for a genetic association study of addiction.  Cases   are defined as individuals with DSM-IV alcohol dependence (lifetime) and potentially other illicit drug dependence. In addition to the   categorical diagnosis, we have data on ordinal measurements of number of DSM-IV symptoms for alcohol, nicotine, marijuana,   cocaine, opiates and other drugs so that we will able to construct quantitative measurements of addiction severity over a wide   range of substances.  Controls are defined as individuals who have been exposed to alcohol (and possibly to other drugs), but   have never met lifetime diagnosis for alcohol dependence or dependence on other illicit substances.  Analyses that include   refinement of the phenotype and incorporation of important demographic and environmental factors into association   studies will be pursued.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Cases and controls were selected from three large, complementary datasets: the Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism (COGA),   the Family Study of Cocaine Dependence (FSCD), and the Collaborative Genetic Study of Nicotine Dependence (COGEND).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;COGA:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt; COGA was initiated in 1989 and is a large-scale family study that has had as its primary aim the identification of genes   that contribute to alcoholism susceptibility and related characteristics.  COGA is funded through the National Institute   on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA).  Subjects were recruited from 7 sites across the U.S. Alcohol dependent probands   were recruited from treatment facilities and assessed by personal interview.  After securing permission, other family   members were also assessed. A set of comparison families was drawn from the same communities as the   families recruited through the alcohol dependent probands. Assessment involved a comprehensive personal interview developed for this   project, the Semi-Structured Assessment for the Genetics of Alcoholism (SSAGA), which gathers detailed information on alcoholism   related symptoms along with other drugs and psychiatric symptoms. Families with three or more first-degree relatives who were   alcohol dependent were invited for more extensive testing, including neurophysiology evaluations (ERPs and EEGs) and a battery   of neuropsychological assessments.  Blood was obtained for genetic studies. Institutional Review Boards at all sites approved the   protocols, including sharing in the NIAAA national repository.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;COGA has four Co-Principal Investigators Bernice Porjesz, Victor Hesselbrock, Howard Edenberg, and Laura Bierut. COGA   includes nine different centers where data collection, analysis, and storage take place. The nine sites and Principal Investigators and    Co-investigators are: University of Connecticut (Victor Hesselbrock); Indiana University (Howard Edenberg, John Nurnberger, Jr.,    Tatiana Foroud); University of Iowa (Samuel Kuperman); SUNY Downstate (Bernice Porjesz); Washington University in St. Louis    (Laura Bierut, Alison Goate, John Rice); University of California at San Diego (Marc Schuckit); Howard University (Robert Taylor);    Rutgers University (Jay Tischfield); Southwest Foundation (Laura Almasy). Q. Max Guo serves as the NIAAA Staff Collaborator. This    national collaborative study is supported by the NIH Grant U10AA008401 from the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism    (NIAAA) and the National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Family Study of Cocaine Dependence (FSCD):&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt; This project was initiated in 2000 as a case-control family study of   cocaine dependence funded through the National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA; PI: Laura Bierut).  The primary goal was to increase the   understanding of the familial and non-familial antecedents and consequences of cocaine dependence.  Cocaine dependent individuals were   systematically recruited from chemical dependency treatment units (both public and private; residential and outpatient) in the greater   St. Louis metropolitan area.  Community based control subjects were identified through a Missouri Driver&amp;#39;s License Registry   (maintained at Washington University for research purposes) and matched by age, race, gender, and residential zip code.  As a supplement   to this project, blood samples were collected for future genetic analysis and were included in the NIDA Genetics Consortium.   Phenotypic data, DNA, and cell lines are in the NIDA Center for Genetics Studies.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Collaborative Genetic Study of Nicotine Dependence (COGEND):&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt; COGEND was initiated in 2001 as a three-part program   project grant funded through the National Cancer Institute (NCI; PI: Laura Bierut).  The three projects included a study of the familial   transmission of nicotine dependence, a genetic study of nicotine dependence, and a study of the relationship of nicotine dependence   with nicotine metabolism. The primary goal is to detect, localize, and characterize genes that predispose or protect an individual   with respect to heavy tobacco consumption, nicotine dependence, and related phenotypes and to integrate these findings with the family   transmission and nicotine metabolism findings. The primary design is a community based case-control family study. All subjects were   recruited from Detroit and St. Louis.  Nicotine dependent cases and non-dependent smoking controls were identified and recruited. In   addition, one sibling for each case and control subject was recruited in a subset of the sample. Over 56,000 subjects aged 25-44 years   were screened by telephone, over 3,100 subjects were personally interviewed, and over 2,900 donated blood samples for genetic studies.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;All three studies (COGA, COGEND, FSCD) include measures of basic socio-demographic variables, including age, sex, race/ethnicity, family   income, educational attainment, religious participation, and family structure. Other important covariates and/or potential   moderators of genetic effects include comorbid addictions and age at initiation of use for cigarettes, alcohol   and drugs. The assessments also include measures of various life stressors, such as physical and sexual abuse, which have been implicated   in gene-environment interactions for several disorders. Coding for both individual variables and indices has been standardized across   studies. All subjects were assessed in person by trained research assistants.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at the Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR),   was provided by the NIH GEI (U01HG004438), the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, the National Institute on   Drug Abuse, and the NIH contract "High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease"(HHSN268200782096C).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note for Publications Related to Study:&lt;/b&gt; The Study of Addiction: Genetics and Environment (SAGE) has not yet generated publications.   Below is a listing of publications related to the three studies from which the SAGE sample was selected.  COGA has over 228   publications listed at &lt;a href="http://www.niaaagenetics.org" target="_blank"&gt;www.niaaagenetics.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;This study is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies initiative   (GENEVA, &lt;a href="http://www.genevastudy.org" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.genevastudy.org&lt;/a&gt;) funded by the trans-NIH Genes,   Environment, and Health Initiative (GEI).  The overarching goal is to identify novel genetic factors that   contribute to addiction through a large-scale genome-wide association study of DSM-IV  alcohol dependent (and frequently illicit drug dependent) cases and non-dependent, unrelated control subjects of European and  African American descent.  Genotyping was performed at the Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR).    Data cleaning and harmonization were done at the GEI-funded GENEVA Coordinating Center at the University of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism (COGA)&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;COGA was initiated in 1989, with Henri Begleiter as the   Principal Investigator and Theodore Reich as the Co-Principal Investigator for 15 years.  In 2004, while Henri Begleiter remained the PI,   four Co-PIs were put into place: Howard Edenberg, Victor Hesselbrock, Bernice Porjesz and Laura Bierut. In 2006, the structure of the   leadership changed again, with these four scientific Co-PIs leading the project, and Bernice Porjesz additionally serving as the   Administrative PI.  In addition to Henri Begleiter and Theodore Reich, several past key members of COGA were T.K. Li, Raymond Crowe,   Wendy Reich, and C. Michael Conneally, who have moved on to new positions or have retired.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;In 1990, Phase I of COGA began, systematically ascertaining   probands in treatment within six catchment areas, located across the United States (Indiana, New York, St. Louis, Connecticut, Iowa, San   Diego). Probands met criteria for alcohol dependence based upon personal interview using the Semi-Structured Assessment for the Genetics   of Alcoholism (SSAGA), a polydiagnostic instrument developed by COGA.  Probands also had to have at least two first-degree relatives   available for evaluation.  Over the next 5 years, affected probands and family members participated in the study. During this time,   control families with the same family structure were also ascertained from the community, to be representative of the general   population; controls did not have to be unaffected individuals.  All families completed the same battery of tests. A subset of families   underwent neurophysiological assessments.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;In Phase II, between 1995 and 1999, some recruitment of new families continued, and the first follow-up protocol (5 year) was initiated.   Affected families were extended. Adult clinical interviews conducted at this time used the SSAGA-II (a slight modification of the SSAGA to meet   new diagnostic criteria).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Phase III began in 1999, and was primarily an extension of Phase II with an emphasis on recruiting high-risk families with young   children. At this same time Howard University became an additional recruitment site.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;In 2004, COGA began Phase IV, the prospective study of adolescents and young adults from pedigrees ascertained in Phases I-III, which   is ongoing. Participants are reassessed every two years.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;For more details see &lt;a href="http://zork.wustl.edu/niaaa/coga_instruments/resources" target="_blank"&gt;zork.wustl.edu/niaaa/coga_instruments/resources&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Family Study of Cocaine Dependence (FSCD)&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;FSCD was initiated in 2000 as a case-control family study of cocaine dependence.   Laura Bierut was the Principal Investigator, and the study was funded by NIDA. The primary goal of this case-control study was to   increase the understanding of the familial and non-familial antecedents and consequences of cocaine dependence. Subjects were   systematically recruited from chemical dependency treatment units (both public and private; residential and outpatient) in the greater   St. Louis metropolitan area to identify potential cocaine dependent individuals.  Subjects were required to speak English and be over   the age of 18 years.  Subjects could not have a condition that prevented them from providing informed consent or effectively   participating in the protocol (e.g., language difficulty, CNS damage, or extremely poor health).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Community based control subjects were identified through a Missouri Driver&amp;#39;s License Registry (maintained at Washington University for   research purposes) and matched by age, race, gender, and residential zip code. Zip code matching was a proxy for socioeconomic and   neighborhood matching. Control subjects were initially contacted with a recruitment letter briefly explaining the study and then screened   by telephone call.  During the phone call, the study was further described, and age, race, and gender were confirmed.  If the   community based comparison subject was dependent on any substance, a second comparison subject with no substance dependence was   recruited. To screen for substance dependence, potential control subjects were asked about maximum number of drinks consumed in a   24-hour period, which correlates strongly with alcohol dependence.  Control subjects were then recruited and thoroughly assessed to   confirm a lifetime history of no dependence on any substance.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;All subjects were assessed using the Semi-Structured Assessment for Cocaine Dependence (SSACD), a polydiagnostic instrument developed   for this project and closely based on the SSAGA.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Data collection ended in 2005; data analysis is ongoing. For more details see &lt;a href="http://fire.wustl.edu/FSCD/index.htm" target="_blank"&gt;http://fire.wustl.edu/FSCD/index.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Collaborative Genetic Study of Nicotine Dependence (COGEND)&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;COGEND was initiated in 2001 as a three-part program project   grant funded through the National Cancer Institute (PI: Laura Bierut).  The three projects included a study of the familial transmission   of nicotine dependence, a genetic study of nicotine dependence, and a study of the relationship of nicotine dependence with nicotine   metabolism. The primary goal was to detect, localize, and characterize genes that predispose or protect an individual with respect to heavy   tobacco consumption, nicotine dependence, and related phenotypes and to integrate these findings with the family transmission and   nicotine metabolism findings. The primary design was a community based case-control family study.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Nicotine dependent and control probands were recruited from the community using the Missouri Driver&amp;#39;s License Registry in St. Louis and   Health Maintenance Organization in Detroit. Nicotine dependent cases were identified during telephone screening as current smokers with a   Fagerstr&amp;#246;m Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND) score of 4 or more (maximum score of 10). Control subjects were identified during   telephone screening as smokers (individuals who smoked at least 100 cigarettes lifetime), who never had any symptoms of dependence   (lifetime FTND=0). All subjects had to be between the ages of 25 to 44 years and speak English.  Subjects could not have a condition   that prevented them from providing informed consent or effectively participating in the protocol (e.g., language difficulty, CNS damage,   or extremely poor health). In a subset of the sample, one sibling was also recruited for case and control subjects.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;All subjects were assessed using the Semi-Structured Assessment of Nicotine Dependence (SSAND), which was developed specifically for   COGEND and is modeled after the SSAGA and Composite International Diagnostic Interview (CIDI).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Data collection ended in 2007; data analysis is ongoing. For more details, see &lt;a href="http://zork.wustl.edu/cogend/" target="_blank"&gt;http://zork.wustl.edu/cogend/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Laura J. Bierut, MD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigator"><AttrName>John P. Rice, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Steering Committee"><AttrName>Naomi Breslau, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Steering Committee"><AttrName>Howard J. Edenberg, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Steering Committee"><AttrName>Alison Goate, DPhil</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Steering Committee"><AttrName>Victor Hesselbrock, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Connecticut, Farmington, CT, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Steering Committee"><AttrName>Eric Johnson, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Research Triangle Institute International, Research Triangle Park, NC, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Arpana Agrawal, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Laura Almasy, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Southwest Foundation, San Antonio, TX, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Kathleen Bucholz, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Li-Shiun Chen, MD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Robert Culverhouse, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Danielle Dick, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Tatiana Foroud, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Richard Grucza, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Dorothy Hatsukami, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Anthony Hinrichs, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>John Kramer, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Robert Krueger, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Samuel Kuperman, MD</AttrName><Institution>University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Michael Lynskey, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Rosalind Neuman, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>John I. Nurnberger, Jr., MD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Bernice Porjesz, PhD</AttrName><Institution>SUNY Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn NY, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Nancy Saccone, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Scott Saccone, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Marc A. Schuckit, MD</AttrName><Institution>University of California, San Diego, CA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Robert Taylor, MD</AttrName><Institution>Howard University, Washington, DC, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Jay A. Tischfield, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Rutgers University, Piscataway, NJ, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Collaborators"><AttrName>Jen C. Wang, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>U01 HG004422</AttrName><Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>U10 AA008401</AttrName><Institution>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism and National Institute on Drug Abuse, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>P01 CA089392</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>R01 DA013423</AttrName><Institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>R01 DA019963</AttrName><Institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><StudyURLs><Url name="&lt;b&gt;GENEVA&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;b&gt;Gene&lt;/b&gt; En&lt;b&gt;v&lt;/b&gt;ironment &lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;ssociation Studies" url="http://www.genevastudy.org"/><Url name="Genes and Environment Initiative Study of Addiction: Genetics and Environment (SAGE)" url="http://zork.wustl.edu/gei/"/></StudyURLs><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="12875050"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="12875049"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16451628"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16961766"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17982586"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15826840"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="8189735"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="10615721"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15024690"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15229186"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16385453"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16924269"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16571603"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18243582"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18065163"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17158188"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17135278"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17716221"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>U01 HG004422-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="BIERUTL" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="BIERUTL" fname="Laura" mname="J" lname="Bierut" email="laura@wustl.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012410141" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wisea2" fname="Anastasia" mname="Leigh" lname="Wise" email="wisea2@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for the Study of Addiction: Genetics and Environment (SAGE) was provided through the NIH Genes, Environment and Health Initiative [GEI] (U01 HG004422). SAGE is one of the genome-wide association studies funded as part of the Gene Environment Association Studies (GENEVA) under GEI. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype cleaning, as well as with general study coordination, was provided by the GENEVA Coordinating Center (U01 HG004446). 
Assistance with data cleaning was provided by the National Center for Biotechnology Information. Support for collection of datasets and samples was provided by the Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism (COGA; U10 AA008401), the Collaborative Genetic Study of Nicotine Dependence (COGEND; P01 CA089392), and the Family Study of Cocaine Dependence (FSCD; R01 DA013423). Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at the Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research, was provided by the NIH GEI (U01HG004438), the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, the National Institute on Drug Abuse, and the NIH contract "High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease" (HHSN268200782096C). The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/study.cgi?study_id=phs000092.v1.p1 through dbGaP accession number phs000092.v1.p. </acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="216" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Alcoholism and Related Conditions" name="ARC" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Limited to genetic studies of alcohol dependence and related conditions. Related conditions include dependence on other substances including nicotine, marijuana, and other illicit drugs (e.g., stimulants, sedatives, opiates), as well as related psychiatric conditions, limited to externalizing disorders and depression.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="217" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research" name="HR" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroupLinks><ConsentGroupLink cg_uid_from="217"><StudyTo study_uid="20653" name="dbGaP Collection: Psychiatric Genomics Consortium (PGC) dbGaP Datasets" accession="phs001254.v1"><ConsentGroupTo uid="2138" name="HR"/></StudyTo></ConsentGroupLink><ConsentGroupLink cg_uid_from="216"><StudyTo study_uid="20653" name="dbGaP Collection: Psychiatric Genomics Consortium (PGC) dbGaP Datasets" accession="phs001254.v1"><ConsentGroupTo uid="2139" name="DS-ALC-GSO-RD"/></StudyTo></ConsentGroupLink></ConsentGroupLinks></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>