<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5748" whole_study_id="5462" phs="000093" v="2" p="2" createDate="2009-10-20T13:59:30-05:00" modDate="2019-07-19T13:30:27-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-07-19T13:30:27-05:00" handle="GENEVA_LungCancer" num_participants="5588"><StudyInfo accession="phs000093.v2.p2" parentAccession="phs000093.v2.p2"><BioProject id="PRJNA75585" entrez_id="75585" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75587" entrez_id="75587" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>GENEVA GWAS of Lung Cancer and Smoking</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The majority of cases of lung cancer are the culmination of a dynamic process that begins with smoking initiation, proceeds through   dependency and smoking persistence, continues with lung cancer development and ends with progression to disseminated   disease or response to therapy and survival. We are conducting a whole genome study of lung cancer and smoking   to examine critical steps in lung cancer progression.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;This study is a genome-wide association study (GWAS) to investigate the genetic determinants of lung cancer risk. The study   design efficiently allows identification of genes that also contribute to smoking persistence and outcome from lung cancer   using a single GWAS of 5,900 subjects using the primary GENEVA dataset, derived from two studies. The first is the &lt;b&gt;E&lt;/b&gt;nvironment   &lt;b&gt;a&lt;/b&gt;nd &lt;b&gt;G&lt;/b&gt;enetics in &lt;b&gt;L&lt;/b&gt;ung Cancer &lt;b&gt;E&lt;/b&gt;tiology Study (EAGLE), a population-based, biologically intensive, case-control   study from the Lombardy region of Italy including ~2000 newly diagnosed lung cancer cases and ~2000 age-, gender- and region- matched   controls. The second is the &lt;b&gt;P&lt;/b&gt;rostate, &lt;b&gt;L&lt;/b&gt;ung, &lt;b&gt;C&lt;/b&gt;olon and &lt;b&gt;O&lt;/b&gt;vary Study (PLCO) Cancer Screening Trial from   which we have selected ~850 lung cancer cases and ~850 controls, also matched on age and gender. Understanding the basis for   the well-established hereditary component of lung cancer and smoking persistence could provide new insights into etiology,   prevention, and treatment, and have an enormous impact on public health.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The same GWAS genotyping data in the two studies will be used to investigate the genetic determinants of smoking persistence.   Specifically, we will analyze current smokers and former smokers from EAGLE and PLCO for diverse smoking phenotypes, including   persistence of smoking as well as ever/never smoking comparisons, quitting attempts, and the Fagerstr&amp;#246;m index of tobacco addiction.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;PLCO participants are all European-Americans and EAGLE involves subjects from Italy.&lt;br/&gt;   EAGLE is a case-control study and contains 3937 phenotyped subjects.&lt;br/&gt;   PLCO is a screening trial with a cohort design and contains 1651 phenotyped subjects.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;This study is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies initiative    (GENEVA, &lt;a href="http://www.genevastudy.org" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.genevastudy.org&lt;/a&gt;) funded by the trans-NIH Genes,    Environment, and Health Initiative (GEI).  The overarching goal is to identify novel    genetic factors that contribute to lung cancer and smoking through large-scale genome-wide association studies of    population-based samples of lung cancer cases and controls.  Genotyping was performed at the Johns Hopkins University    Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR).  Data cleaning and harmonization were done at the GEI-funded GENEVA    Coordinating Center at the University of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;EAGLE&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;EAGLE is a large population-based case-control study designed and conducted to investigate the genetic and environmental determinants   of lung cancer and smoking persistence using an integrative approach that allows combined analysis of genetic, environmental, clinical,   and behavioral data.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The study includes over 2,000 incident lung cancer cases, both males and females of Italian nationality, ages 35 to 79 years old,   with verified lung cancer of any histological type, and over 2,000 healthy population-based controls matched to cases by age, gender,   and residence. The participation rate was high: 85% and 73% in cases and controls, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Lung cancer cases were enrolled from 13 hospitals within the Lombardy region of Italy. The healthy controls were randomly   selected from the same residential area of the lung cancer cases. The study setting, the Lombardy region of Italy, is served by   a network of modern hospitals, medical schools, and a regional health service. Within the Lombardy region, the catchment&amp;#39;s area   includes 5 cities and 216 surrounding municipalities, encompassing, in the selected age range, over 1.3 million people. &lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Extensive epidemiological data have been collected through both an interview-based computer-assisted questionnaire and a   self-administered questionnaire. Available data includes demographical characteristics, detailed smoking history (active and passive),   family history of lung cancer and other cancers, previous lung diseases, medications, diet, alcohol, attempts at quitting smoking,   anxiety, depression, personality scores, occupation, reproductive and residential history.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Clinical data (stage, grade, histology, imaging and pathology reports, spirometry, and routine laboratory studies) were recorded.   All study subjects donated a blood sample (or, rarely, a buccal rinse sample), which was processed to obtain cryopreserved   lymphocytes, RBC, granulocytes, DNA, RNA, whole blood, buffy coat, serum, plasma, and blood cards. Lung tissue paraffin blocks and   slides were collected from the cases who underwent surgery, biopsy or cytological examination of the lung tumor. Multiple   fresh "normal" lung tissue and tumor samples, frozen in liquid nitrogen within 20 minutes of excision, were also collected from   over 500 surgical cases.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;All data and biospecimen information are stored in a secure relational database. Quality control procedures were implemented   to ensure accuracy, completeness, and privacy of the data collected. Genetic and epidemiological studies are ongoing. This   study will help answer many questions related to lung cancer etiology in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;PLCO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The Prostate, Lung, Colorectal and Ovarian Cancer Screening Trial (PLCO) is a multi-center clinical trial sponsored by the   National Cancer Institute. The purpose of the PLCO Trial is to determine whether certain cancer screening tests reduce deaths   from these cancers of the prostate, lung, colorectum, and ovaries. Together, these four cancers account for about 60% of   all diagnosed cancers in the United States. Enrollment opened in 1993 and ended in 2001, with over 155,000 men and women   participating at 10 locations throughout the United States. Blood specimens are collected from screened participants, buccal   cell DNA from controls, and histology slides from cases; these are maintained in a biorepository. Participants complete   a baseline questionnaire (covering health status and risk factors) and a dietary questionnaire. More than 12,000 participants   were enrolled in the pilot phase (concluded in September 1994). Data were scanned into on-site computers for uploading by   participant identification number to the coordinating center for quality checks, archival storage, and preparation of analysis   datasets for use by the National Cancer Institute (NCI). Scientific direction is provided by NCI scientists, trial   investigators, external consultants, and there is an independent data safety and monitoring board. Performance and data quality   are monitored via data edits, site visits, random record audits, and teleconferences.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Neil Caporaso</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Maria Teresa Landi</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Genetic Epidemiologists"><AttrName>Lynn Goldin</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Genetic Epidemiologists"><AttrName>Alisa Goldstein</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Genomics"><AttrName>Stephen Chanock</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Core Genotyping Facility, Advanced Technology Center, Gaithersburg , MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Genomics"><AttrName>Gilles Thomas</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Core Genotyping Facility, Advanced Technology Center, Gaithersburg , MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Genomics"><AttrName>Andrew Bergen</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Core Genotyping Facility, Advanced Technology Center, Gaithersburg , MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Statisticians"><AttrName>Nilanjan Chatterjee</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Statisticians"><AttrName>Sholom Wacholder</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Statisticians"><AttrName>Kai Yu</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Clinical Experts and Coordination"><AttrName>Margaret Tucker</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Clinical Experts and Coordination"><AttrName>Joseph F. Fraumeni, Jr</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Clinical Experts and Coordination"><AttrName>Demetrius Albanes (ATBC)</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Clinical Experts and Coordination"><AttrName>Martin Oken (PLCO)</AttrName><Institution>University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Clinical Experts and Coordination"><AttrName>Pier Alberto Bertazzi</AttrName><Institution>University of Milan, Milan, Italy</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>A GWAS of Lung Cancer in a Comprehensive Population-Based Design (RFA-HG-06-033)</AttrName><Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><StudyURLs><Url name="PLCO" url="http://prevention.cancer.gov/programs-resources/groups/ed/programs/plco"/><Url name="EAGLE" url="http://dceg.cancer.gov/eagle/index.html"/></StudyURLs><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18538025"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18297132"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16368945"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17497175"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="11189688"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="11189684"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>ZO1 CP010200</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="0010062217" aid="1" auth="cit" login="caporasn" fname="Neil" mname="E" lname="Caporaso" email="caporasn@epndce.nci.nih.gov"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010091613" aid="1" auth="cit" login="manoliot" fname="Teri" mname="A" lname="Manolio" email="manoliot@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011217741" aid="1" auth="cit" login="tobiasg" fname="Geoffrey" mname="Scott" lname="Tobias" email="tobiasg@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS:  This study has not provided a suggested acknowledgement statement. However, Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (GSR are sensitive according to the Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="106" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Research related to adult diseases and methods" name="CADM" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>The informed consent document signed by the PLCO study participants allows use of these data by investigators for discovery and hypothesis generation in the investigation of the genetic contributions to cancer and other adult diseases as well as development of novel analytical approaches for GWAS.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="107" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Research related to smoking or lung disease" name="SLD" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the dataset is limited to scientific genetic research related to the etiology, molecular basis, and outcome of lung disease and smoking.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><AdditionalEmails><Email>caporasn@mail.nih.gov</Email><Email>landim@mail.nih.gov</Email></AdditionalEmails></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="5462" whole_study_id="5462" phs="000093" v="1" p="1" createDate="2008-12-12T16:06:43-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T09:53:51-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T09:53:51-05:00" num_participants="5588"><StudyInfo accession="phs000093.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000093.v1.p1"><StudyNameEntrez>GENEVA GWAS of Lung Cancer and Smoking</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Funding>ZO1 CP010200</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="0010062217" aid="1" auth="cit" login="caporasn" fname="Neil" mname="E" lname="Caporaso" email="caporasn@epndce.nci.nih.gov"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010091613" aid="1" auth="cit" login="manoliot" fname="Teri" mname="A" lname="Manolio" email="manoliot@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=5668&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="Lung DUC.doc" md5="6982f93e02db76bc539d6689cc26e0e4" size="53760" modDate="2009-07-23T14:34:02-05:00" content-type="application/msword"/></DUC><DUC_PDF><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=16546&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="Lung DUC.doc.pdf" md5="4deafb2d5f8c1e6abb9f687a7e88cc83" size="98530" modDate="2015-08-31T15:58:14-05:00" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="35" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Cancer and other diseases in adults only (PLCO)" name="PLCO" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the dataset is limited to scientific genetic research related to cancer and other diseases appropriate to the age group.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="36" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Research related to smoking or lung disease (EAGLE)" name="EAGLE" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the dataset is limited to scientific genetic research related to the etiology, molecular basis, and outcome of lung disease and smoking.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><AdditionalEmails><Email>caporasn@mail.nih.gov</Email><Email>landim@mail.nih.gov</Email></AdditionalEmails></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>