<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5546" whole_study_id="5546" phs="000142" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-04-20T15:47:37-05:00" modDate="2018-06-19T11:33:22-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2018-06-19T11:33:22-05:00" handle="CIDR_MyopiaGlaucoma"><StudyInfo accession="phs000142.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000142.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75493" entrez_id="75493" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75495" entrez_id="75495" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>NEI:Myopia and Glaucoma Risk Factors at CIDR</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Myopia and glaucoma are highly prevalent ophthalmic disorders worldwide and contribute significantly to ocular morbidity.  There

 is substantial evidence that genetic factors play a significant role in the development of non-syndromic myopia and glaucoma.  We propose to

 perform mapping studies for well-characterized twin populations in the United Kingdom and Australia in order to ultimately identify implicated

 genes for these disorders and related ocular parameters.  This will provide a fundamental molecular understanding of how these disorders

 develop, and may lead to directed physiologic (i.e. pharmacologic, gene therapy) interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;Our aim is to dissect the genetic basis of the eye disorders myopia and glaucoma. Instead of limited analyses of the trait/disease in

 a dichotomous manner, we are using continuous phenotypes of measures of refraction and intermediate phenotypes of glaucoma to analyze quantitative

 traits in unselected population samples of volunteer twins. Achievement of this goal requires cooperative efforts and large sample sizes.

 Thus, we have created an international collaboration of large complementary studies.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;We have performed classic twin studies (comparing monozygotic [MZ] correlations with DZ correlations to determine heritability) for myopia

   and glaucoma by analyzing quantitative traits including: refraction, axial eye length, CCT, intraocular pressure (IOP), optic disc

   area, and optic disc cup area using twins from the Australian Twin Registry and the TwinsUK Adult Twin Registry.&lt;/p&gt;

   &lt;p&gt;We have performed comprehensive ophthalmic examination of 800 DZ twin pairs (500 in Queensland and 300 in Tasmania), and 2000 DZ

   twin pairs and 1000 MZ samples in the UK for glaucoma and myopia endophenotypes.  These subjects have been consented for DNA genetic study.&lt;/p&gt;

   &lt;p&gt;We wish to conduct the CIDR SNP WGA scan on all of these individuals, and analyze these SNP data in both linkage and association

   studies, to identify regions of the human genome likely to contain loci that influence variation in these measurements.  The goal

   is to identify the genes in these loci associated with a particular trait.  We will also compare and analyze the genes and loci

   identified by this twin genome-wide scan with other myopia and glaucoma mapping and gene discovery studies. These include the 280

   multiplex pedigrees of the International Myopia Consortium (Dr. Young-PI) and the Glaucoma Inheritance Study in Tasmania

   (Dr. Mackey-PI), with over 400 glaucoma pedigrees and 2000 cases of glaucoma.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Terri L. Young, MD</AttrName><Institution>Duke University Eye Center and the Center for Human Genetics, Durham, NC, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>David A. Mackey, MD</AttrName><Institution>University of Melbourne Department of Ophthalmology, Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital, East Melbourne, Australia</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Nicholas G. Martin, Ph.D</AttrName><Institution>Genetic Epidemiology Laboratory, Queensland Institute of Medical Research, Royal Brisbane Hospital, Brisbane, Australia</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Christopher J. Hammond, MD</AttrName><Institution>Twin Research and Genetic Epidemiology Unit, King's College London, London, United Kingdom</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Tim Spector, MD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>UK Twin Research Unit, St. Thomas' Hospital, London, United Kingdom</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Toby Andrew, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, Imperial College, London, United Kingdom</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Yi-Ju Li, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Statistical Genetics, Duke Center for Human Genetics, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Peter Visscher, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Genetic Epidemiology Laboratory, Queensland Institute of Medical Research, Royal Brisbane Hospital, Brisbane, Australia</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping"><AttrName>HHSN268200782096C. NIH contract "High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease"</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15307048"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16186354"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15671282"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="14691154"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="12537873"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="11734523"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="9634508"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="9792869"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="12714612"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15980214"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17327828"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="11836361"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="12376937"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15291966"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="10777361"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="14741004"/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="MacKinnon JR, Brown S, Poulsen J, Hammond CJ, Mackey DA" title="Genetic influence on intraocular pressure in children: the Twins Eye Study in Tasmania" journal="Invest Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci. 2004;45:e-abstract 4390"/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="Poulsen JL, Brown SA, Kearns LS, Scotter LW, Hewitt AW, MacKinnon JR, Toh TY, Hammond CJ, Mackey DA" title="Heritability of Optic Disc Morphology in the Australian Twins Eye Studies" journal="Invest Ophthalmol.Vis.Sci. 2005;46:e-abstract 1092"/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="Sorsby A, Sheridan M, Leary GA" title="Refraction and its components in twins" journal="London, Her Majesty's Stationery Office. Medical Research Council Special Report Series. 1962;303:1-43"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>R01 EY018246-02</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/><IC id="2" name="NEI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="YOUNGT" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="YOUNGT" fname="Terri" mname="LOIS" lname="Young" email="tyoung6@wisc.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN-MADISONCHILDREN'S HOSP OF PHILADELPHIADUKE UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010146067" aid="1" auth="cit" login="chinh" fname="Hemin" mname="R" lname="Chin" email="hc7v@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010162544" aid="1" auth="cit" login="sheng" fname="Grace" mname="L" lname="Shen" email="sheng@nei.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="2 months"><acknowledgement_statement>
The Requestor agrees to acknowledge the TES and the TES Research Group in all oral and written presentations, disclosures, and publications resulting from any analyses of the TES Project Dataset(s).  The Requestor further agrees that the acknowledgment shall include:  1) a reference to the specific version of the TES Project Dataset(s) analyzed; and 2) a sample statement to be used in all acknowledgments  &#8220;The dataset(s) used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from the  &#8220;A Whole Genome Association Scan for Myopia and Glaucoma Endophenotypes using Twin Studies&#8221;  database in dbGaP.  Funding support for this study was provided by the Wellcome Trust, Guide Dogs for the Blind Association (UK), NHMRC (350415), the Ophthalmic Research Institute of Australia, the Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust, the National Glaucoma Research Organization, the American Health Assistance Foundation, and the National Eye Institute (R01EY018246).  We would like to thank the participants and the TES Research Group for their valuable contributions to this research.&#8221; 
</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="63" CGType="cg_class_other" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="52" dac_name="NEI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Twins Eye Study of Refractive Error and Glaucoma Endophenotypes (TES) participant consented to general research use. </Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>