<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5511" whole_study_id="5511" phs="000103" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-03-17T16:23:29-05:00" completedByGPADate="2018-05-17T10:51:15-05:00" modDate="2020-01-21T13:41:14-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-01-21T13:41:14-05:00" handle="GEI_PretermBirth_Murray" num_participants="3840"><StudyInfo accession="phs000103.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000103.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75461" entrez_id="75461" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75463" entrez_id="75463" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>GENEVA GWAS of Prematurity and its Complications - European Ancestry</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType></StudyTypes><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Preterm labor resulting in the delivery of a premature child is a complex problem with an enormous impact on individuals,   families and society. An estimated 500,000 children are born prematurely in the U.S. each year, and 5 million worldwide die   annually of prematurity and its complications. Prematurity is also the single largest contributor to disability-adjusted   life years, a measure of the lifetime impact of a disease. Despite the importance of the problem and its disproportionate   occurrence in poor and minority populations, its underlying etiology (or etiologies) remains unknown; the single best   predictor for preterm delivery is a previous preterm birth. The largest single cause of prematurity is spontaneous preterm labor,   and suspected triggers for this include infection, stress, poor nutrition and genetic factors. Family and twin studies provide   strong evidence that genetic factors underlie about 40% of the risk for prematurity. A major challenge in studying genetic   factors in prematurity is maternal/uterine factors, fetal/placental factors, or both may influence risk. Thus, any approach to   studying preterm birth should account for both infant and maternal risk, environmental covariates and interactions. The Danish   National Birth Cohort (DNBC) is a well-established, prospective cohort that enrolled women early in pregnancy, prior to   any adverse pregnancy outcomes, to minimize bias in data collection and sampling. See details at:   &lt;a href="http://www.ssi.dk/English" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.ssi.dk/English&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The DNBC followed over 100,000 pregnancies beginning in the first trimester and has extensive biological material and   epidemiologic data on health outcomes in both mother and child. The current study posted on dbGaP contains data from a   genome-wide case/control study using approximately 1,000 preterm mother-child pairs from the DNBC most with spontaneous   onset of labor or preterm premature rupture of membranes (PPROM), along with 1,000 control pairs where the child was born   at ~40 weeks&amp;#39; gestation. After data cleaning some small changes in case/control status and other variables resulted   in minor changes in numbers of cases or controls in certain categories. Environmental variables are being used as   covariates in the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;To replicate positive findings, we are using additional mother-child pairs from the DNBC and from the general   Danish population, as well as 2200 samples coming primarily from an African-American population known to have high rates   of preterm labor and delivery. This group includes over 1000 mostly very low birthweight infants, over 500 infant term   controls, 326 term mother/baby pairs and 180 preterm mother/baby pairs. The  data from these additional cohorts will be   available in separate dbGaP postings. The study is expected to yield a better understanding of the biology of parturition,   identify common genetic factors that play a role in preterm birth and its complications and suggest environmental   modifications that can prolong gestation, with the goal of improving both neonatal and adult outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;This study is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies initiative   (GENEVA, &lt;a href="http://www.genevastudy.org" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.genevastudy.org&lt;/a&gt;) funded by the trans-NIH Genes,   Environment, and Health Initiative (GEI).  The overarching goal is to identify novel genetic factors   that contribute to prematurity and its complications through large-scale genome-wide association studies of a   well-characterized cohort of Danish mothers and babies.  Genotyping was performed at the Johns Hopkins University   Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR).  Data cleaning and harmonization were done at the GEI-funded GENEVA   Coordinating Center at the University of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Jeffrey C. Murray</AttrName><Institution>Department of Pediatrics, University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Mads Melbye</AttrName><Institution>Statens Serum Institute,Copenhagen, Denmark</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Mary Marazita</AttrName><Institution>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>NIH HD-004423-01 Genome-wide Association Studies of Prematurity and Its Complications</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>NIH HD-052953 Identification of Maternal and Fetal Genetic Factors in Preterm Birth</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping"><AttrName>U01HG004438-01. NIH GEI grant "JH/CIDR Genotyping for Genome-Wide Association Studies"</AttrName><Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>U01-HG-004423</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="JMURRAY" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="JMURRAY" fname="Jeffrey" mname="C" lname="Murray" email="jeff-murray@uiowa.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF IOWA</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012410141" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wisea2" fname="Anastasia" mname="Leigh" lname="Wise" email="wisea2@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for the GWAS of Prematurity and its Complications study was provided through the NIH Genes, Environment and Health Initiative [GEI] (U01HG004423). The GWAS of Prematurity and its Complications study is one of the genome-wide association studies funded as part of the Gene Environment Association Studies (GENEVA) under GEI. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype cleaning, as well as with general study coordination, was provided by the GENEVA Coordinating Center (U01 HG004446). Assistance with data cleaning was provided by the National Center for Biotechnology Information. Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at the Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research, was provided by the NIH GEI (U01HG004438) and the NIH contract "High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&#8221; (HHSN268200782096C).  The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?db=gap through dbGaP accession number phs000103.v1.p1.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="96" CGType="cg_class_other" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>No limitations</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>