<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5536" whole_study_id="5536" phs="000171" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-04-03T14:20:48-05:00" modDate="2019-07-19T13:30:24-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-07-19T13:30:24-05:00" handle="GeneMSA" num_participants="1880"><StudyInfo accession="phs000171.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000171.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75473" entrez_id="75473" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75475" entrez_id="75475" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>A Case-Controlled Study for genotype-Phenotype Associations in Multiple Sclerosis (Genetic Multiple Sclerosis - GeneMSA)</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;This is a multi-centre, case-controlled study to develop a dataset containing 1000 MS cases and 1000 matched controls and to   associate DNA sequence (allelic) variations with MS phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Study subjects were enrolled through a prospective effort initiated in 2003. Three MS clinical centres were involved in subject    recruitment and biological specimen collection using identical inclusion/exclusion criteria, two in Europe (Vrije Universiteit Medical   Center, Amsterdam; and University Hospital Basel) and one in the US (University of California San Francisco). This study recruited subjects   of northern-European ancestry with a diagnosis of MS   (&lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11456302" target="_blank"&gt;McDonald et al., 2001&lt;/a&gt;), with dissemination in time and space.   Patients with Clinically Isolated Syndromes (CIS) were also included if they fulfilled 3 of the 4 Barkhof criteria for dissemination in space as   per application of the McDonald criteria (&lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11456302" target="_blank"&gt;McDonald et al., 2001&lt;/a&gt;).   While recruitment predominantly included subjects with a relapsing onset   of MS, individuals with all clinical subtypes of the disease participated, including clinically isolated syndrome (CIS), relapsing   remitting MS (RRMS), secondary progressive MS (SPMS), primary progressive MS (PPMS), and progressive relapsing MS (PRMS).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The control group consisted of unrelated individuals, primarily spouses/partners, friends, and other volunteers. Control subjects   were of northern-European ancestry and matched as a group, proportionally with cases according to age (&amp;#177;5 years) and gender.   A familial history or current diagnosis of MS as well as a relation to another case or control subject were considered exclusionary   for this group.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Protocols were approved by the Committees on Human Research at all Institutions and informed consent was obtained from all   participants prior to participation in the study.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Primary Study Objective:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To identify DNA sequence variations (genotype) and flanking sequences that    are associated with clinical factors (phenotype) which differ between study subjects with and without MS.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Secondary Study Objectives:&lt;/b&gt;   &lt;ol&gt;    &lt;li&gt;To develop a clinical dataset including quantitative measures of 1000 well-characterized cases with MS, and 1000 ethnically matched    controls.&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;To identify other genotype-phenotype associations in MS study subjects such as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) measures of    disease burden and/or severity.&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;To identify or confirm candidate surrogate markers of neurodegeneration using a variety of techniques including biochemical    assays, blood transcriptome analysis, plasma proteomics and MRI*.&lt;/li&gt;   &lt;/ol&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Genotyping&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Genotyping of the complete dataset was performed at the Illumina facilities using the Sentrix&amp;#174; HumanHap550   BeadChip.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;*MRI results are not available on dbGaP.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Ludwig Kappos, MD</AttrName><Institution>University Hospital Basel, Basel, Switzerland</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Chris Polman, MD</AttrName><Institution>Free University Medical Centre, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Steven Hauser, MD</AttrName><Institution>University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Jorge Oksenberg, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigator"><AttrName>Sergio E. Baranzini, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19010793"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17660530"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19286671"/></Publication></Publications></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="7" name="NINDS" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="HAUSERS" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="HAUSERS" fname="Stephen" mname="L" lname="Hauser" email="stephen.hauser@ucsf.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN FRANCISCO</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010563438" aid="1" auth="cit" login="utzu" fname="Ursula" mname="" lname="Utz" email="utzu@ninds.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010146585" aid="1" auth="cit" login="zhangr" fname="Ran" mname="" lname="Zhang" email="zhangr@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS:  This study has not provided a suggested acknowledgement statement. However, Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.</acknowledgement_statement><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="54" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Multiple Sclerosis Genetics research" name="MSG" dac_uid="53" dac_name="NINDS" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>The informed consent documents signed by the GeneMSA study participants allows use of these data only for multiple sclerosis genetic research ( i.e. not for other diseases, even co-morbid diseases, and only for genetics).  </Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>