<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5542" whole_study_id="5542" phs="000187" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-04-15T14:07:42-05:00" modDate="2019-05-07T10:39:09-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-05-07T10:39:09-05:00" handle="GENEVA_Melanoma" num_participants="3000"><StudyInfo accession="phs000187.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000187.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75477" entrez_id="75477" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75479" entrez_id="75479" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>High Density SNP Association Analysis of Melanoma: Case-Control and  Outcomes Investigation</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;This research builds upon an extensive resource of melanoma cases and hospital based controls collected over several years  at the U.T. M.D. Anderson Cancer Center.  The goal of this research is to identify novel susceptibility and outcome-related  genes for melanoma using a systematic genome-wide association-based approach.   Our goal is to conduct high-density SNP  association and outcome studies.   This dbGaP study contains samples from 2000 European ancestry cases and 1000 European ancestry controls using the  Illumina OMNI1-Quad SNP chip.   As a part of an ongoing R01 project, we have epidemiological data together with  candidate gene results for 1000 of the melanoma cases and the controls. With regard to the outcome aspect of our design,  as part of our melanoma Specialized Program of Research Excellence (SPORE) grant, our MelCore database contains comprehensive,  prospectively maintained clinical information from all melanoma patients included in the study cohort, including primary  tumor histopathology and staging information, standard and investigational blood tumor markers, details of surgical and  systemic therapies, and extensive follow-up information, including time to relapse or recurrence, pattern of recurrence  and survival duration.   Finally, we intend to collaborate with the GenoMEL collaboration so we can jointly evaluate  each other&amp;#39;s findings.  The goal of our analysis will be to identify novel genetic factors predisposing the  development of melanoma, as well as genetic factors controlling melanoma stage at presentation, recurrence and  progression.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;This study is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies initiative   (GENEVA, &lt;a href="http://www.genevastudy.org" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.genevastudy.org&lt;/a&gt;) funded by the trans-NIH Genes,   Environment, and Health Initiative (GEI).  The overarching goal is to identify novel   genetic factors that contribute to melanoma through large-scale genome-wide association studies of 2000 European ancestry   cases and 1000 European ancestry controls.  Genotyping was performed at the Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited   Disease Research (CIDR).  Data cleaning and harmonization were done at the GEI-funded GENEVA Coordinating Center   at the University of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;We are proposing to include all cases from M.D. Anderson Cancer Center who have documented invasive melanomas and available  DNA.  Tables 1 and 2 provide demographic data on cases seen at M.D. Anderson Cancer Center for whom the SPORE or Dr. Wei&amp;#39;s  grant have collected both DNA samples and data.  There is currently a total of 2159 melanoma cancer cases with DNA available  using samples from both Dr. Wei&amp;#39;s and the melanoma SPORE and both projects are continuing to accrue subjects. The mean and  median age at diagnosis for cases in the combined melamoma R01/SPORE was 50.9, which is about 6 years younger than the mean  age of 57 reported by SEER (&lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18408748" target="_blank"&gt;Lachiewicz et al., 2008&lt;/a&gt;).    Among the R01/SPORE patients, the median primary Breslow tumor thickness was 1.1 mm (range 0.1-99) and 15% of patients   had ulcerated primary tumors.  Sentinel lymph node biopsy was performed in 98% of patients presenting with localized melanoma;   of these, 20.3% had positive sentinel lymph nodes.  The patients in the combined R01/SPORE dataset have a median follow-up   of 35 months (mean 36); 346 (19%) have developed a melanoma recurrence and 193 (11%) have died. 2.8% of patients have had   more than one primary melanoma and 2.6% presented with unknown primary melanoma. Sample acquisition has been a major focus   for the SPORE and the melanoma program, in general.  There are currently 6699 Paraffin-embedded blocks, 2878 snap-frozen   samples, 3200 OCT-preserved samples (that can be used for RNA studies) and 83 new melanoma tumor lines.  These samples   can be used for follow-up and correlative analyses for loci that are identified.  Data are maintained in the MelCore database   which was established in part through an institutional grant and maintains information on 8976 patients.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;  &lt;table width="100%" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="5"&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;td width="50%"&gt;  &lt;b&gt;Table 1: &lt;/b&gt;Staging information  &lt;table border="1"&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Staging&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Frequency&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Percent&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;AMP Only&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;0.11&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;I&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;970&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;53.98&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;I/II&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;153&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;8.51&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;II&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;295&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;16.42&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;III&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;343&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;19.09&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;IV&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;1.06&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;In-Situ&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;0.83&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Unknown&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;360&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;/table&gt;  &lt;/td&gt;   &lt;td width="50%"&gt;  &lt;b&gt;Table 2: &lt;/b&gt;Ethnicity of cases  &lt;table border="1"&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;    &lt;th colspan="3"&gt;RACE&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;RACE&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Frequency&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Percent&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;White&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;2109&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;97.7&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Hispanic&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Asian&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;0.1&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Black&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Unknown&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;tr&gt;  &lt;th&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;td&gt;2159&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;/table&gt;  &lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;/table&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;For the R01 population that has been assembled by Dr. Wei, the mean age at onset is 52 years of age.  Of those meeting criteria  and consenting to the study, 99% are non-Hispanic.  Tables 1 and 2 of the manuscript of Li et al. (2007) contains detailed  information about the melanoma risk factors that have been identified in the R01 population for the cases and controls that  will be genotyped.  Of individuals studied, 64% of the cases are male and 67% of the controls are male and 20% of cases  and 18% of controls show household incomes of $35,000 or less. Cases and controls were well matched with respect to demographic  factors.  Risk factors for melanoma included blond or red hair (OR=2.15), Blue eye color (OR=2.09), moderate or poor skin  tanning (OR=1.9), lifetime sun burning (OR=1.55), atypical nevi (OR=7.78), frecking as a child (OR=1.55), and having a first  degree relative with cancer (OR=1.42).  In tables 1 and 2 above, 360 cases that were accrued by Dr. Wei do not have staging  information yet retrieved as they were accrued before the SPORE/Melcore database was established, but these data will be  retrieved from the medical charts.  R01 cases and controls respond to a detailed questionnaire about their sun exposure  patterns, skin type, hair color, history of moles, family history of cancers and SES.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Christopher Amos, PhD</AttrName><Institution>U.T. M.D. Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Qingyi Wei, MD</AttrName><Institution>U.T. M.D. Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Jeffrey E. Lee, MD</AttrName><Institution>U.T. M.D. Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>R01CA100264</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>P50CA093459</AttrName><Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping"><AttrName>HHSN268200782096C. "NIH contract High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease"</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18183598"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18563783"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>R01 CA133996-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="CIAMOS" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="CIAMOS" fname="Christopher" mname="I." lname="Amos" email="chrisa@bcm.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>DARTMOUTH COLLEGEBAYLOR COLLEGE OF MEDICINE</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012269563" aid="1" auth="cit" login="schullys" fname="Sheri" mname="Dixon" lname="Schully" email="schullys@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001203526" aid="1" auth="cit" login="cagaananef" fname="Emilie" mname="Charlisse F" lname="Caga-Anan" email="charlisse.caga-anan@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Research support to collect data and develop an application to support this project was provided by 3P50CA093459, 5P50CA097007, 5R01ES011740, and 5R01CA133996.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="134" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>