<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="23351" whole_study_id="6239" phs="000284" v="2" p="1" createDate="2017-01-30T10:24:47-05:00" completedByGPADate="2017-02-02T11:33:48-05:00" modDate="2022-01-25T16:16:14-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-01-25T16:16:14-05:00" handle="CFS" num_participants="704"><StudyInfo accession="phs000284.v2.p1" parentAccession="phs000284.v2.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75725" entrez_id="75725" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75727" entrez_id="75727" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>NHLBI Cleveland Family Study (CFS) Candidate Gene Association Resource (CARe)</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="cloud_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType></StudyTypes><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The Cleveland Family Study is the largest family-based study of sleep apnea world-wide, consisting of 2284 individuals   (46% African American) from 361 families studied on up to 4 occasions over a period of 16 years. The study was begun in 1990   with the initial aims of quantifying the familial aggregation of sleep apnea.  NIH renewals provided expansion of the   original cohort (including increased minority recruitment) and longitudinal follow-up, with the last exam occurring   in February 2006. Index probands (n=275) were recruited from 3 area hospital sleep labs if they had a confirmed   diagnosis of sleep apnea and at least 2 first-degree relatives available to be studied.  In the first 5 years of   the study, neighborhood control probands (n=87) with at least 2 living relatives available for study were selected   at random from a list provided by the index family and also studied. All available first degree relatives and spouses   of the case and control probands also were recruited. Second-degree relatives, including half-sibs, aunts, uncles and   grandparents, were also included if they lived near the first degree relatives (cases or controls), or if the family   had been found to have two or more relatives with sleep apnea.  Blood was sampled and DNA isolated for participants   seen in the last two exam cycles (n=1447). The sample, which is enriched with individuals with sleep apnea, also   contains a high prevalence of individuals with sleep apnea-related traits, including: obesity, impaired glucose   tolerance, and HTN.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Phenotyping data have been collected over 4 exam cycles, each occurring ~every 4 years. The last three exams   targeted all subjects who had been studied at earlier exams, as well as new minority families and family members   of previously studied probands who had been unavailable at prior exams. Data from one, two, three and four visits   are available for 412, 630, 329 and 67, participants, respectively.  In the first 3 exams, participants underwent   overnight in-home sleep studies, allowing determination of the number and duration of hypopneas and apneas, sleep   period, heart rate, and oxygen saturation levels; anthropometry (weight, height, and waist, hip, and neck circumferences);   resting blood pressure; spirometry; standardized questionnaire evaluation of symptoms, medications, sleep patterns,   quality of life, daytime sleepiness measures and health history; venipuncture and measurement of total and HDL   cholesterol. The 4th exam (2001-2006) was designed to collect more detailed measurements of sleep, metabolic and   CVD phenotypes and included measurement of state-of-the-art polysomnography, with both collection of blood and   measurement of blood pressure before and after sleep, and anthropometry, upper airway assessments, spirometry,   exhaled nitric oxide, and ECG performed the morning after the sleep study.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Data have been collected by trained research assistants or GCRC nurses following written Manuals of Procedures   who were certified following standard approaches for each study procedure. Ongoing data quality, with assessment of   within or between individual drift, has been monitored on an ongoing basis, using statistical techniques as well as   regular re-certification procedures. Between and within scorer reliabilities for key sleep apnea indices have been   excellent, with intra-class correlation coefficients (ICCs) exceeding 0.92 for the apnea-hypopnea index (AHI). Sleep staging, assessed with   epoch specific comparisons, also demonstrate excellent reliability for stage identification (kappas&amp;gt;0.82). There has   been no evidence of significant time trends-between or within scorers- for the AHI variables. We also have evaluated   the night-to-night variability of the AHI and other sleep variables in 91 subjects, with each measurement made 1-3   months apart. There is high night to night consistency for the AHI (ICC: 0.80), the arousal index (0.76), and   the % sleep time in slow-wave sleep (0.73). We have demonstrated the comparability of the apnea estimates (AHI)   determined from limited channel studies obtained at in-home settings with in full in-laboratory polysomnography.   In addition to our published validation study, we more recently compared the AHI in 169 Cleveland Family Study   participants undergoing both assessments (in-home and in-laboratory) within one week apart. These showed excellent   levels of agreement (ICC=0.83), demonstrating the feasibility of examining data from either in-home or in-laboratory   studies for apnea phenotyping. Data collected in the GCRC were obtained, when possible, with comparable, if not   identical techniques, as were the same measures collected at prior exams performed in the participants&amp;#39; homes. To   address the comparability of data collected over different exams, we calculated the crude age-adjusted   correlations ~3 year within individual correlations between measures made in the most recent GCRC exam with   measures made in a prior exam and demonstrated excellent levels of agreement for BMI (r=.91); waist   circumference (0.91);  FVC (0.88); and FEV1 (0.86). As expected due to higher biological and measurement   variability, 149 somewhat lower 3-year correlations were demonstrated for SBP (0.56); Diastolic BP (0.48); AHI (0.62);   and nocturnal oxygen desaturation (0.60).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NHLBI Candidate-gene Association Resource.&lt;/b&gt; The NHLBI initiated the Candidate gene Association Resource (CARe) to create a shared genotype/phenotype resource for analyses of the association of genotypes with phenotypes relevant to the mission of the NHLBI. The resource comprises nine cohort studies funded by the NHLBI including: Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC), Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Cleveland Family Study (CFS), Coronary Artery Risk Development in Young Adults (CARDIA), Framingham Heart Study (FHS), Jackson Heart Study (JHS), Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis (MESA), and the Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS). A database of genotype and phenotype data was created that includes records for approximately 41,000 study participants with approximately 50,000 SNPs from more than 2,000 selected candidate genes. In addition, a genome wide association study using a 1,000K SNP Chip was conducted on approximately 8,900 African American participants drawn from five CARe cohorts: ARIC, CARDIA, CFS, JHS, and MESA. Data from individual cohorts is available to approved investigators through dbGaP.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Some relevant CARe publications&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   CARe Study: PMID &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20400780" target="_blank"&gt;20400780&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   CVD Chip Design: PMID &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18974833" target="_blank"&gt;18974833&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;The Cleveland Family Study contains longitudinal data (multiple observations per person) sent to CARe. Exam visits   occurred as many as 4 times over a 15 year time interval. Unlike some of the other CARe cohorts, new participants   joined the study during subsequent waves of data collection and thus data are available from one to four exams per   participant.  The variable named VISIT denotes the type of visit and are labeled as VISIT #1 (1990-2001),   VISIT #2 (1996-2001), VISIT #3 (1999-2001) and VISIT #5 (2001-2005) (there is no VISIT #4).  These visits   did not occur in "waves", instead they reflect which visit number was recorded.  Recruitment was rolling, thus some   individuals had a first visit (VISIT=1) after others had a second or third visit (VISIT = 2 or 3).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The first 3 visits occurred in participants&amp;#39; homes.  Individuals who participated in visits 2 and 3 included as   many participants who were available for examination from a prior visit. There were also additional family members   and new minority families recruited later and recorded as visit 1 or 5, depending on type of data collected.   Visit 5 occurred in a dedicated clinical research facility (GCRU).  This visit targeted minority families and   families in whom a prior microsatellite exam had been conducted (selected for genetic informativity). Data   collection for visit 5 was more comprehensive-it generally included prior measurements made as well as   more detailed biochemical data, ECGs, endothelial function, and sleep staging data. Thus, the data from   VISIT = 5 accounts for the most recent visit for data collected on individuals in the Cleveland Family Study   and represents the most complete data collection but only includes data for 735 participants.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><StudyURLs><Url name="Cleveland Family Study" url="http://dceweb1.case.edu/serc/collab/project_family.shtml"/></StudyURLs></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="12" name="NHLBI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="SREDLINE" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="SREDLINE" fname="Susan" mname="S" lname="Redline" email="sredline@partners.org"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>BRIGHAM AND WOMEN'S HOSPITALCASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010404851" aid="1" auth="cit" login="gjp" fname="George" mname="John" lname="Papanicolaou" email="gjp@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="BCADE47" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="BCADE47" fname="Brian" mname="" lname="Cade" email="bcade@partners.org"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization>BRIGHAM AND WOMEN'S HOSPITAL</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011276160" aid="1" auth="cit" login="thomsonal" fname="Alastair" mname="Alexander" lname="Thomson" email="alastair.thomson@nih.gov"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014418323" aid="1" auth="cit" login="dzakpasuns" fname="Noble" mname="Senyo" lname="Dzakpasu" email="dzakpasuns@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="GROSSMANR" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GROSSMANR" fname="ROBERT" mname="" lname="GROSSMAN" email="rgrossman1@uchicago.edu"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS AT CHICAGOUNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010579723" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wewu" fname="Wenyu" mname="" lname="Wu" email="wwu@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011552437" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jawang" fname="Zhen" mname="Yuan" lname="Wang" email="zhen.wang@nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001545300" aid="1" auth="cit" login="lic17" fname="Chengyuan" mname="" lname="Press" email="chanel.press@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Support for the Cleveland Family Study was provided by NHLBI grant number R01 HL46380 and NHLBI grant number R01 HL113338.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>Data use is limited to academic researchers conducting research in heart, lung, blood and sleep disorders, and their risk factors, and does not include the study of population origins and ancestry. CFS data may not be used to investigate individual pedigree structures, individual participant genotypes, phenotype-only analyses or issues such as non-maternity and non-paternity. All researchers requesting CFS data will be required to obtain approval from their IRB for their proposed project using CFS data.</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access_timeout_extend" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (institution requested additional time)"/><ConsentGroup uid="212" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Heart, Lung, Blood, and Sleep Disorders, IRB, NPU)" name="DS-HLBS-IRB-NPU" dac_uid="56" dac_name="NHLBI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Heart, Lung, Blood, and Sleep Disorders.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.

Data use is limited to academic researchers conducting research in heart, lung, blood and sleep disorders, and their risk factors, and does not include the study of population origins and ancestry. CFS data may not be used to investigate individual pedigree structures, individual participant genotypes, phenotype-only analyses or issues such as non-maternity and non-paternity. All researchers requesting CFS data will be required to obtain approval from their IRB for their proposed project using CFS data.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><TrustedPartners><TrustedPartner trp_id="11" trp_db_name="NHLBI BioData Catalyst" trp_download_url="https://biodatacatalyst.nhlbi.nih.gov/resources/data" trp_help_url="https://biodatacatalyst.nhlbi.nih.gov/contact"><StudyFlags sam_with_min_meta="Yes" seq_data_to_ncbi="Yes" gen_phen_to_ncbi="Yes" has_out_ncbi_data="Yes"/></TrustedPartner></TrustedPartners></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="6239" whole_study_id="6239" phs="000284" v="1" p="1" createDate="2010-06-14T14:03:25-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T09:49:22-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T09:49:22-05:00" handle="CFS" num_participants="704"><StudyInfo accession="phs000284.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000284.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75725" entrez_id="75725" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75727" entrez_id="75727" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>NHLBI CFS Candidate Gene Association Resource (CARe)</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType></StudyTypes><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The Cleveland Family Study is the largest family-based study of sleep apnea world-wide, consisting of 2284 individuals   (46% African American) from 361 families studied on up to 4 occasions over a period of 16 years. The study was begun in 1990   with the initial aims of quantifying the familial aggregation of sleep apnea.  NIH renewals provided expansion of the   original cohort (including increased minority recruitment) and longitudinal follow-up, with the last exam occurring   in February 2006. Index probands (n=275) were recruited from 3 area hospital sleep labs if they had a confirmed   diagnosis of sleep apnea and at least 2 first-degree relatives available to be studied.  In the first 5 years of   the study, neighborhood control probands (n=87) with at least 2 living relatives available for study were selected   at random from a list provided by the index family and also studied. All available first degree relatives and spouses   of the case and control probands also were recruited. Second-degree relatives, including half-sibs, aunts, uncles and   grandparents, were also included if they lived near the first degree relatives (cases or controls), or if the family   had been found to have two or more relatives with sleep apnea.  Blood was sampled and DNA isolated for participants   seen in the last two exam cycles (n=1447). The sample, which is enriched with individuals with sleep apnea, also   contains a high prevalence of individuals with sleep apnea-related traits, including: obesity, impaired glucose   tolerance, and HTN.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Phenotyping data have been collected over 4 exam cycles, each occurring ~every 4 years. The last three exams   targeted all subjects who had been studied at earlier exams, as well as new minority families and family members   of previously studied probands who had been unavailable at prior exams. Data from one, two, three and four visits   are available for 412, 630, 329 and 67, participants, respectively.  In the first 3 exams, participants underwent   overnight in-home sleep studies, allowing determination of the number and duration of hypopneas and apneas, sleep   period, heart rate, and oxygen saturation levels; anthropometry (weight, height, and waist, hip, and neck circumferences);   resting blood pressure; spirometry; standardized questionnaire evaluation of symptoms, medications, sleep patterns,   quality of life, daytime sleepiness measures and health history; venipuncture and measurement of total and HDL   cholesterol. The 4th exam (2001-2006) was designed to collect more detailed measurements of sleep, metabolic and   CVD phenotypes and included measurement of state-of-the-art polysomnography, with both collection of blood and   measurement of blood pressure before and after sleep, and anthropometry, upper airway assessments, spirometry,   exhaled nitric oxide, and ECG performed the morning after the sleep study.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Data have been collected by trained research assistants or GCRC nurses following written Manuals of Procedures   who were certified following standard approaches for each study procedure. Ongoing data quality, with assessment of   within or between individual drift, has been monitored on an ongoing basis, using statistical techniques as well as   regular re-certification procedures. Between and within scorer reliabilities for key sleep apnea indices have been   excellent, with intra-class correlation coefficients (ICCs) exceeding 0.92 for the apnea-hypopnea index (AHI). Sleep staging, assessed with   epoch specific comparisons, also demonstrate excellent reliability for stage identification (kappas&amp;gt;0.82). There has   been no evidence of significant time trends-between or within scorers- for the AHI variables. We also have evaluated   the night-to-night variability of the AHI and other sleep variables in 91 subjects, with each measurement made 1-3   months apart. There is high night to night consistency for the AHI (ICC: 0.80), the arousal index (0.76), and   the % sleep time in slow-wave sleep (0.73). We have demonstrated the comparability of the apnea estimates (AHI)   determined from limited channel studies obtained at in-home settings with in full in-laboratory polysomnography.   In addition to our published validation study, we more recently compared the AHI in 169 Cleveland Family Study   participants undergoing both assessments (in-home and in-laboratory) within one week apart. These showed excellent   levels of agreement (ICC=0.83), demonstrating the feasibility of examining data from either in-home or in-laboratory   studies for apnea phenotyping. Data collected in the GCRC were obtained, when possible, with comparable, if not   identical techniques, as were the same measures collected at prior exams performed in the participants&amp;#39; homes. To   address the comparability of data collected over different exams, we calculated the crude age-adjusted   correlations ~3 year within individual correlations between measures made in the most recent GCRC exam with   measures made in a prior exam and demonstrated excellent levels of agreement for BMI (r=.91); waist   circumference (0.91);  FVC (0.88); and FEV1 (0.86). As expected due to higher biological and measurement   variability, 149 somewhat lower 3-year correlations were demonstrated for SBP (0.56); Diastolic BP (0.48); AHI (0.62);   and nocturnal oxygen desaturation (0.60).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NHLBI Candidate-gene Association Resource.&lt;/b&gt; The NHLBI initiated the Candidate gene Association Resource (CARe) to create a shared genotype/phenotype resource for analyses of the association of genotypes with phenotypes relevant to the mission of the NHLBI. The resource comprises nine cohort studies funded by the NHLBI including: Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC), Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Cleveland Family Study (CFS), Coronary Artery Risk Development in Young Adults (CARDIA), Framingham Heart Study (FHS), Jackson Heart Study (JHS), Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis (MESA), and the Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS). A database of genotype and phenotype data was created that includes records for approximately 41,000 study participants with approximately 50,000 SNPs from more than 2,000 selected candidate genes. In addition, a genome wide association study using a 1,000K SNP Chip was conducted on approximately 8,900 African American participants drawn from five CARe cohorts: ARIC, CARDIA, CFS, JHS, and MESA. Data from individual cohorts is available to approved investigators through dbGaP.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Some relevant CARe publications&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   CARe Study: PMID &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20400780" target="_blank"&gt;20400780&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   CVD Chip Design: PMID &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18974833" target="_blank"&gt;18974833&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;The Cleveland Family Study contains longitudinal data (multiple observations per person) sent to CARe. Exam visits   occurred as many as 4 times over a 15 year time interval. Unlike some of the other CARe cohorts, new participants   joined the study during subsequent waves of data collection and thus data are available from one to four exams per   participant.  The variable named VISIT denotes the type of visit and are labeled as VISIT #1 (1990-2001),   VISIT #2 (1996-2001), VISIT #3 (1999-2001) and VISIT #5 (2001-2005) (there is no VISIT #4).  These visits   did not occur in "waves", instead they reflect which visit number was recorded.  Recruitment was rolling, thus some   individuals had a first visit (VISIT=1) after others had a second or third visit (VISIT = 2 or 3).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The first 3 visits occurred in participants&amp;#39; homes.  Individuals who participated in visits 2 and 3 included as   many participants who were available for examination from a prior visit. There were also additional family members   and new minority families recruited later and recorded as visit 1 or 5, depending on type of data collected.   Visit 5 occurred in a dedicated clinical research facility (GCRU).  This visit targeted minority families and   families in whom a prior microsatellite exam had been conducted (selected for genetic informativity). Data   collection for visit 5 was more comprehensive-it generally included prior measurements made as well as   more detailed biochemical data, ECGs, endothelial function, and sleep staging data. Thus, the data from   VISIT = 5 accounts for the most recent visit for data collected on individuals in the Cleveland Family Study   and represents the most complete data collection but only includes data for 735 participants.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Susan Redline, MD</AttrName><Institution>Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH, USA and Brigham and Women's Hospital, Boston, MA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>R0146380</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="CARe Project Officers"><AttrName>George Papanicolaou, PhD</AttrName><Institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="CARe Project Officers"><AttrName>Dina Paltoo, PhD</AttrName><Institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Candidate Gene Association Resource (CARe) - Broad Institute"><AttrName>HHSN268200625226C (ADB No. N01-HC-65226)</AttrName><Institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><StudyURLs><Url name="Cleveland Family Study" url="http://dceweb1.case.edu/serc/collab/project_family.shtml"/></StudyURLs><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="20400780"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18974833"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="7881656"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="8665046"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="9001310"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="9230740"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="11921084"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15070816"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="12734134"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="15611783"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16374834"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17520798"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17682664"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18209735"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18754839"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18579548"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19238807"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19480228"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="20538960"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="20508215"/></Publication></Publications></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="12" name="NHLBI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="SREDLINE" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="SREDLINE" fname="Susan" mname="S" lname="Redline" email="sredline@partners.org"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>BRIGHAM AND WOMEN'S HOSPITALCASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010404851" aid="1" auth="cit" login="gjp" fname="George" mname="John" lname="Papanicolaou" email="gjp@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011552437" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jawang" fname="Zhen" mname="Yuan" lname="Wang" email="zhen.wang@nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011574474" aid="1" auth="cit" login="runkoa" fname="Alexander" mname="Peter" lname="Runko" email="alexander.runko@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=6263&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="CFS New DUC.docx" md5="fa7df41e8e29d78fa741d48e5a72dc4d" size="31655" modDate="2010-07-06T09:17:53-05:00" content-type="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.word"/></DUC><DUC_PDF><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=14813&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="CFS New DUC.docx.pdf" md5="75ce04b60d449aef96e59ea71ddb45ba" size="144131" modDate="2015-06-18T17:33:07-05:00" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="212" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Non Profit Use " name="NPU" dac_uid="56" dac_name="NHLBI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>The informed consent document signed by Cleveland Family Study participants allows use of these genetic data by investigators employed by non-profit organizations only. Direct use of these data by private companies to develop diagnostics or therapeutics is not allowed under the current consent. Investigation is limited to CVD, Sleep Apnea, and Diabetes Research Use Only.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>