<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="8213" whole_study_id="5813" phs="000264" v="3" p="1" createDate="2012-07-03T09:46:24-05:00" completedByGPADate="2014-03-12T15:14:09-05:00" modDate="2022-03-03T10:50:13-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-03-03T10:50:13-05:00" handle="HMP_ViromeFebrile" num_participants="250"><StudyInfo accession="phs000264.v3.p1" parentAccession="phs000264.v3.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA46335" entrez_id="46335" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74945" entrez_id="74945" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>The Human Virome in Children and its Relationship to Febrile Illness</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes/><StudyTypes2 calculated="No"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No" other_value=""/></StudyTypes2><SraStorages/></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="5" name="NIAID" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GREGORYSTORCH" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GREGORYSTORCH" fname="Gregory" mname="A." lname="Storch" email="storch@wustl.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011421375" aid="1" auth="cit" login="salomonra" fname="Rachelle" mname="" lname="Salomon" email="rachelle.salomon@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2003273233" aid="1" auth="cit" login="vanpanhuiswg" fname="Willem" mname="Gijsbert" lname="Van Panhuis" email="wilbert.vanpanhuis@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding for the study of The Human Virome in Children and its Relationship to Febrile Illness was provided from the NIAID (1UH2AI083266-01). This project is one of a network of Demonstration Projects funded by the Human Microbiome Project of the NIH.  Support is also derived from the Washington University Institute of Clinical and Translational Sciences (UL1RR024992).

The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP found at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/XXXXX through dbGaP study accession numbers XXXXX.  Data for the The Human Virome in Children and its Relationship to Febrile Illness were provided by Dr. Gregory Storch on behalf of his collaborators Washington University.
 
Dr. Storch and his collaborators request that publications resulting from these data cite their original publication: (to follow, after submission).
</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="407" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="65" dac_name="NIAID " irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data can be used for any research related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA><STUDY sra_id="63" accession="SRP002430" bioproject="46335" center_name="Washington University " srastatus="new" disable_sra_ship="0"><DESCRIPTOR><STUDY_TITLE>Human Virome in Children and its Relationship to Febrile Ilness</STUDY_TITLE><STUDY_TYPE existing_study_type="Metagenomics"/><CENTER_NAME>Washington University </CENTER_NAME></DESCRIPTOR><sra_stats/><STUDY_ATTRIBUTES><STUDY_ATTRIBUTE><TAG>dbgapss_sra_id</TAG><VALUE>63</VALUE></STUDY_ATTRIBUTE></STUDY_ATTRIBUTES><add_data><bioproject srp_by_bioid="yes">46335</bioproject></add_data></STUDY></SRA><Documents/><Status uid="14" name="completed_by_gpa" title="Completed by GPA"/></Study><Study uid="6810" whole_study_id="5813" phs="000264" v="2" p="1" createDate="2011-03-02T16:35:01-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T10:42:06-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T10:42:06-05:00" handle="HMP_ViromeFebrile" num_participants="250"><StudyInfo accession="phs000264.v2.p1" parentAccession="phs000264.v2.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA46335" entrez_id="46335" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74945" entrez_id="74945" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>The Human Virome in Children and its Relationship to Febrile Illness</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Definition of the human microbiome is an important scientific priority.  This study will expand the scope of the  investigation to include viruses, which account for a substantial proportion of infectious disease morbidity and  mortality, especially in children. The long-term goal of this project is to describe the human virome in children  and to investigate its relevance to febrile illnesses in children.  The project will also seek to understand the  relationship of the immune system to the composition of the virome.  Thus, the project&amp;#39;s specific aims are 1) To  elucidate the spectrum of viruses that can be detected using non-biased, high throughput sequencing on samples of  blood, respiratory, and gastrointestinal secretions from healthy children and to use this information as a basis  for understanding the role of viruses in acute febrile illnesses without an obvious source, and 2) to investigate  the effect of various forms of immunosuppression on the spectrum of viruses detected in children, and to use this  information as a basis for understanding the role of viruses in acute febrile illnesses occurring in these children.  Our preliminary studies show that diverse viruses can be detected in children having undiagnosed fever.  To carry  out the specific aims, well children will be enrolled prior to having elective surgery, and febrile otherwise well  children will be enrolled from the Emergency Department at St. Louis Children&amp;#39;s Hospital.  Immunocompromised children  will be recruited from hematopoietic stem cell and solid organ transplant clinics, the HIV/AIDS clinic, and the  rheumatology/immunology clinic from the same hospital.  Children with fever will have samples obtained at the time  of the febrile illness and at 1 and 6-month follow-up visits.  Selected samples from each study group will be  analyzed at the Genome Center at Washington University (GCWU) using next generation 454 high throughput sequencing  to detect and sequence all viral sequences present.  We anticipate detecting and sequencing a broad range of viruses,  including previously unrecognized agents.  A variety of techniques will be used to investigate the significance of  viruses detected.  Virus-specific PCR assays will be used to determine the frequency and extent of viruses detected  by sequencing, using the full range of samples collected.  Host response to the detected viruses will be investigated  using serologic analysis, cytokine profiling, and microarrays to characterize host gene expression.  These studies  will take advantage of follow-up samples to compare the acute response with the response in the convalescent period.  This study will draw upon the expertise and technological assets of one of the world&amp;#39;s most powerful sequencing centers  to provide the research community with a comprehensive sequence data base of the viruses that are present in children,  which can be used to improve our understanding of the causes of febrile illnesses in young children, many of which are  currently undiagnosed.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;Starting in July, 2007, we began a study of viral causes of fever in children between 2 and 36 months of age who had  fevers without an idententifiable focus.  Starting in February 2009, we also began to include well children having same  day surgery as controls.  During this same time frame, Dr. David Wang began to assemble a repository of specimens from  children undergoing organ transplantation.  These specimens from these studies were incorporated into the present  study which began specimen collection in July, 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Gregory Storch, MD</AttrName><Institution>National Institute for Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>1UH2AI083266-01</AttrName><Institution>National Institute for Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="5" name="NIAID" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GREGORYSTORCH" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GREGORYSTORCH" fname="Gregory" mname="A." lname="Storch" email="storch@wustl.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011421375" aid="1" auth="cit" login="salomonra" fname="Rachelle" mname="" lname="Salomon" email="rachelle.salomon@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010066953" aid="1" auth="cit" login="mgiovanni" fname="Maria" mname="Y" lname="Giovanni" email="mgiovanni@niaid.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS:  This study has not provided a suggested acknowledgement statement. However, Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.</acknowledgement_statement><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="407" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="65" dac_name="NIAID " irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data can be used for any research related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA><STUDY sra_id="63" accession="SRP002430" bioproject="46335" center_name="Washington University " srastatus="new" disable_sra_ship="0"><DESCRIPTOR><STUDY_TITLE>Human Virome in Children and its Relationship to Febrile Ilness</STUDY_TITLE><STUDY_TYPE existing_study_type="Metagenomics"/><CENTER_NAME>Washington University </CENTER_NAME></DESCRIPTOR><sra_stats/><STUDY_ATTRIBUTES><STUDY_ATTRIBUTE><TAG>dbgapss_sra_id</TAG><VALUE>63</VALUE></STUDY_ATTRIBUTE></STUDY_ATTRIBUTES><add_data><bioproject srp_by_bioid="yes">46335</bioproject></add_data></STUDY></SRA><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="5813" whole_study_id="5813" phs="000264" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-12-18T17:48:18-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T10:03:51-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T10:03:51-05:00" handle="HMP_ViromeFebrile" num_participants="250"><StudyInfo accession="phs000264.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000264.v1.p1"><StudyNameEntrez>The Human Virome in Children and its Relationship to Febrile Illness</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Definition of the human microbiome is an important scientific priority.  This study will expand the scope of the   investigation to include viruses, which account for a substantial proportion of infectious disease morbidity and   mortality, especially in children. The long-term goal of this project is to describe the human virome in children   and to investigate its relevance to febrile illnesses in children.  The project will also seek to understand the   relationship of the immune system to the composition of the virome.  Thus, the project&amp;#39;s specific aims are 1) To   elucidate the spectrum of viruses that can be detected using non-biased, high throughput sequencing on samples of   blood, respiratory, and gastrointestinal secretions from healthy children and to use this information as a basis   for understanding the role of viruses in acute febrile illnesses without an obvious source, and 2) to investigate   the effect of various forms of immunosuppression on the spectrum of viruses detected in children, and to use this   information as a basis for understanding the role of viruses in acute febrile illnesses occurring in these children.   Our preliminary studies show that diverse viruses can be detected in children having undiagnosed fever.  To carry   out the specific aims, well children will be enrolled prior to having elective surgery, and febrile otherwise well   children will be enrolled from the Emergency Department at St. Louis Children&amp;#39;s Hospital.  Immunocompromised children   will be recruited from hematopoietic stem cell and solid organ transplant clinics, the HIV/AIDS clinic, and the   rheumatology/immunology clinic from the same hospital.  Children with fever will have samples obtained at the time   of the febrile illness and at 1 and 6-month follow-up visits.  Selected samples from each study group will be   analyzed at the Genome Center at Washington University (GCWU) using next generation 454 high throughput sequencing   to detect and sequence all viral sequences present.  We anticipate detecting and sequencing a broad range of viruses,   including previously unrecognized agents.  A variety of techniques will be used to investigate the significance of   viruses detected.  Virus-specific PCR assays will be used to determine the frequency and extent of viruses detected   by sequencing, using the full range of samples collected.  Host response to the detected viruses will be investigated   using serologic analysis, cytokine profiling, and microarrays to characterize host gene expression.  These studies   will take advantage of follow-up samples to compare the acute response with the response in the convalescent period.   This study will draw upon the expertise and technological assets of one of the world&amp;#39;s most powerful sequencing centers   to provide the research community with a comprehensive sequence data base of the viruses that are present in children,   which can be used to improve our understanding of the causes of febrile illnesses in young children, many of which are   currently undiagnosed.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;Starting in July, 2007, we began a study of viral causes of fever in children between 2 and 36 months of age who had   fevers without an idententifiable focus.  Starting in February 2009, we also began to include well children having same   day surgery as controls.  During this same time frame, Dr. David Wang began to assemble a repository of specimens from   children undergoing organ transplantation.  These specimens from these studies were incorporated into the present   study which began specimen collection in July, 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Gregory Storch, MD</AttrName><Institution>National Institute for Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>1UH2AI083266-01</AttrName><Institution>National Institute for Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="5" name="NIAID" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GREGORYSTORCH" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GREGORYSTORCH" fname="Gregory" mname="A." lname="Storch" email="storch@wustl.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011421375" aid="1" auth="cit" login="salomonra" fname="Rachelle" mname="" lname="Salomon" email="rachelle.salomon@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010066953" aid="1" auth="cit" login="mgiovanni" fname="Maria" mname="Y" lname="Giovanni" email="mgiovanni@niaid.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=6245&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="Storch DUC Agreement 031210.docx" md5="61f3f34a49fd3fd169b2458f02f63d1c" size="27677" modDate="2010-06-22T10:58:28-05:00" content-type="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.word"/></DUC><ConsentGroup uid="125" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="65" dac_name="NIAID " irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data can be used for any research related to the human microbiome.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>