<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="6050" whole_study_id="6050" phs="000245" v="1" p="1" createDate="2010-03-26T09:48:12-05:00" modDate="2020-01-21T13:41:19-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-01-21T13:41:19-05:00" handle="NHGRI_TripleNegativeBreastCancer" num_participants="1"><StudyInfo accession="phs000245.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000245.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA74803" entrez_id="74803" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74805" entrez_id="74805" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>Whole Genome Sequencing of Triple Negative Breast Cancer</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>resequencing</StudyType><StudyType>cancer_genomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Breast Cancer Subject Participant ID 700064 (Source Sample names: 6888 and 206). We used massively parallel DNA sequencing technologies    to screen entire genomes, in an unbiased manner, for genetic changes associated with tumor growth and metastasis. We describe the    complete genome sequence analysis of four DNA samples from a 44-year old African-American patient with basal-like breast cancer:    peripheral blood, the primary tumor, a brain metastasis that developed within a year of initial therapy, and a first-passage    xenograft derived from the primary tumor. A total of 50 validated mutations were discovered within coding, RNA, or splice site    sequences. Of these, 20 mutations were abundantly present in all three tumors, including mutations in &lt;i&gt;CSMD1&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;JAK2&lt;/i&gt;.    These two genes subsequently were found to be mutated in other breast tumors. The metastasis contained two &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; mutations    not present in the primary tumor, and was significantly enriched for 20 shared mutations, suggesting that they may be involved    in the metastatic process. The xenograft contained no unique coding, RNA, or splice site mutations and retained all primary tumor    mutations, albeit at different frequencies. However, a significant increase in copy number alterations was observed in the xenograft    as compared to the primary tumor. We validated 28 large deletions and six inversions, as well as seven translocations in at least    one of the three tumor samples. Among them, a 26 kb deletion in &lt;i&gt;MECR&lt;/i&gt; was solely identified, assembled, and validated in the    brain metastasis and two overlapping large deletions on chromosome 5 encompassing &lt;i&gt;CTNNA1&lt;/i&gt;, a potential tumor suppressor gene,    were identified in all three tumors. The differential mutation frequencies and structural variation patterns between primary and    metastatic tumors suggest that metastatic tumors may arise from minor subpopulations of cells within the primary. Namely, the    metastatic and xenografting processes apparently select for cells harboring a distinct subset of the primary tumor mutation    repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;A previously healthy, premenopausal 44 year old African American woman presented to the medical oncologist with newly diagnosed    inflammatory left breast cancer, clinical stage IIIB, T4dN1M0. Patient&amp;#39;s past medical history was insignificant; no prior cancer,    hypertension, heart disease or history of any surgical interventions. The patient&amp;#39;s family history was obtained by the treating    medical oncologist, and was positive for cancer in maternal grandfather with lung cancer, one uncle with throat cancer and another    with brain cancer. All three were deceased.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Patient reported that she noted that left breast was larger than right. A mammogram performed 3 days later showed no significant    masses, calcifications or other abnormalities. Patient subsequently presented to the surgeon following a 3 week history of an enlarging    left breast mass with edema, erythema and increasing pain. A left breast excisional biopsy and skin biopsy were performed. Breast biopsy    showed invasive ductal carcinoma, poorly differentiated, with extensive lymphatic invasion.  The tumor was ER negative (0%), PR    positive (11%) and HER2 negative (0) by immunohistochemistry. Skin biopsy showed invasive carcinoma involving deep dermal lymphatics.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Staging work-up was obtained prior to initiating neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Bone scan and CT of chest, abdomen and pelvis were    negative for distant metastatic disease, positive only for left axillary lymphadenopathy.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;After informed consent was obtained, the patient was enrolled in an institutional protocol studying the effect of neoadjuvant    chemotherapy on breast cancers, bone marrow cancer cells, and circulating cancer cells. Specimens of breast tumor mass, bone marrow and    peripheral blood were collected and preserved prior to initiation of neoadjuvant chemotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The patient initiated neoadjuvant chemotherapy with four cycles of dose dense doxorubicin and cyclophosphomide followed by four    cycles of paclitaxel. Left breast mastectomy with axillary node dissection performed 3 weeks following chemotherapy completion showed    multifocal, poorly differentiated invasive mammary carcinoma with ductal and lobular features.  Six of thirteen lymph nodes were positive.    Pathologic stage was T2N2. Right breast simple mastectomy showed no evidence of malignancy. Post-treatment specimens of breast mass,    bone marrow and peripheral blood were collected and preserved for the effect of neoadjuvant chemotherapy study at that time as well.     Patient subsequently received four week course of radiation therapy to the left chest wall and regional lymphatics followed by    tamoxifen 20 mg daily.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Despite these therapies, patient returned in approximately 11 months from diagnosis complaining of severe right hip pain, nausea and    vomiting.  Patient was found to have relapsed to the right cerebellum. Also of note: while never pathologically diagnosed, right hip pain    was suspected to be due to progressive metastatic disease.  Neurosurgical consultation was obtained, and patient was scheduled for    sub-occipital craniectomy for resection of right cerebellar lesion. Prior to the procedure, informed consent was obtained for an    institutional protocol entitled Longitudinal Cancer Genome Profiling Using Sequential Tissue Biopsies in Patients with Breast Cancer.    After ensuring adequate tumor was obtained for diagnostic purposes, specimens from the cerebellar mass were collected and preserved for    protocol. Pathology from craniectomy showed metastatic carcinoma, consistent with breast primary.  Patient tolerated the procedure    well.  However, after the procedure, patient&amp;#39;s neurologic status continued to decline and the patient expired 11 months after    her initial diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Richard Wilson, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Washington University, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>HG002079</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><StudyURLs><Url name="The Genome Center at Washington University" url="http://genome.wustl.edu/cancer/breast"/></StudyURLs><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="20393555"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>U54 HG003079-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="RKWILSON" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="RKWILSON" fname="Richard" mname="K." lname="Wilson" email="Richard.Wilson@nationwidechildrens.org"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITYRESEARCH INST NATIONWIDE CHILDREN'S HOSP</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011607806" aid="1" auth="cit" login="bozenberger" fname="Bradley" mname="Alton" lname="Ozenberger" email="bradley.ozenberger@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for this work was provided by grants to R.K.W. (Richard K. Wilson) from Washington University in St. Louis and the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI U54 HG003079), and grants to M.J.E. (Matthew J. Ellis) from the National Cancer Institute (NCI 1 U01 CA114722-01), the Susan G Komen Breast Cancer Foundation (BCTR0707808), and the Fashion Footwear Charitable Foundation, Inc. NCI U10 CA076001 and a Breast Cancer Research Foundation grant awarded to the American College of Surgeons Oncology Group supported the acquisition of samples for recurrence testing. The tissue procurement core was supported by an NCI core grant to the Siteman Cancer Center (NCI 3P50 CA68438). The Human and Mouse Linked Evaluation of Tumors Core was supported by the Institute of Clinical and Translational Sciences at Washington University (CTSA grant UL1 RR024992). Illumina, Inc. and Washington University also supported this work through the Washington University Cancer Genome Initiative.
The following publication should be cited in publications using the Whole Genome Sequencing of a Triple Negative Breast Cancer Patient datasets:
Ding L, Ellis MJ, Li S, Larson DE, Chen K, Wallis JW, Harris CC, McLellan MD, Fulton RS, Fulton LL, Abbott RM, Hoog J, Dooling DJ, Koboldt DC, Schmidt H, Kalicki J, Zhang Q, Chen L, Lin L, Wendl MC, McMichael JF, Magrini VJ, Cook L, McGrath SD, Vickery TL, Appelbaum E, Deschryver K, Davies S, Guintoli T, Lin L, Crowder R, Tao Y, Snider JE, Smith SM, Dukes AF, Sanderson GE, Pohl CS, Delehaunty KD, Fronick CC, Pape KA, Reed JS, Robinson JS, Hodges JS, Schierding W, Dees ND, Shen D, Locke DP, Wiechert ME, Eldred JM, Peck JB, Oberkfell BJ, Lolofie JT, Du F, Hawkins AE, O'Laughlin MD, Bernard KE, Cunningham M, Elliott G, Mason MD, Thompson DM Jr, Ivanovich JL, Goodfellow PJ, Perou CM, Weinstock GM, Aft R, Watson M, Ley TJ, Wilson RK, Mardis ER. 
Genome remodelling in a basal-like breast cancer metastasis and xenograft. 
Nature. 2010 Apr 15; 464(7291):999-1005.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="158" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Cancer Research" name="CR" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data Use is limited to cancer research.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>