<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5623" whole_study_id="5623" phs="000210" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-06-29T16:52:07-05:00" modDate="2019-05-08T13:05:26-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-05-08T13:05:26-05:00" handle="MayoBC_Batzler" num_participants="500"><StudyInfo accession="phs000210.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000210.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75545" entrez_id="75545" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75547" entrez_id="75547" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>PGRN-RIKEN Mayo Breast Cancer</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Source of Patients&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   The source of the patients for this genome-wide case control study was MA.27, which was conducted as a multi-cooperative group effort   under the auspices of the NCI Breast Cancer Intergroup of North America. The NCIC Clinical Trials Group (CTG) serves as the   coordinating group, with participation by the NCI-sponsored North Central Cancer   Treatment Group, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG), Southwest Oncology Group, and Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CALGB).   MA.27 involved postmenopausal women with histologically confirmed and completely resected invasive breast cancer with surgical   margins clear of invasive carcinoma and DCIS in the following TMN categories (AJCC Version 6): pT1, pT2, pT3; pNx, pN0, pN1,   pN2, pN3 (only when the sole basis is presence of 10 or more involved axillary nodes); MO.  The primary tumor must have been   ER and/or progesterone receptor positive.  Patients were stratified by lymph node status at diagnosis, prior adjuvant chemotherapy,   and trastuzumab use and were randomized to 5 years of adjuvant therapy with anastrozole or exemestane. The trial was activated   on May 26, 2003, and reached its accrual objectives on July 31, 2008, after the randomization of 6827 North American patients,   with the majority (79%) providing DNA and consent for genetic testing.  Non-North American patients were also entered by the   International Breast Cancer Study Group but they did not contribute DNA.  From 2003 to December 21, 2004, patients also   underwent a second randomization to celecoxib 400 mg twice daily or placebo but, after the entry of 1,622 patients, this   treatment was discontinued because of reports of increased cardiovascular risk associated with celecoxib.   &lt;/p&gt;      &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Case Definition for Musculoskeletal Adverse Events&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   Cases were defined to have had at least one of the following six MSAE): 1. pain - joint, 2. pain - muscle, 3. pain - bone, 4.   arthritis, 5. joint - function, 6. musculoskeletal - other. Cases were required to have at least grade 3 toxicity, according   to the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v3.0, or go off treatment for any grade of the six MSAEs; and   were required to have had an MSAE within the first two years (i.e., a MSAE occurring after 2 years was not be considered   a case). Subjects were excluded from the case group who met the case definition while on celecoxib or in the three months   after stopping celecoxib but subjects were allowed to be cases if they developed their first MSAE more than three months   after stopping celecoxib.   &lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Study Design&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   The design was a nested matched case-control study with two controls selected for each case. Random matching from the potential control   group (i.e., risk-set sampling such that controls had at least the same length of followup as the timing of the case event) was   done by matching the case on the following factors: 1. treatment arm (exemestane vs. anastrozole, blinded), 2. prior   adjuvant chemotherapy (yes vs. no), 3. age at start of treatment (+/- 5 years), 4. Celecoxib allocation (yes vs. no).  Attempts   were made to exactly match each case with two controls according to the above criteria. If, however, controls could not be   exactly matched, "close" matching was used to define a distance between each case and all potential controls in an optimal matching   algorithm.  Race is a potential confounding factor, and 94% of the MA.27 population is Caucasian, 3% are Black, 1% Asian, 1%   American Indian, and 1% are of unknown race. Because there are so few non-Caucasian participants, was restricted to only Caucasians.   Following identification of cases and controls, the list was sent to the CALGB Pathology Coordinating Office (PCO) at Ohio State   University Medical Center for plating of the samples.  Other patient factors that might influence the association of SNP   genotypes with a MSAE, either as confounding factors or as effect modifiers, were included as investigational covariates.   These include 1. body mass index (BMI), 2. bisphosphonate use, 3. fractures in past 10 years, 4. baseline ECOG performance status, 5.   prior hormone replacement therapy, 6. prior adjuvant radiotherapy, and 7. prior taxane treatment.  An Honest Broker Process was   utilized to ensure patient confidentiality.   &lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Genotype Assays and Quality Control&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   A GWAS was performed with the Illumina Human610-Quad at the RIKEN Center for Genomic Medicine.  The DNA for all of the samples were   adjusted to a concentration of 50 to 100 ng/&amp;#181;L in a final volume of 50 &amp;#181;L.  The 96-well plates were designed to have a unique   distribution pattern with x duplicates per plate to evaluate genotype concordance.  Samples with &amp;lt;98% call rate were removed   from analyses.  SNPs with ambiguous call will be excluded using the following criteria: 1. low signal intensity of each   allele, 2. low cluster separation score, 3. SNP call rate &amp;lt;0.98, 4. SNPs with Hardy Weinberg Equilibrium p-value &amp;lt;0.001 were excluded.   X-chromosome SNPs were used to validate female sex and quality control measures were examined across the different submitting centers.   For all pairs of subjects, the percentage of matching genotypes were computed to screen for unexpected duplicate samples.  All SNPs   found to be associated with MSAE were subjected to visual inspection of the cluster plots to verify that the genotype clustering was   adequate.   &lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;June 27, 2008: Protocol approved by The Breast Cancer Intergroup Correlative Sciences Committee and Clinical Investigations Branch,   Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program, Division of Cancer Treatment and Diagnosis, National Cancer Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>James N. Ingle, MD</AttrName><Institution>Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>GM 61388</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="20876420"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>U01 GM061388-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="1" name="NIGMS" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="WEINSHILBOUM1" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="WEINSHILBOUM1" fname="Richard" mname="M" lname="Weinshilboum" email="weinshilboum.richard@mayo.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>MAYO CLINIC ROCHESTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010070749" aid="1" auth="cit" login="longr" fname="Rochelle" mname="" lname="Long" email="longr@nigms.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010150228" aid="1" auth="cit" login="dkras" fname="Donna" mname="M" lname="Krasnewich-Vostal" email="dkras@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Samples and associated genotype and phenotype data used in this study were provided by the Mayo Clinic.  Funding support for the Mayo Clinic was provided through a cooperative agreement with the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS), Grant U01 GM61388.  The datasets used for analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number [phs000210.v1.p1].  Dr. James Ingle and his collaborators request that publications resulting from this data cite their original publication.  </acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_old_cert" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution responded that the study is not sensitive without submitting a new Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="99" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research " name="HR" dac_uid="58" dac_name="NIGMS" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Mayo Clinic data may be used only for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems. Investigators must state in the DAR their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from their study with the scientific community.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>