<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="10661" whole_study_id="5814" phs="000256" v="4" p="3" createDate="2014-01-13T18:22:06-05:00" completedByGPADate="2014-03-12T15:16:51-05:00" modDate="2022-03-03T10:50:16-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-03-03T10:50:16-05:00" handle="HMP_VaginalMicrobiome" num_participants="165"><StudyInfo accession="phs000256.v4.p3" parentAccession="phs000256.v4.p3"><BioProject id="PRJNA46311" entrez_id="46311" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA46877" entrez_id="46877" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74947" entrez_id="74947" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>The Vaginal Microbiome: Disease, Genetics and the Environment</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Funding>UH2 AI83263</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="5" name="NIAID" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GABUCK" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GABUCK" fname="Gregory" mname="ALLEN" lname="Buck" email="gregory.buck@vcuhealth.org"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010169778" aid="1" auth="cit" login="hdavid" fname="Hagit" mname="G" lname="Skolnik david" email="hdavid@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2003273233" aid="1" auth="cit" login="vanpanhuiswg" fname="Willem" mname="Gijsbert" lname="Van Panhuis" email="wilbert.vanpanhuis@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Datasets from the &#8220;The Vaginal Microbiome: Disease, Genetics and the Environment&#8221; that were used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/XXXXX through dbGaP accession number [INSERT ACCESSION NUMBER]. Data for the The Vaginal Microbiome: Disease, Genetics and the Environment were provided by Dr. Gregory Buck on behalf of his collaborators at Virginia Commonwealth University. Funding support for the project was provided through the Human Microbiome Roadmap Project funded to VCU by NIAID/NHGRI of the NIH through grant number 1UH2AI083263-01 and by Virginia Commonwealth University. Dr. Buck and his collaborators request that publications resulting from these data cite their original publication</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="435" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="65" dac_name="NIAID " irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data can be used for any research related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="8295" whole_study_id="5814" phs="000256" v="3" p="2" createDate="2012-07-18T11:00:32-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T09:46:14-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T09:46:14-05:00" handle="HMP_VaginalMicrobiome" num_participants="165"><StudyInfo accession="phs000256.v3.p2" parentAccession="phs000256.v3.p2"><BioProject id="PRJNA46311" entrez_id="46311" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA46877" entrez_id="46877" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74947" entrez_id="74947" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>The Vaginal Microbiome: Disease, Genetics and the Environment</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Funding>UH2 AI83263</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="5" name="NIAID" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GABUCK" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GABUCK" fname="Gregory" mname="ALLEN" lname="Buck" email="gregory.buck@vcuhealth.org"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010169778" aid="1" auth="cit" login="hdavid" fname="Hagit" mname="G" lname="Skolnik david" email="hdavid@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010066953" aid="1" auth="cit" login="mgiovanni" fname="Maria" mname="Y" lname="Giovanni" email="mgiovanni@niaid.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS:  This study has not provided a suggested acknowledgement statement. However, Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.</acknowledgement_statement><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="435" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="65" dac_name="NIAID " irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data can be used for any research related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="6894" whole_study_id="5814" phs="000256" v="2" p="2" createDate="2011-03-31T15:44:08-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T09:11:25-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T09:11:25-05:00" handle="HMP_VaginalMicrobiome" num_participants="165"><StudyInfo accession="phs000256.v2.p2" parentAccession="phs000256.v2.p2"><BioProject id="PRJNA46311" entrez_id="46311" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA46877" entrez_id="46877" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74947" entrez_id="74947" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>The Vaginal Microbiome: Disease, Genetics and the Environment</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The vagina is an interactive interface with the environment, and as such is covered by a protective epithelial surface.  This surface is colonized by bacteria and other microorganisms which, through a variety of mechanisms serve to further  protect the host from invasion by pathogens. Alterations in the normal vaginal microflora, particularly those associated  with bacterial vaginosis, are thought to contribute to risk of spontaneous pregnancy loss in the second trimester and  spontaneous preterm birth. Additionally, alterations in the vaginal microbiome may increase the likelihood of transmission  of certain agents including human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1). There are physiologic alterations in host  condition (e.g., menopause and pregnancy), which are beginning to be investigated as potential selective conditions  for change in the "normal" flora, and their impact on disease susceptibility and transmission remains to be more  definitively elucidated. The effects of chronically abnormal physiologic states (e.g., diabetes mellitus) on normal  vaginal flora have not been well described or studied. Finally, an almost unexplored area of inquiry is the genetic  contribution, including race/ethnicity, to the establishment and maintenance of a "normal" vaginal flora, under normal  and physiologically altered circumstances. Our research will shed light on how the vaginal microbiome contributes to  adverse obstetrical outcomes and sexually transmitted infections in diverse populations. This project addresses the  following questions:&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First: Do the genes of the host contribute to the composition of the vaginal microbiome?&lt;/b&gt;  We hypothesize that a woman&amp;#39;s genetic composition significantly affects the ability of certain commensal, parasitic  and pathogenic microbes to colonize and/or infect the genital tract. Thus, we will compare and quantify the microbial  populations inhabiting the vaginas of monozygotic and dizygotic twins from the Mid Atlantic Twin Registry, and, in  the process, address the question of whether there is a relationship between the microbiomes of the vagina, mouth  and GI tract.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Second: What changes in the vaginal microbiome are associated with common physiological perturbations or non-infectious  pathological states of the host?&lt;/b&gt;We hypothesize that "altered" physiologic (pregnancy, menopause) and pathologic  (chronic disease, hysterectomy) conditions, or environmental "exposures" (exogenous hormones, antibiotics, chronic  immunosuppressant, smoking; douching) can predictably alter the vaginal microenvironment. These alterations will lead  to changes in microbial populations within the vagina. Changes in the microbial populations may have impacts, positive  or more likely negative, on the spontaneous and future well-being of the affected individual. We are characterizing  the effects of these "altered" physiologic and pathologic conditions, and environmental exposures, on the composition  of the vaginal microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Third: What changes in the vaginal microbiome are associated with relevant infectious diseases and conditions?&lt;/b&gt;  We are testing the hypothesis that infectious diseases predictably alter the vaginal microbiome, and that these changes  have an impact on the disease susceptibility, process, and outcome. A predilection for bacterial vaginosis, vaginitis,  HIV infection, or other sexually transmitted diseases, is likely associated with a women&amp;#39;s vaginal microbial composition.  Thus, we will characterize samples from women with a variety of these infectious conditions to determine the contribution  of their micriobiomes to the disease process and susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;We are addressing these questions using a combination of high throughput &amp;#39;nextgen&amp;#39; sequencing technologies,  including the Roche 454 FLX and the upgraded Illumina Genome Analyzer II instruments currently installed in the Nucleic  Acids Research Facilities at VCU. Thus, segments of the 16S rRNA genes will be amplified from the complex samples taken  from various target sites in and around the vagina of each study participant. These segments will be sequenced and  subjected to taxonomic classification protocols to identify and quantify the bacterial taxa present in each sample.  Additionally, total DNA isolated from these samples will be subjected to shotgun sequence analysis to empirically  reconstruct the metabolic potential of these microbiomes. Finally, specific bacterial clones will be completely  sequenced and analyzed to associate the unavoidable strain and isolate diversity with the clinical phenotypes  presented.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Gregory Buck, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>1UH2AI083263</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>UH2 AI83263</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="5" name="NIAID" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GABUCK" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GABUCK" fname="Gregory" mname="ALLEN" lname="Buck" email="gregory.buck@vcuhealth.org"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010169778" aid="1" auth="cit" login="hdavid" fname="Hagit" mname="G" lname="Skolnik david" email="hdavid@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010066953" aid="1" auth="cit" login="mgiovanni" fname="Maria" mname="Y" lname="Giovanni" email="mgiovanni@niaid.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=6081&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="VCU Buck DUC Agreement 032910 (2).docx" md5="e8e10261850d49e2bcac36f23fc02341" size="27063" modDate="2010-04-01T14:09:32-05:00" content-type="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.word"/></DUC><ConsentGroup uid="435" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="65" dac_name="NIAID " irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data can be used for any research related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="5814" whole_study_id="5814" phs="000256" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-12-18T17:54:01-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T11:10:40-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T11:10:40-05:00" handle="HMP_VaginalMicrobiome" num_participants="165"><StudyInfo accession="phs000256.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000256.v1.p1"><StudyNameEntrez>The Vaginal Microbiome: Disease, Genetics and the Environment</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The vagina is an interactive interface with the environment, and as such is covered by a protective epithelial surface.   This surface is colonized by bacteria and other microorganisms which, through a variety of mechanisms serve to further   protect the host from invasion by pathogens. Alterations in the normal vaginal microflora, particularly those associated   with bacterial vaginosis, are thought to contribute to risk of spontaneous pregnancy loss in the second trimester and   spontaneous preterm birth. Additionally, alterations in the vaginal microbiome may increase the likelihood of transmission   of certain agents including human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1). There are physiologic alterations in host   condition (e.g., menopause and pregnancy), which are beginning to be investigated as potential selective conditions   for change in the "normal" flora, and their impact on disease susceptibility and transmission remains to be more   definitively elucidated. The effects of chronically abnormal physiologic states (e.g., diabetes mellitus) on normal   vaginal flora have not been well described or studied. Finally, an almost unexplored area of inquiry is the genetic   contribution, including race/ethnicity, to the establishment and maintenance of a "normal" vaginal flora, under normal   and physiologically altered circumstances. Our research will shed light on how the vaginal microbiome contributes to   adverse obstetrical outcomes and sexually transmitted infections in diverse populations. This project addresses the   following questions:&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First: Do the genes of the host contribute to the composition of the vaginal microbiome?&lt;/b&gt;   We hypothesize that a woman&amp;#39;s genetic composition significantly affects the ability of certain commensal, parasitic   and pathogenic microbes to colonize and/or infect the genital tract. Thus, we will compare and quantify the microbial   populations inhabiting the vaginas of monozygotic and dizygotic twins from the Mid Atlantic Twin Registry, and, in   the process, address the question of whether there is a relationship between the microbiomes of the vagina, mouth   and GI tract.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Second: What changes in the vaginal microbiome are associated with common physiological perturbations or non-infectious   pathological states of the host?&lt;/b&gt;We hypothesize that "altered" physiologic (pregnancy, menopause) and pathologic   (chronic disease, hysterectomy) conditions, or environmental "exposures" (exogenous hormones, antibiotics, chronic   immunosuppressant, smoking; douching) can predictably alter the vaginal microenvironment. These alterations will lead   to changes in microbial populations within the vagina. Changes in the microbial populations may have impacts, positive   or more likely negative, on the spontaneous and future well-being of the affected individual. We are characterizing   the effects of these "altered" physiologic and pathologic conditions, and environmental exposures, on the composition   of the vaginal microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Third: What changes in the vaginal microbiome are associated with relevant infectious diseases and conditions?&lt;/b&gt;   We are testing the hypothesis that infectious diseases predictably alter the vaginal microbiome, and that these changes   have an impact on the disease susceptibility, process, and outcome. A predilection for bacterial vaginosis, vaginitis,   HIV infection, or other sexually transmitted diseases, is likely associated with a women&amp;#39;s vaginal microbial composition.   Thus, we will characterize samples from women with a variety of these infectious conditions to determine the contribution   of their micriobiomes to the disease process and susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;We are addressing these questions using a combination of high throughput &amp;#39;nextgen&amp;#39; sequencing technologies,   including the Roche 454 FLX and the upgraded Illumina Genome Analyzer II instruments currently installed in the Nucleic   Acids Research Facilities at VCU. Thus, segments of the 16S rRNA genes will be amplified from the complex samples taken   from various target sites in and around the vagina of each study participant. These segments will be sequenced and   subjected to taxonomic classification protocols to identify and quantify the bacterial taxa present in each sample.   Additionally, total DNA isolated from these samples will be subjected to shotgun sequence analysis to empirically   reconstruct the metabolic potential of these microbiomes. Finally, specific bacterial clones will be completely   sequenced and analyzed to associate the unavoidable strain and isolate diversity with the clinical phenotypes   presented.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Gregory Buck, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>1UH2AI083263</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>UH2 AI83263</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="5" name="NIAID" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GABUCK" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GABUCK" fname="Gregory" mname="ALLEN" lname="Buck" email="gregory.buck@vcuhealth.org"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010169778" aid="1" auth="cit" login="hdavid" fname="Hagit" mname="G" lname="Skolnik david" email="hdavid@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010066953" aid="1" auth="cit" login="mgiovanni" fname="Maria" mname="Y" lname="Giovanni" email="mgiovanni@niaid.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=6081&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="VCU Buck DUC Agreement 032910 (2).docx" md5="e8e10261850d49e2bcac36f23fc02341" size="27063" modDate="2010-04-01T14:09:32-05:00" content-type="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.word"/></DUC><ConsentGroup uid="126" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="65" dac_name="NIAID " irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Data can be used for any research related to the human microbiome.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>