<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5603" whole_study_id="5603" phs="000203" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-06-20T19:55:12-05:00" completedByGPADate="2018-05-17T10:58:55-05:00" modDate="2020-12-04T21:43:59-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-12-04T21:43:59-05:00" handle="eMERGE_PAD" num_participants="3372"><StudyInfo accession="phs000203.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000203.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75529" entrez_id="75529" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75531" entrez_id="75531" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>eMERGE Whole Genome Association Study of Peripheral Arterial Disease</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType></StudyTypes><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The Electronic Medical Record Phenotypes and Community-engaged Genomic Association Study aims to identify genetic variants  mediating susceptibility to peripheral arterial disease (PAD). The study leverages a biorepository of blood samples of 1688 PAD  cases and 1649 controls, and the electronic medical record (EMR) to annotate the biorepository.  PAD cases were identified  from the vascular laboratory database as having an ankle brachial index (ABI) &amp;lt;0.9 at rest or after exercise or having  non-compressible vessels. Controls were without prior history of atherosclerotic vascular disease and when tested, no evidence  of ischemia on a stress test. Phenotypes and environmental exposures including age, ethnicity, demographic and anthropometric  data are derived from the Mayo Electronic Medical Record (EMR).  Comorbidities were determined using algorithms for diabetes  and hypertension based on ICD-9 codes and medication use. Relevant laboratory data, including lipid levels, fasting blood  sugar and serum creatinine at index date or within a 1-year window of the index date were extracted. Medication classes  at index date were identified using Mayo&amp;#39;s Natural Language Processing-based system with RxNorm codification and NDF-RT  terminologies mapping. Smoking status was confirmed by natural language processing of clinical notes. Genotyping of ~600,000  SNPs across the genome is being conducted at the Broad Institute using the Illumina 660W platform. Statistical analyses  will be conducted to identify genetic variants associated with susceptibility to PAD.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Motivation for the study:&lt;/u&gt; Sequencing of the human genome, subsequent validation of single nucleotide  polymorphisms (SNPs), and advances in genotyping technology with decreasing costs have made possible studies that involve  genotyping of 500,000 or more SNPs across the genome (genome-wide association studies).  Combining genome-wide association  data with clinical information from the electronic medical record (EMR) provides new opportunities to identify genetic variants  that influence susceptibility to the common &amp;#39;complex&amp;#39; diseases that afflict humans; this knowledge can be used to improve  diagnosis, prognosis, prevention, and treatment of these diseases.  Existing health care systems can be leveraged for  genomic research given the potential for speed, efficiency, cost-effectiveness, and rapid translation to improved care of  patients.  However, optimal approaches for conducting genome-wide research in biorepositories to identify genes that  influence susceptibility to complex diseases have yet to be established.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;An important goal of the project is to delineate optimal strategies for extracting comprehensive and unbiased phenotype/exposure  data from the Mayo EMR, obtaining suitable consent for genome-wide association studies and broad data sharing, and interacting  with participants, communities, and IRBs.  We will attempt to define potential sources of bias and error in phenotypic and exposure  data derived from EMR, and identify approaches for improving data collection and standardization for genomic research.  Additionally, we will identify sources of concern among biorepository participants and other relevant groups regarding current  consent and consultation processes for application of genome-wide technologies, and for sharing of data; define needs for  additional consent and/or consultation, and recommend approaches for improving consent and consultation processes in  biorepository-based research.  Using state of the art statistical genetic methods, we will identify genetic variants associated  with two distinct phenotypes of PAD using phenotype and covariate information derived from EMR data.  We will make the  resulting data rapidly and widely available for research use and work collaboratively to share experience and expertise  across participating biorepositories.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Christopher G. Chute, MD, DRPH</AttrName><Institution>Mayo Clinic College of Medicine, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Institute"><AttrName>Mayo Clinic</AttrName><Institution>Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>HG04599-02</AttrName><Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping"><AttrName>U01-HG004424</AttrName><Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18385739"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18176561"/></Publication></Publications></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="CHUTE1" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="CHUTE1" fname="Christopher" mname="G" lname="Chute" email="chute@jhu.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>MAYO CLINIC ROCHESTERJOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2002367725" aid="1" auth="cit" login="rowleyrk" fname="Robb" mname="Kenneth" lname="Rowley" email="robb.rowley@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Sample statements for the acknowledgment of the eMERGE GWAS dataset(s) can be found at the following link: eMERGE dbGaP Acknowledgment Statements (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetPdf.cgi?document_name=eMERGE_Acknowledgement.pdf). Please include all Acknowledgment Statements relevant to the dataset(s) used in your analysis.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><DUC_SupplementaryDocuments><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=7394&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="eMERGE dbGaP Acknowledgment Statements 9-16-11.doc" md5="3b9dc779a5ce7e356907a6bbbe27d1c5" size="43008" modDate="2011-09-23T18:08:55-05:00" content-type="application/msword"/></DUC_SupplementaryDocuments><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (GSR are sensitive according to the Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="71" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Mayo Clinic" name="HR_MYO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Mayo Clinic Data may only be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.

Investigators must state in the Data Use Request their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from his or her study with the scientific community.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>