<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="17524" whole_study_id="5606" phs="000234" v="2" p="2" createDate="2015-10-26T17:01:36-05:00" completedByGPADate="2015-11-03T10:42:00-05:00" modDate="2020-01-21T13:41:48-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-01-21T13:41:48-05:00" handle="eMERGE_AD_Dementia" num_participants="3648"><StudyInfo accession="phs000234.v2.p2" parentAccession="phs000234.v2.p2"><BioProject id="PRJNA75533" entrez_id="75533" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75535" entrez_id="75535" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>eMERGE Genome Wide Association Study of Dementia</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType></StudyTypes><Funding>U01 HG004610-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="ERICLARSON" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="ERICLARSON" fname="Eric" mname="B" lname="Larson" email="larson.e@ghc.org"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTONGROUP HEALTH COOPERATIVE</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2002367725" aid="1" auth="cit" login="rowleyrk" fname="Robb" mname="Kenneth" lname="Rowley" email="robb.rowley@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Yuki" lname="Bradford" email="yub7@psu.edu"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011552437" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jawang" fname="Zhen" mname="Yuan" lname="Wang" email="zhen.wang@nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Sample statements for the acknowledgment of the eMERGE GWAS dataset(s) can be found at the following link: eMERGE dbGaP Acknowledgment Statements (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetPdf.cgi?document_name=eMERGE_Acknowledgement.pdf). Please include all Acknowledgment Statements relevant to the dataset(s) used in your analysis.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>none</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><DUC_SupplementaryDocuments><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=7402&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="eMERGE dbGaP Acknowledgment Statements 9-16-11.doc" md5="3b9dc779a5ce7e356907a6bbbe27d1c5" size="43008" modDate="2011-09-23T18:16:48-05:00" content-type="application/msword"/></DUC_SupplementaryDocuments><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_old_cert" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution responded that the study is not sensitive without submitting a new Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="72" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Group Health Seattle" name="HR_GHS" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>These data will be used only for health related research, including research to improve methods for health related research.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="73" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Dementia or Aging - Group Health Seattle" name="AGING_GHS" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Limited to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. For example, studies of conditions like cataract, diabetes, and psoriasis might be appropriate, while conditions like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and neuroblastoma might not be appropriate. Studies of conditions that are common in both children and the elderly, such as schizophrenia or depression, would not be appropriate if they focused on children or young adults. Studies focused primarily on pediatric populations are not permitted.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="74" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Marshfield Clinic" name="HR_MC" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.
No Permitted Use: Insurance companies</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="75" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Vanderbilt U" name="HR_VU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="401" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Mayo Clinic" name="HR_MYO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Mayo Clinic Data may only be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.

Investigators must state in the Data Use Request their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from his or her study with the scientific community.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="5606" whole_study_id="5606" phs="000234" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-06-20T20:01:38-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T09:23:58-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T09:23:58-05:00" handle="eMERGE_AD_Dementia" num_participants="3648"><StudyInfo accession="phs000234.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000234.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75533" entrez_id="75533" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75535" entrez_id="75535" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>eMERGE Genome Wide Association Study of Dementia</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType></StudyTypes><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The "Development and Use of Network Infrastructure for High-Throughput GWA Studies" project is collaboration between Group  Health Cooperative (GH), the University of Washington (UW), and the Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center (FHCRC).  It is one of  5 sites participating in The Electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE) Network funded by the National Human Genome Research  Institute (NHGRI) with additional funding from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS).  The overall eMERGE  project is designed to assess whether linking biorepositories of patients in healthcare delivery systems with electronic medical  records (EMRs) is an efficient strategy for high-throughput genome wide association (GWA) studies and whether information can  be pooled across sites.  The primary phenotype in the Group Health/UW Aging and Dementia eMERGE study project is dementia.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Phenotyped participants originated from four population-based sources.  Seattle-area members of GH (a large integrated health  care system in Washington State) consented and enrolled in 1) the University of Washington Alzheimer&amp;#39;s Disease Patient  Registry (ADPR) and 2) the Adult Changes in Thought (ACT) study, 3) Marshfield Clinic Personalized Medicine Research  Project (PMRP), a population-based DNA, plasma and serum biobank of 20,000 adults, 4) Vanderbilt&amp;#39;s BioVU, a de-identified  DNA biobank.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The ADPR (PI: Eric B. Larson; NIH/NIA U01 AG 006781) is a population-based registry of incident dementia cases designed to  identify all new dementia cases within GH from 1987 to 1996.  Potential dementia cases were identified through referrals from  primary care physicians, mental health services, and neurologists, as well as review of CT scans, neurology, emergency room,  geriatrician, and mental health clinic logs, and hospital discharge diagnoses.  Medical history, physical, laboratory testing,  and neuropsychological testing were performed on all consenting potential cases.  These data were reviewed by a consensus  conference including a neuropsychologist, study physicians, and an epidemiologist.  After discussion of the case, dementia  status is assigned using DSM-III-R criteria.  Alzheimer&amp;#39;s disease status was assigned using the National Institute of  Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke-Alzheimer&amp;#39;s Disease and Related Disorders Association (NINCDS-ADRDA)  criteria.  The study base of the ADPR population was stable with an attrition rate of less than 1%/year.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The ACT study (PI: Eric B. Larson; NIH/NIA U01 AG 006781) is an ongoing community-based cohort study designed to determine  the incidence of Alzheimer&amp;#39;s Disease (AD), other types of dementia, and cognitive impairment and to determine risk factors  for these conditions.  The original cohort of 2,581 was enrolled in 1994-1996.  An expansion cohort of 811 was enrolled  in 2000-2002.  Continuous enrollment to keep 2,000 persons enrolled and at-risk for dementia outcomes was begun in 2005.  To date the study has accrued more than 4,000 participants.  Dementia-free participants are enrolled in this cohort and  evaluated every two years by study personnel with many evaluations including an assessment of cognitive functioning  using the Cognitive Abilities Screening Instrument (CASI), which is an extended version of the Mini-Mental State  Examination that has been widely used in epidemiological studies of the elderly.  Persons with CASI scores lower  than 86 or in whom interviewers suspect unusual cognitive decline are followed up with dementia diagnostic evaluations  which include physical and neurological examinations and neuropsychological tests.  Medical records are reviewed, and  laboratory tests and neuroimaging are obtained if not available.  The dementia diagnoses and dementia subtypes are  determined during a consensus conference attended by the examining clinicians and other study physicians, a neuropsychologist,  and research nurse.  After discussion of the case, dementia status is assigned using DSM-IV criteria.  Alzheimer&amp;#39;s disease  status was assigned using NINCDS-ADRDA criteria.  Individuals diagnosed with dementia are seen again one year following diagnosis  using the same procedures.  Individuals not diagnosed with dementia are returned to the pool of at-risk individuals and are  seen at their next routinely scheduled biennial visit.  The ACT sub-sample is stable; for the original cohort, median  enrollment in GH was 19 years prior to joining the ACT study, and 85% of the cohort has &amp;#8805; 10 years of GH enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;DNA for the ADPR participants were obtained through a companion study, Genetic Differences in Cases and Controls  (PI: Walter Kukull; NIH/NIA R01 AG007584).  DNA obtained through both studies were extracted from blood using Gentra  Systems Puregene methods.  DNA concentration is determined by UV optical density. All samples are checked for quality  by OD 260/280 ratio.  For long-term storage, samples are aliquoted and stored at -70&amp;#176;C.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The Marshfield study, Personalized Medicine Research Project (PMRP), a population-based DNA, plasma and serum biobank  of 20,000 adults. PMRP was started in 2002 as a 3 Phase project.  Completed in April 2004, the objectives of Phase I were  to build and develop a large population-based biobank with DNA, plasma and serum samples to facilitate genomics research.  Phase 1 was also to educate, inform and consult with the Marshfield Epidemiologic Study Area population and communities  concerning potential studies, create the DNA foundation of the personalized medicine database and build the bioinformatics  tools to store securely and analyze genotypic and phenotypic data. Phase I tasks included operation of the ethics and  security advisory board, scientific advisory board and community advisory group. More than 18,000 residents aged 18 and  above from 19 different zip codes surrounding Marshfield, WI were invited to participate in Phase I.  After providing  written informed consent, participants completed brief questionnaires that included questions about demographics, some  environmental exposures, family history of disease, and adverse drug reactions, as well as family members living in the  area.  Participants provided 50ml of blood from which DNA was extracted and plasma and serum samples were stored. The  informed consent process allowed access to electronic medical records and included language about non-disclosure of personal  research results.  A tick-off box was included so that participants could either allow or decline subsequent recontact for  future research studied.  The objectives of Phase II are to create the phenotypic database, establish the scientific and  administrative infrastructure to support genetic mapping of the DNA and the initial discovery projects and genotype a  sufficient portion of the genetic material to support these discovery projects. The objectives of Phase III are to expand  the discovery projects, complete the genotyping of the genetic database and expand physician/health care provider education  and community consultation.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The Vanderbilt BioVU model uses discarded blood leftover from clinical care and de-identified clinical information, both  of which are tracked with a Research Unique Identifier that is permanently disconnected from the medical record number used to  generate it. The Vanderbilt IRB determined that the project does not qualify as "human subject" research under &amp;#167;46.102(f)(1)(2).  The program has been reviewed by OHRP twice (the latest immediately prior to launch), and the determination of the Vanderbilt  IRB that the project is consistent with the 8/10/2004 guidance has been validated.  The model includes a simple opt out mechanism  developed for patients who do not wish to have their samples included. Planning (including community involvement, ethics and  IRB discussions, focus groups, development of operating procedures and pilot studies to assess them) began in May 2004, and  the resource commenced sample collection in February 2007 and as of May 2009 contains approximately 56,000 samples. The current  resource will be available to all Vanderbilt investigators who sign a Data Use Agreement. The resource represents Vanderbilt&amp;#39;s  broad patient population and thus provides a potential resource for research in a range of common and rare diseases as well as  drug response or medication safety.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;BioVU patient protection model: There has been extensive involvement by the ethics community and the IRB to put in place  procedures to provide privacy protection. The overall protection plan is multifaceted and includes a combination of technology  and policy: (1) creation of the SD described above; (2) return of only the specific clinical data items requested by  investigators (rather than the complete de-identified chart); (3) submission of any specific proposed project to the IRB  and to a separate protocol review committee, both of which must approve; (4) implementing a Data Use Agreement that permits  only approved queries and data analyses, specifically prohibits attempts at re-identification (at the risk of institutional  sanctions), and mandates redeposit of all genetic information generated in a research study back into a genomic database;  and (5) tracking and auditing all use.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;table&gt;&lt;b&gt;Time line for Alzheimer Disease Patient Registry (ADPR):&lt;/b&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;1986&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;The Alzheimer&amp;#39;s Disease Patient Registry (ADPR) was established&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;1987&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;The ADPR started enrolling cases of dementia and AD who came to medical attention&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;ADPR enrollment stopped&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;/table&gt;  &lt;table&gt;&lt;b&gt;Time line for Adult Changes in Thought (ACT):&lt;/b&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;1994 - 1996&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;ACT enrolled the original cohort of 2,581 dementia-free individuals&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;2000 - 2002&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;ACT enrolled an expansion cohort of 811 dementia-free individuals&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;ACT began continuous enrollment of dementia-free individuals&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;/table&gt;  &lt;table&gt;&lt;b&gt;Time line for Vanderbilt&amp;#39;s BioVU study:&lt;/b&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;Feb 2007&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;Vanderbilt&amp;#39;s BioVU became operational&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;May 2009&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;Electronic phenotype algorithm applied to BioVU and cases identified.&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;/table&gt;  &lt;table&gt;&lt;b&gt;Time line for Marshfield study:&lt;/b&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;Sep 2002&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;Personalized Medicine Research Project (PMRP) launches recruitment.&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;Nov 2007&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;IRB officially approves the 1st GWAS study for Personalized Medicine to be included into a data-repository (dbGAP)&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;Dec 2007&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;Cut-off date for Cataract and Low HDL cohort enrollment&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;Apr 2009&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;Began Dementia phentyping process&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;Jun 2009&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;Selected samples to be genotyped&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;   &lt;tr&gt;       &lt;td&gt;Jun 2009&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;Samples shipped and received at CIDR &lt;/td&gt;   &lt;/tr&gt;  &lt;/table&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Eric Larson, MD, MPH</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-investigator, Principle Investigator at University of Washington"><AttrName>Gail Jarvik, MD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-investigator, Principle Investigator at Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center"><AttrName>Christopher Carlson, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Wylie Burke, MD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Paul K. Crane, MD, MPH</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Stephanie Malia Fullerton, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Walter Kukull, PhD, MS</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Ge Li, MD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Katherine M. Newton, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Research Associate"><AttrName>Leslie Spangler, VMD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Project Managers"><AttrName>Kelly Ehrlich</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Project Managers"><AttrName>Monica Fujii</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Programmers"><AttrName>David Carell, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Programmers"><AttrName>Robert Harrison</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Programmers"><AttrName>Gene Hart, MS</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Programmers"><AttrName>Noah Weston</AttrName><Institution>Group Health Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Research Scientist-UW"><AttrName>Susan Brown Trinidad, MA</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Research Scientist-UW"><AttrName>David Crosslin, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Research Scientist-Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center"><AttrName>Andrew McDavid</AttrName><Institution>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigator at Marshfield"><AttrName>Catherine A. McCarty, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Marshfield Clinic Research Foundation, Marshfield, WI, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigator at Marshfield"><AttrName>Peggy Peissig, MBA</AttrName><Institution>Marshfield Clinic Research Foundation, Marshfield, WI, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Principal Investigator at Vanderbilt"><AttrName>Dan Roden, MD</AttrName><Institution>Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigator at Vanderbilt"><AttrName>Josh Denny, MD</AttrName><Institution>Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>U01 HG004610-01 or RFA-HG-07-005 )</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping"><AttrName>U01HG004438-01</AttrName><Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><StudyURLs><Url name="eMERGE" url="https://www.mc.vanderbilt.edu/victr/dcc/projects/acc/index.php/About"/><Url name="Group Health Center for Health Studies" url="http://www.centerforhealthstudies.org/"/><Url name="Marshfield Clinic Research Foundation" url="http://www.marshfieldclinic.org/"/><Url name="Personalized Medicine Research Project" url="http://www.marshfieldclinic.org/pmrp"/></StudyURLs><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="2094380"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="12433261"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="8826994"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19176974"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18500243"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16418406"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17724290"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18047492"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19259965"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19386997"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="6610841"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="8054493"/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="McCarty CA, Wilke RA, Gianpietro PF, Wesbrook SD, Caldwell MD" title="Marshfield Clinic Peresonalized Medicine Researhc Project (PMRP): design, methods and recruitment for a large population-based biobank" journal="Future Medicine. 2005; 2(1):49-79" notes="http://www.marshfieldclinic.org/chg/pages/Proxy.aspx?Content=MCRF-Centers-PMRP-Pubs-McCartyMethodsCHG0522122553.1.pdf"/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="American Psychiatric Association" title="Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition." journal="Washington, DC: American Psychiatric Association; 1994."/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="American Psychiatric Association" title="Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Third Edition." journal="Washington, DC: American Psychiatric Association; 1987."/></Publication></Publications><Funding>U01 HG004610-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="ERICLARSON" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="ERICLARSON" fname="Eric" mname="B" lname="Larson" email="larson.e@ghc.org"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTONGROUP HEALTH COOPERATIVE</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014296067" aid="1" auth="cit" login="lir2" fname="Rongling" mname="" lname="Li" email="lir2@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011573826" aid="1" auth="cit" login="otawangv" fname="Vivian" mname="" lname="Ota Wang" email="otawangv@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=7431&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="eMERGE GWAS_DUC_09-23-2011.doc" md5="91f5bf3a10802db42028e9cca017f651" size="70656" modDate="2011-09-29T08:09:45-05:00" content-type="application/msword"/></DUC><DUC_PDF><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=17282&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="eMERGE GWAS_DUC_09-23-2011.doc.pdf" md5="9115b766b93eac0a1b296f08ae4e02e3" size="105960" modDate="2015-10-05T16:23:39-05:00" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><DUC_SupplementaryDocuments><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=7402&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="eMERGE dbGaP Acknowledgment Statements 9-16-11.doc" md5="3b9dc779a5ce7e356907a6bbbe27d1c5" size="43008" modDate="2011-09-23T18:16:48-05:00" content-type="application/msword"/></DUC_SupplementaryDocuments><ConsentGroup uid="72" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Group Health Seattle" name="HR_GHS" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>These data will be used only for health related research, including research to improve methods for health related research.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="73" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Dementia or Aging - Group Health Seattle" name="AGING_GHS" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Limited to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. For example, studies of conditions like cataract, diabetes, and psoriasis might be appropriate, while conditions like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and neuroblastoma might not be appropriate. Studies of conditions that are common in both children and the elderly, such as schizophrenia or depression, would not be appropriate if they focused on children or young adults. Studies focused primarily on pediatric populations are not permitted.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="74" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Marshfield Clinic" name="HR_MC" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.
No Permitted Use: Insurance companies</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="75" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Vanderbilt U" name="HR_VU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="401" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Health Research - Mayo Clinic" name="HR_MYO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Mayo Clinic Data may only be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.

Investigators must state in the Data Use Request their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from his or her study with the scientific community.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>