<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="6927" whole_study_id="5510" phs="000289" v="2" p="1" createDate="2011-04-21T11:43:21-05:00" modDate="2020-01-21T13:41:22-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-01-21T13:41:22-05:00" handle="VenousThrombosis" num_participants="2600"><StudyInfo accession="phs000289.v2.p1" parentAccession="phs000289.v2.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75937" entrez_id="75937" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75939" entrez_id="75939" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>GENEVA GWAS of Venous Thrombosis</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Funding>U01 HG004735-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="JHEIT1" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="JHEIT1" fname="John" mname="A" lname="Heit" email="heit.john@mayo.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>MAYO CLINIC ROCHESTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012410141" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wisea2" fname="Anastasia" mname="Leigh" lname="Wise" email="wisea2@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014190168" aid="1" auth="cit" login="sharopon" fname="Nataliya" mname="Rashidovna" lname="Sharopova" email="sharopon@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for the GWAS of Venous Thrombosis study was provided through the NIH Genes, Environment and Health Initiative [GEI] (U01HG004735). The GWAS of Venous Thrombosis study is one of the genome-wide association studies funded as part of the Gene Environment Association Studies (GENEVA) under GEI. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype cleaning, as well as with general study coordination, was provided by the GENEVA Coordinating Center (U01 HG004446). Assistance with data cleaning was provided by the National Center for Biotechnology Information. Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at the Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research, was provided by the NIH GEI (U01HG004438) and the NIH contract "High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&#8221;(HHSN268200782096C).  The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?db=gap through dbGaP accession number phs000289.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="447" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="5510" whole_study_id="5510" phs="000289" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-03-17T16:21:25-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T09:09:18-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T09:09:18-05:00" handle="VenousThrombosis" num_participants="2600"><StudyInfo accession="phs000289.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000289.v1.p1"><StudyNameEntrez>GENEVA GWAS of Venous Thrombosis</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Overview:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   &lt;u&gt;Our overall long-term goal is to determine risk factors for the complex (multifactorial) disease, venous thromboembolism (&lt;b&gt;VTE&lt;/b&gt;),   that will allow physicians to stratify individual patient risk and target VTE prophylaxis to those who would benefit most.&lt;/u&gt;  In this   genome-wide association case-control study (1300 cases and 1300 controls) we hope to identify susceptibility variants for VTE.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Mutations within genes encoding for important components of the anticoagulant, procoagulant, fibrinolytic, and innate   immunity pathways are risk factors for VTE.  We hypothesize that other genes within these four pathways or within other   pathways also are VTE disease-susceptibility genes.  Therefore, we performed a genome wide association (GWA) screen and analysis   using the Illumina 660W platform to identify SNPs within 1,300 clinic-based, non-cancer VTE cases primarily from Minnesota and   the upper Midwest USA, and 1300 clinic-based, unrelated controls frequency-matched on patient age, gender, myocardial   infarction/stroke status and state of residence.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;This is a subset of a slightly larger candidate gene study using 1500 case-control pairs to identify haplotype-tagging   SNPs (&lt;b&gt;ht&lt;/b&gt;-SNPs) in a large set of candidate genes (n~750) within the anticoagulant, procoagulant, fibrinolytic, and   innate immunity pathways.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Study Populations.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Cases&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/b&gt; VTE cases were consecutive Mayo Clinic outpatients with objectively-diagnosed deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and/or   pulmonary embolism (PE) residing in the upper Midwest and referred by Mayo Clinic physician to the Mayo Clinic Special   Coagulation Laboratory for clinical diagnostic testing to evaluate for an acquired or inherited thrombophilia, or to the   Mayo Clinic Thrombophilia Center. Any person contacted to be a control but discovered to have had a VTE was evaluated   for inclusion as a case.  Cases were primarily residents from Minnesota, Wisconsin, Iowa, Michigan, Illinois, North or   South Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas, Missouri and Indiana.  A DVT or PE was categorized as objectively diagnosed when (a) confirmed   by venography or pulmonary angiography, or pathology examination of thrombus removed at surgery, or (b) if at least one   non-invasive test (compression duplex ultrasonography, lung scan, computed tomography scan, magnetic resonance imaging)   was positive.  A VTE was defined as:    &lt;ol&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Proximal leg deep vein thrombosis (DVT), which includes the common iliac, internal iliac, external iliac,     common femoral, superficial [now termed "femoral"] femoral, deep femoral [sometimes referred to as "profunda" femoral]     and/or popliteal veins.  (Note:  greater and lesser saphenous veins, or other superficial or perforator veins, were     not included as proximal or distal leg DVT).&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Distal leg DVT (or "isolated calf DVT"), which includes the anterior tibial, posterior tibial and/or peroneal     veins.  (Note: gastrocnemius, soleal and/or sural [e.g., "deep muscular veins" of the calf] vein thrombosis     was not included as distal leg DVT).&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Arm DVT, which includes the axillary, subclavian and/or innominate (brachiocephalic) veins.  (Note:     jugular [internal or external], cephalic and brachial vein thrombosis was not included in "arm DVT").&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Hepatic, portal, splenic, superior or inferior mesenteric, and/or renal vein thrombosis. (Note: ovarian,     testicular, peri-prostatic and/or pelvic vein thrombosis was not included).&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Cerebral vein thrombosis (includes cerebral or dural sinus or vein, saggital sinus or vein, and/or transverse     sinus or vein thrombosis).&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Inferior vena cava (IVC) thrombosis&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Superior vena cava (SVC) thrombosis&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;li&gt;Pulmonary embolism&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;/ol&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Patients with VTE related to active cancer, antiphospholipid syndrome, inflammatory bowel disease, vasculitis, a rheumatoid   or other autoimmune disorder, a vascular anomaly (e.g., Klippel-Tr&amp;#233;naunay syndrome, etc.), heparin-induced thrombocytopenia,   or a mechanical cause for DVT (e.g., arm DVT or SVC thrombosis related to a central venous catheter or transvenous pacemaker,   portal and/or splenic vein thrombosis related to liver cirrhosis, IVC thrombosis related to retroperitoneal fibrosis, etc.),   with hemodialysis arteriovenous fistula thrombosis, or with prior liver or bone marrow transplantation were excluded.   &lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Controls&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/b&gt; A Mayo Clinic outpatient control group was prospectively recruited for this study. Controls   were frequency-matched on the age group (18-29, 30-39, 40-49, 50-59, 60-69, 70-79, and 80+ years), sex, myocardial   infarction/stroke status, and state of residence distribution of the cases. We selected clinic-based controls   using a controls&amp;#39; database of persons undergoing general medical examinations in the Mayo Clinic Departments   of General Internal Medicine or Primary Care Internal Medicine. Additionally persons undergoing evaluation at   the Mayo Clinic Sports Medicine Center, and the Department of Family Medicine were screened for inclusion as controls.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;This study is part of the Gene Environment Association Studies initiative   (GENEVA, &lt;a href="http://www.genevastudy.org" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.genevastudy.org&lt;/a&gt;) funded by the trans-NIH Genes,   Environment, and Health Initiative (GEI). The overarching goal is to identify novel genetic factors that contribute to   venous thrombosis through large-scale genome-wide association studies of 1,300 clinic-based, VTE cases and 1300   clinic-based, unrelated controls. Genotyping was performed at the Johns Hopkins University   Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR). Data cleaning and harmonization were done at the GEI-funded GENEVA Coordinating Center   at the University of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>John A. Heit, MD</AttrName><Institution>Division of Cardiovascular Diseases, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Mariza de Andrade, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Division of Biomedical Statistics and Informatics, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Julie M. Cunningham, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Genomics Shared Resource, Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Yan Asmann, PhD</AttrName><Institution>Division of Biomedical Statistics and Informatics, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>U01HG004735</AttrName><Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping"><AttrName>U01HG004438. NIH GEI grant "JH/CIDR Genotyping for Genome-Wide Association Studies"</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>U01 HG004735-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="JHEIT1" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="JHEIT1" fname="John" mname="A" lname="Heit" email="heit.john@mayo.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>MAYO CLINIC ROCHESTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012410141" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wisea2" fname="Anastasia" mname="Leigh" lname="Wise" email="wisea2@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011573826" aid="1" auth="cit" login="otawangv" fname="Vivian" mname="" lname="Ota Wang" email="otawangv@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=5927&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="GENEVA_DUC-GWAS of Venous Thrombosis updated 021610.docx" md5="74690280ce05d28b65512b0d6399ae2d" size="30773" modDate="2010-02-16T16:05:33-05:00" content-type="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.word"/></DUC><DUC_PDF><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=16550&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="GENEVA_DUC-GWAS of Venous Thrombosis updated 021610.docx.pdf" md5="0a384f368e2729a4333082b59e7caba7" size="110487" modDate="2015-08-31T15:58:47-05:00" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="48" CGType="cg_class_other" title="GWAS of Venous Thrombosis" name="GRU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>General Research Use: There are no uses that are specifically excluded from the informed consent document</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>