<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="8329" whole_study_id="5830" phs="000251" v="2" p="2" createDate="2012-07-26T14:29:03-05:00" modDate="2020-07-08T08:49:59-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-07-08T08:49:59-05:00" handle="HMP_CutaneousPsoriasis" num_participants=""><StudyInfo accession="phs000251.v2.p2" parentAccession="phs000251.v2.p2"><BioProject id="PRJNA46309" entrez_id="46309" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74929" entrez_id="74929" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>Evaluation of the cutaneous microbiome in psoriasis</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Funding>UH2 AR057506-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="18" name="NIAMS" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/><IC id="22" name="OD" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="BLASEM01" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="BLASEM01" fname="Martin" mname="J" lname="Blaser" email="martin.blaser@med.nyu.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY SCHOOL OF MEDICINE</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010166247" aid="1" auth="cit" login="bakerc" fname="Carl" mname="C" lname="Baker" email="bakerc@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001435773" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kirilushaag" fname="Anthony" mname="G" lname="Kirilusha" email="anthony.kirilusha@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for the National Institutes of Health was obtained from the Human Microbiome Project. Support was provided in the form of UH2 grant 1UH2AR057506-01. The datasets were obtained from dbGaP found at https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP study accession number phs000251. Data for the Study dbGaP were provided by Barbara Methe on behalf of all the participants in this project. Dr. Blaser and his collaborators request that publications resulting from these data cite their original publication: Alekseyenko AV, Perez-Perez GI, D&#8217;Souza A, Strober B, Gao Z, Bihan M, Li K, Methe B, Blaser MJ. Community differentiation of the cutaneous microbiota in psoriasis. Microbiome 2013; 1:31-8.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="130" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="61" dac_name="NIAMS" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>These data may be be used only for studies related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="5830" whole_study_id="5830" phs="000251" v="1" p="1" createDate="2010-01-07T12:50:57-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T10:38:22-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T10:38:22-05:00" handle="HMP_CutaneousPsoriasis" num_participants=""><StudyInfo accession="phs000251.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000251.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA46309" entrez_id="46309" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74929" entrez_id="74929" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>Evaluation of the cutaneous microbiome in psoriasis</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Psoriasis, a highly prevalent disease of humans of unknown cause, is a chronic inflammatory disorder primarily involving  skin, with distinctive clinical characteristics. With the newly developed tools that facilitate microbiome research, it now  is possible to assess whether the cutaneous microbiome plays a role in the pathogenesis of this disorder. Preliminary data  from our studies suggest that the cutaneous microbiome in psoriasis is complex and possibly different from normal. To deal  with this complexity, we propose to examine the cutaneous microbiome in relation to psoriasis with explorations at several  taxonomic and informatic levels. Our overall objective is to examine how changes in the normal cutaneous microbiome contribute  to the pathogenesis of psoriasis. Since causality is complex and often difficult to prove, and beyond the scope of this RFP,  our overall hypothesis is that there are alterations in the cutaneous microbiome in areas of skin affected by psoriasis in  comparison with the range observed in clinically unaffected areas, or in healthy persons. We also hypothesize that the  characteristics of the microbiome may affect clinical responses to the immunomodulatory agents used to treat psoriasis.  An alternative hypothesis is that effective treatment of psoriasis with systemic immunomodulatory agents will not substantially  affect the disordered microbial ecosystem.  Such observations would provide evidence for the roles of the microbiota in this  disorder. Since an important consideration in microbiome research is the optimal level (e.g. phylum, genus, species, strain,  gene) at which to examine a scientific question, and we are not yet certain what are the optimal levels for psoriasis,  this also will be examined. Our studies of psoriasis should allow development of both approaches and tools that will have  general utility for Microbiome research. To test our hypothesis, we propose the following specific aims: 1) To understand  the cutaneous microbiome species composition overlaying psoriatic lesions; 2) To investigate differences in metagenome  content for psoriatic lesions compared to normal skin; 3) To identify differences in the transcriptional profiles of the  microbiome and the host between normal skin and psoriatic lesions using high-throughput sequencing; and 4. To estimate the  effects of systemic immunomodulatory therapy for psoriasis on microbiome composition. In total, these studies should help  us understand the role of the microbiome in psoriasis pathogenesis.     &lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Psoriasis: clinical features and course.&lt;/b&gt; The initial lesions of psoriasis often appear gradually. The natural history  of psoriasis following initial symptoms includes unpredictable exacerbations and remissions, but no long-lasting freedom from  disease (1, 2). After the initial presentation, the disease usually consolidates into a chronic condition that sometimes  varies in intensity depending on season, worsening flares in colder, drier months, and the presence of concomitant infections.  Specific drugs (lithium, beta-blockers, alcohol, and withdrawal of systemic corticosteroids) may cause exacerbations of  disease (3). There are different types of psoriasis (2, 4). Chronic plaque psoriasis (psoriasis vulgaris [PV]), the most  common form, is marked by relatively static, thick, erythematous plaques with overlying scale, that may bleed if removed  (Auspitz sign). Although the plaques of psoriasis can appear anywhere on the skin, including trunk, extremities, genitals,  and face, the most commonly affected areas are the elbows and knees, lower back, and scalp (5).&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Other forms of psoriasis include &lt;b&gt;pustular psoriasis&lt;/b&gt;, an acute generalized eruption of sterile  pustules that may be accompanied by fever, lymphocytosis, hypocalcemia, and hypoalbuminemia. Pustular psoriasis  may be limited to the hands and fingers or the palms and soles. This form also appears during pregnancy (referred  to as "impetigo herpetiformis"). &lt;b&gt;Guttate psoriasis&lt;/b&gt; is characterized by small psoriatic papules  and plaques (0.5-1.5 cm) distributed diffusely over the trunk and proximal extremities. Streptococcal pharyngitis often  precedes guttate psoriasis, which commonly occurs in children and adolescents. &lt;b&gt;Erythrodermic psoriasis&lt;/b&gt; is characterized  by large erythematous patches (involving &amp;gt; 2/3 of the body surface area) without much overlying scale. Both the plaque  and pustular psoriasis variants may progress to this more severe form of the disease. Psoriasis may be associated with both  nail disease (onychodystrophy) and arthritis. Psoriatic arthritis involves asymmetrical joints including the vertebral  and sacroiliac joints. Psoriasis may be related to Reiter&amp;#39;s syndrome, a post-infectious disease constellation characterized  by urethritis, conjunctivitis, and arthritis. The frequency of inflammatory bowel disease is higher in patients with psoriasis,  and many patients with psoriatic arthritis have asymptomatic bowel inflammation. Hypertension, obesity, and diabetes  mellitus all are more common in psoriatic patients (6).&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The lesions of psoriasis display several primary features:  (i) &lt;b&gt;keratinocyte hyperplasia&lt;/b&gt;, characterized by thickening of the epidermis (acanthosis) and downward expansion of the rete  pegs, and associated with multiple overlying layers of scale (parakeratosis), and loss of the highest (granular) layer  of the epidermis; (ii) &lt;b&gt;inflammation&lt;/b&gt;, characterized by infiltrating neutrophils within the epidermis and in the scaly layer,  and lymphocytes, monocytes, and dendritic cells (DC) in the dermis and epidermis; and (iii) &lt;b&gt;ectatic blood vessels&lt;/b&gt;,  scattered in the upper layers of the dermis (creating telangiectasias within the papillary tips).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary of the pathophysiology of psoriasis.&lt;/b&gt; Psoriasis is characterized by immune dysregulation within the skin,  with the appearance of cutaneous autoreactive T cells (Th1) producing IFN-&amp;#947; and TNF-&amp;#946; (2). Induction of an inflammatory  milieu accelerates keratinocyte proliferation, leading to the development of epidermal hyperplasia (hyperkeratosis) and  angiogenic tissue reactions, progressing to the increased skin vascularization and inflammatory cellular infiltrates  that are the hallmarks of the psoriatic lesion. Normal skin contains both T lymphocytes and dendritic cells (7, 8)  indicating a potential for triggering of recall immune responses to environmental agents. The lesions of psoriasis  vulgaris contain large populations of leukocytes in addition to T cells and DCs, suggesting a function similar to  organized lymphoid tissue that perpetuates immune infiltrates in psoriatic plagues. There is no good animal model  for psoriasis; mouse and human skin are substantially different. Although some of the features of psoriasis  (e.g. keritinocyte hyperplasia)can be obtained in transgenic or knock-out mice, the phenotypes include features  of other dermatoses and neonatal lethality, which are not normally associated with human psoriasis (2). Thus, humans  are the best experimental subjects in whom to study psoriasis. The availability of effective, systemic immunomodulatory  agents in recent years has added resources for understanding pathogenesis (2, 3, 9, 10).&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Th1 T cell-inducing cytokines from dendritic cells (DC) drive the Th1 response observed in psoriasis,  and thus are prime targets for disease control with anti-cytokine reagents (11). IL-12 and IL-23 are related  molecules sharing a common p40 chain. Whereas IL-12 induces IFN-&amp;#947; and TNF-&amp;#946;, IL-23 induces IL-17 (12), TNF-&amp;#946;,  and IL-6; both play important roles in the psoriatic inflammatory response. IL-12/IL-23 production by cutaneous DC,  and thus to Th1-driven inflammation, may be due to Toll-like receptor (TLR) stimulation in the psoriatic lesions  (via NF-kB stimulation). The role of TLRs in recognizing microbes implies a possible pathway for microbial involvement,  at least in the final steps of psoriatic inflammation. The formation of a psoriatic plaque requires the continued  presence of activated T cells specific for an unknown inciting antigen, and persistent T cell expression of plaque-inducing  cytokines or cell-surface factors that form a "cytokine network." Thus, by the release of specific cytokines that act  as growth factors or by cell-to-cell interactions, activated intra-dermal T cells trigger keratinocyte  hyperproliferation. Subsequently, cytokines produced by stimulated nonlymphoid cells in the skin, such as  keratinocyte-derived IL-8, chemotactic for neutrophils, and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), inducing  the proliferation of the dermal vasculature, contribute to the inflammatory process. The triggers that initiate the  inflammatory pathways are unknown, however, immunomodulatory agents are effective therapies (3, 9, 13).&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Small subunit ribosomal RNA diversity.&lt;/b&gt; Investigation of ssrRNA gene sequences has revolutionized the study of  microbial ecology, leading to fundamental new insights into the diversity present in the prokaryotic world. Further, it  has underscored the major difference between the numbers of microbes cultured in the laboratory versus those present in  the environment; thus, it has become a well-accepted method for interrogating diversity in environmental samples (14, 15).  Diversity measurements using ssrRNA analyses have become an important complement to whole community or metagenomic  sequencing. New approaches are constantly being developed to address diversity questions with respect to microbial  communities, by focusing on the regions of the ribosomal operons that have the highest information content (see for example 16-19).  &lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Molecular analysis of the human microbiome has great potential (20-23). It has focused on fecal samples from  the human GI tract (24) at the J. Craig Venter Institute (JCVI), and other centers (25-28), and in relation to  disease (29, 30). Such studies have highlighted the extent of diversity associated with the human body. Other studies  of the human Microbiome have focused on the oral cavity (31), upper gastrointestinal tract (32, 33), vagina (34-36), and  on the skin (29, 37-41). Previous studies using ssrRNA approaches to study the diversity of the skin microbiome  indicate that a community of microorganisms is consistently associated with the skin and is dominated by a median level  of ~30-50 operational taxonomic units (OTUs) from the bacterial domain in individual hosts at any time in a single  site (37). In total, based on previous studies, &amp;gt;400 OTUs are predicted for superficial skin. The metabolic potential  of these microbes has not been well-studied despite their fundamental importance to health and disease states of skin.  Molecular studies of the fungal biota of the skin are in their infancy (99-41), but also are based on SSU sequences,  especially the ITS1 and ITS2 loci (42-44).&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Psoriasis is a chronic inflammatory disease of unknown cause affecting 3% of the U.S. population. Its cause  is unknown but there is evidence for extensive immune dysregulation. The role of the cutaneous microbiota in  psoriasis has not been extensively examined which is surprising based on the evidence for inflammatory changes  in tissues. Important questions that can be addressed by the proposed work include: Addressing such questions  should enhance our knowledge about the diagnosis, prevention, natural history, and treatment of psoriasis.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;   &lt;ol&gt;    &lt;li&gt;Are there organisms whose presence or absence is a marker for psoriasis?&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;Could a host&amp;#39;s status with respect to an organism reflect propensity to develop psoriasis?&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;Could specific organisms or their metabolic pathways correlate with psoriasis risk, and possibly    explain the altered immunity?&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;Since immunomodulatory therapy is not always successful, could the nature of the microbiota be a predictor    for treatment success or failure?&lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;Will treatment of psoriasis with systemic therapy clear any abnormal microbiota, or do the abnormalities    persist, suggesting a primary microbiological role in the disease?&lt;/li&gt;   &lt;/ol&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Martin J. Blaser, MD</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Bruce Strober, MD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Guillermo Perez-Perez, DSc</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Aieska Sousa, MD</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Stuart Brown, PhD</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Barbara A. Methe, PhD</AttrName><Institution>J Craig Venter Institute, Rockville, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Research Assistants"><AttrName>Elizabeth Camacho</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Research Assistants"><AttrName>Trisha Ali-Shaw</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Research Assistants"><AttrName>Ari Blumberg</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Researcher Associate"><AttrName>Zhan Gao, MD</AttrName><Institution>New York University Langone Medical Center, New York, New York, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding source"><AttrName>1UH2AR057506-01</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17903304"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19898491"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17293459"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="16891514"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18294199"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18571992"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19478181"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="18502944"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="20231444"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19004758"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="19892944"/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="Gao Z, Souza A, Perez Perez GI, Strober B, Blaser MJ" title="Cutaneous bacterial biota in psoriatic lesion and involved skin in patients with psoriasis" journal="American Society for Microbiology San Diego California, May 2010"/></Publication><Publication><Journal authors="Koren S, Durkin S, Gillis M, Hostetler J, MaCorrison J, Miller J, Perez-Perez G, Radune D, Tatz J, Torralba M, Blaser M, Sutton G, Nelson K" title="Two genomes for the price of one: Assembly of a mixed sample" journal="Human Microbiome Project, Houston TX January, 2010"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>UH2 AR057506-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="18" name="NIAMS" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/><IC id="22" name="OD" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="BLASEM01" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="BLASEM01" fname="Martin" mname="J" lname="Blaser" email="martin.blaser@med.nyu.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY SCHOOL OF MEDICINE</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010166247" aid="1" auth="cit" login="bakerc" fname="Carl" mname="C" lname="Baker" email="bakerc@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010161066" aid="1" auth="cit" login="sharrocw" fname="William" mname="J" lname="Sharrock" email="sharrocw@ep.niams.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=6491&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="Blaser DUC rev042110_NIAMS.docx" md5="225c733e5ac2bb460952e8f14f2dfefd" size="33517" modDate="2010-11-17T10:55:31-05:00" content-type="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.word"/></DUC><DUC_PDF><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=16590&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="Blaser DUC rev042110_NIAMS.docx.pdf" md5="fcb15460d5c9550f6569293352b0bc04" size="92879" modDate="2015-08-31T16:05:40-05:00" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="130" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="61" dac_name="NIAMS" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>These data may be be used only for studies related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>