<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="8335" whole_study_id="6088" phs="000258" v="3" createDate="2012-07-26T14:31:02-05:00" completedByGPADate="2018-05-09T10:31:21-05:00" modDate="2022-02-16T17:13:05-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-02-16T17:13:05-05:00" handle="HMP_GutObesity" num_participants="150"><StudyInfo accession="phs000258.v3" parentAccession="phs000258.v3"><BioProject id="PRJNA46319" entrez_id="46319" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74937" entrez_id="74937" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>The Thrifty Microbiome: The role of the gut microbiota in metabolic syndrome in the Amish</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="microbiome"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>microbiome</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Funding>UH2 DK083982-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="11" name="NIDDK" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/><IC id="22" name="OD" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="CMFRASER" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="CMFRASER" fname="Claire" mname="M" lname="Fraser-Liggett" email="cmfraser@som.umaryland.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND BALTIMOREINSTITUTE FOR GENOMIC RESEARCH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010067753" aid="1" auth="cit" login="karpr" fname="Robert" mname="W" lname="Karp" email="karpr@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2003219528" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pawlikowskals" fname="Ludmila" mname="Sylwia" lname="Pawlikowska" email="ludmila.pawlikowska@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS:  This study has not provided a suggested acknowledgement statement. However, Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="gsr_not_apply" gsr_mode_label="GSR does not apply (ONLY for studies that will not have genomic data in dbGaP)"/><ConsentGroup uid="359" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="60" dac_name="NIDDK" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Studies related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="14" name="completed_by_gpa" title="Completed by GPA"/></Study><Study uid="6582" whole_study_id="6088" phs="000258" v="2" p="1" createDate="2011-01-06T11:46:30-05:00" modDate="2022-02-16T17:13:05-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-02-16T17:13:05-05:00" handle="HMP_GutObesity" num_participants="150"><StudyInfo accession="phs000258.v2.p1" parentAccession="phs000258.v2.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA46319" entrez_id="46319" type="bp_data_submission"/><BioProject id="PRJNA74937" entrez_id="74937" type="bp_admin_access"/><StudyNameEntrez>The Thrifty Microbiome: The role of the gut microbiota in metabolic syndrome in the Amish</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Emerging evidence that the gut microbiota may contribute in important ways to human health and disease has led  us and others to hypothesize that both symbiotic and pathological relationships between gut microbes and their host  may be key contributors to obesity and the metabolic complications of obesity. Our "Thrifty Microbiome Hypothesis"  poses that gut microbiota play a key role in human energy homeostasis. Specifically, constituents of the gut microbial  community may introduce a survival advantage to its host in times of nutrient scarcity, promoting positive energy  balance by increasing efficiency of nutrient absorption and improving metabolic efficiency and energy storage.  However, in the presence of excess nutrients, fat accretion and obesity may result, and in genetically predisposed  individuals, increased fat mass may result in preferential abdominal obesity, ectopic fat deposition (liver, muscle),  and metabolic complications of obesity (insulin resistance, hypertension, hyperlipidemia). Furthermore, in the  presence of excess nutrients, a pathological transition of the gut microbial community may occur, causing leakage  of bacterial products into the intestinal lymphatics and portal circulation, thereby inducing an inflammatory state,  further aggravating metabolic syndrome traits and accelerating atherosclerosis. This pathological transition and  the extent to which antimicrobial leakage occurs and causes inflammatory and other maladaptive sequelae of obesity  may also be influenced by host factors, including genetics. In the proposed study, we will directly test the Thrifty  Microbiome Hypothesis by performing detailed genomic and functional assessment of gut microbial communities in intensively  phenotyped and genotyped human subjects before and after intentional manipulation of the gut microbiome. To address  these hypotheses, five specific aims are proposed: (1) enroll three age- and sex-matched groups from the Old Order  Amish: (i) 50 obese subjects (BMI &amp;gt; 30 kg/m2) with metabolic syndrome, (ii) 50 obese subjects (BMI &amp;gt; 30 kg/m2)  without metabolic syndrome, and (iii) 50 non-obese subjects (BMI &amp;lt; 25 kg/m2) without metabolic syndrome and  characterize the architecture of the gut microbiota from the subjects enrolled in this study by high-throughput  sequencing of 16S rRNA genes; (2) characterize the gene content (metagenome) to assess the metabolic potential of  the gut microbiota in 75 subjects to determine whether particular genes or pathways are correlated with disease  phenotype; (3) characterize the transcriptome in 75 subjects to determine whether differences in gene expression  in the gut microbiota are correlated with disease phenotype, (4) determine the effect of manipulation of the gut  microbiota with antibiotics on energy homeostasis, inflammation markers, and metabolic syndrome traits in 50 obese  subjects with metabolic syndrome and (5) study the relationship between gut microbiota and metabolic and cardiovascular  disease traits, weight change, and host genomics in 1,000 Amish already characterized for these traits and in whom  500K Affymetrix SNP chips have already been completed. These studies will provide our deepest understanding to date  of the role of gut microbes in terms of &amp;#39;who&amp;#39;s there?&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;what are they doing?&amp;#39;, and &amp;#39;how are they influencing host  energy homeostasis, obesity and its metabolic complications? PUBLIC HEALTH RELEVANCE: This study aims to unravel the  contribution of the bacteria that normally inhabit the human gastrointestinal tract to the development of obesity,  and its more severe metabolic consequences including cardiovascular disease, insulin resistance and Type II diabetes.  We will take a multidisciplinary approach to study changes in the structure and function of gut microbial communities  in three sets of Old Order Amish patients from Lancaster, Pennsylvania: obese patients, obese patients with metabolic  syndrome and non-obese individuals. The Old Order Amish are a genetically closed homogeneous Caucasian population of  Central European ancestry ideal for genetic studies. These works have the potential to provide new mechanistic insights  into the role of gut microflora in obesity and metabolic syndrome, a disease that is responsible for significant morbidity  in the adult population, and may ultimately lead to novel approaches for prevention and treatment of this disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;The obesity epidemic has stimulated a number of studies that have explored host and environmental factors  that affect energy balance.  Excessive fat tissue, especially in and around the abdomen is associated with  metabolic syndrome (MetS) and its attendant features of dyslipidemia, elevated blood pressure, insulin  resistance, abnormalities in blood clotting, and elevated circulating levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines.  Great inter-individual variation is apparent in propensity toward obesity, location where excess fat is deposited,  and the extent to which this results in adverse health outcomes. Comparison of gut microbiota in obese and lean  mice and humans, suggest that the gut microbial communities may contribute to overall energy balance in man.  To explore the possible dysbiosis of gut microbiota in obesity and its metabolic complications, we will study  obese and non-obese Old Order Amish subjects.  Using a number of approaches we will characterize the genomic  architecture of the gut microbiota at baseline, and after manipulation with antibiotics, to access its role  in energy homeostasis, inflammation, and MetS traits.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Claire Fraser-Liggett</AttrName><Institution>University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigator"><AttrName>Alan Shuldiner</AttrName><Institution>University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>1UH2DK083982-01</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>UH2 DK083982-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="11" name="NIDDK" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/><IC id="22" name="OD" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="CMFRASER" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="CMFRASER" fname="Claire" mname="M" lname="Fraser-Liggett" email="cmfraser@som.umaryland.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND BALTIMOREINSTITUTE FOR GENOMIC RESEARCH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010067753" aid="1" auth="cit" login="karpr" fname="Robert" mname="W" lname="Karp" email="karpr@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2003219528" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pawlikowskals" fname="Ludmila" mname="Sylwia" lname="Pawlikowska" email="ludmila.pawlikowska@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS:  This study has not provided a suggested acknowledgement statement. However, Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.</acknowledgement_statement><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><ConsentGroup uid="359" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Human Microbiome Research" name="HMP" dac_uid="60" dac_name="NIDDK" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Studies related to the human microbiome.
Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="6088" whole_study_id="6088" phs="000258" v="1" p="1" createDate="2010-04-02T18:09:23-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T10:08:23-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T10:08:23-05:00" handle="HMP_GutObesity" num_participants="150"><StudyInfo accession="phs000258.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000258.v1.p1"><StudyNameEntrez>The Thrifty Microbiome: The role of the gut microbiota in metabolic syndrome in the Amish</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>sra</StudyType><StudyType>metagenomics</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Description>
&lt;p&gt;Emerging evidence that the gut microbiota may contribute in important ways to human health and disease has led   us and others to hypothesize that both symbiotic and pathological relationships between gut microbes and their host   may be key contributors to obesity and the metabolic complications of obesity. Our "Thrifty Microbiome Hypothesis"   poses that gut microbiota play a key role in human energy homeostasis. Specifically, constituents of the gut microbial   community may introduce a survival advantage to its host in times of nutrient scarcity, promoting positive energy   balance by increasing efficiency of nutrient absorption and improving metabolic efficiency and energy storage.   However, in the presence of excess nutrients, fat accretion and obesity may result, and in genetically predisposed   individuals, increased fat mass may result in preferential abdominal obesity, ectopic fat deposition (liver, muscle),   and metabolic complications of obesity (insulin resistance, hypertension, hyperlipidemia). Furthermore, in the   presence of excess nutrients, a pathological transition of the gut microbial community may occur, causing leakage   of bacterial products into the intestinal lymphatics and portal circulation, thereby inducing an inflammatory state,   further aggravating metabolic syndrome traits and accelerating atherosclerosis. This pathological transition and   the extent to which antimicrobial leakage occurs and causes inflammatory and other maladaptive sequelae of obesity   may also be influenced by host factors, including genetics. In the proposed study, we will directly test the Thrifty   Microbiome Hypothesis by performing detailed genomic and functional assessment of gut microbial communities in intensively   phenotyped and genotyped human subjects before and after intentional manipulation of the gut microbiome. To address   these hypotheses, five specific aims are proposed: (1) enroll three age- and sex-matched groups from the Old Order   Amish: (i) 50 obese subjects (BMI &amp;gt; 30 kg/m2) with metabolic syndrome, (ii) 50 obese subjects (BMI &amp;gt; 30 kg/m2)   without metabolic syndrome, and (iii) 50 non-obese subjects (BMI &amp;lt; 25 kg/m2) without metabolic syndrome and   characterize the architecture of the gut microbiota from the subjects enrolled in this study by high-throughput   sequencing of 16S rRNA genes; (2) characterize the gene content (metagenome) to assess the metabolic potential of   the gut microbiota in 75 subjects to determine whether particular genes or pathways are correlated with disease   phenotype; (3) characterize the transcriptome in 75 subjects to determine whether differences in gene expression   in the gut microbiota are correlated with disease phenotype, (4) determine the effect of manipulation of the gut   microbiota with antibiotics on energy homeostasis, inflammation markers, and metabolic syndrome traits in 50 obese   subjects with metabolic syndrome and (5) study the relationship between gut microbiota and metabolic and cardiovascular   disease traits, weight change, and host genomics in 1,000 Amish already characterized for these traits and in whom   500K Affymetrix SNP chips have already been completed. These studies will provide our deepest understanding to date   of the role of gut microbes in terms of &amp;#39;who&amp;#39;s there?&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;what are they doing?&amp;#39;, and &amp;#39;how are they influencing host   energy homeostasis, obesity and its metabolic complications? PUBLIC HEALTH RELEVANCE: This study aims to unravel the   contribution of the bacteria that normally inhabit the human gastrointestinal tract to the development of obesity,   and its more severe metabolic consequences including cardiovascular disease, insulin resistance and Type II diabetes.   We will take a multidisciplinary approach to study changes in the structure and function of gut microbial communities   in three sets of Old Order Amish patients from Lancaster, Pennsylvania: obese patients, obese patients with metabolic   syndrome and non-obese individuals. The Old Order Amish are a genetically closed homogeneous Caucasian population of   Central European ancestry ideal for genetic studies. These works have the potential to provide new mechanistic insights   into the role of gut microflora in obesity and metabolic syndrome, a disease that is responsible for significant morbidity   in the adult population, and may ultimately lead to novel approaches for prevention and treatment of this disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;The obesity epidemic has stimulated a number of studies that have explored host and environmental factors   that affect energy balance.  Excessive fat tissue, especially in and around the abdomen is associated with   metabolic syndrome (MetS) and its attendant features of dyslipidemia, elevated blood pressure, insulin   resistance, abnormalities in blood clotting, and elevated circulating levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines.   Great inter-individual variation is apparent in propensity toward obesity, location where excess fat is deposited,   and the extent to which this results in adverse health outcomes. Comparison of gut microbiota in obese and lean   mice and humans, suggest that the gut microbial communities may contribute to overall energy balance in man.   To explore the possible dysbiosis of gut microbiota in obesity and its metabolic complications, we will study   obese and non-obese Old Order Amish subjects.  Using a number of approaches we will characterize the genomic   architecture of the gut microbiota at baseline, and after manipulation with antibiotics, to access its role   in energy homeostasis, inflammation, and MetS traits.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Claire Fraser-Liggett</AttrName><Institution>University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigator"><AttrName>Alan Shuldiner</AttrName><Institution>University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>1UH2DK083982-01</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>UH2 DK083982-01</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="11" name="NIDDK" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/><IC id="22" name="OD" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="CMFRASER" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="CMFRASER" fname="Claire" mname="M" lname="Fraser-Liggett" email="cmfraser@som.umaryland.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND BALTIMOREINSTITUTE FOR GENOMIC RESEARCH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010067753" aid="1" auth="cit" login="karpr" fname="Robert" mname="W" lname="Karp" email="karpr@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><DUC><File uri="dbgapssws.cgi?blob_id=6246&amp;file=get&amp;page=file" filename="HMP_GutObesity_FraserAmish.doc" md5="3ed2ae4b27394380f382066efeea27ff" size="71168" modDate="2010-06-22T16:34:09-05:00" content-type="application/msword"/></DUC><ConsentGroup uid="169" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Microbiome" name="HMP" dac_uid="60" dac_name="NIDDK" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Studies related to the human microbiome</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>