<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5628" whole_study_id="5628" phs="000207" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-07-02T09:02:21-05:00" modDate="2020-03-04T21:37:18-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-03-04T21:37:18-05:00" handle="CGEMS_ProstateCancer"><StudyInfo accession="phs000207.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000207.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75549" entrez_id="75549" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75551" entrez_id="75551" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>CGEMS Prostate Cancer</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The Cancer Genetic Markers of Susceptibility (CGEMS) prostate cancer genome-wide association study (GWAS) included genotyping   approximately 550,000 SNPs (Phase 1A with HumanHap300 and Phase 1B HumanHap240, both from Illumina, San Diego, CA) in 1,172   prostate cancer patients and 1,157 controls of European ancestry from the Prostate, Lung, Colon and Ovarian   (PLCO, &lt;a href="http://www.cancer.gov/prevention/plco/" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.cancer.gov/prevention/plco/&lt;/a&gt;) Cancer   Screening Trial. The original analysis published in Nature Genetics [PMID: &lt;a href="http://ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17401363" target="_blank"&gt;17401363&lt;/a&gt;]   included 2,282 subjects. After improvement and revisions of the original analysis, 2,252 subjects were submitted to dbGaP.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;The PLCO Cancer Screening Trial is a large, randomized controlled trial of approximately 155,000 men and women. Participants are    randomized to either a screening or control arm.  Each year after enrollment, subjects are asked to notify the study of any cancers    diagnosed in the past year using the Annual Study Update (ASU).&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;p&gt;The trial is designed to test the efficacy of cancer screening to prevent early death from prostate, lung, colorectal and ovarian    cancer. The collection of questionnaire data and biospecimens (e.g., repeated blood samples and in some instances, buccal cell    samples) allows investigation of early markers for cancer as well as etiology of common cancers.&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;p&gt;PLCO enrollment began in 1993 and ended in 2001. Recruitment included men and women, aged 55 to 74 with no reported history of    prostate, lung, colon and ovarian cancer, although prior diagnoses of other cancers were acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;p&gt;The CGEMS cohort consisted of men enrolled in the screening arm of the PLCO Trial who:&lt;br/&gt;     &lt;ol&gt;      &lt;li&gt;were White and non-Hispanics;&lt;/li&gt;      &lt;li&gt;had no prior history of prostate of cancer before randomization;&lt;/li&gt;      &lt;li&gt;had at least one PLCO prostate cancer screen (PSA) before October 1, 2003;&lt;/li&gt;      &lt;li&gt;had completed a Baseline Questionnaire about risk factors for cancer;&lt;/li&gt;      &lt;li&gt;had signed informed consent;&lt;/li&gt;      &lt;li&gt;had provided a blood sample with       &lt;ol&gt;        &lt;li&gt;at least 11 &amp;#181;g DNA&lt;/li&gt;        &lt;li&gt;at least 1 vial of buffy coat, or&lt;/li&gt;        &lt;li&gt;at least 7 vials of whole blood was available; &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;/ol&gt;      &lt;/li&gt;      &lt;li&gt;for controls, had returned at least one Annual Study Update (ASU).&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;/ol&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Based on these criteria, 28,521 men were included in the CGEMS sub-cohort.&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;p&gt;CGEMS distinguishes between non-aggressive and aggressive cases of prostate cancer at the time of diagnosis. The two subtypes are defined as follows:&lt;br/&gt;     &lt;ol&gt;      &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Non-aggressive&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;: cases with a Gleason Score &amp;lt; 7 and Stage &amp;lt; III.&lt;/li&gt;      &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Aggressive&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;: cases with a Gleason Sore &amp;#8805; 7 or Stage &amp;#8805; III.&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;/ol&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Study enrollment began on October 1, 1993. Consequently, study years in the PLCO Trial are counted according to the Federal    fiscal year, Oct 1 to the next September 30.&lt;/p&gt;    &lt;p&gt;All men diagnosed with prostate cancer between enrollment and the end of FY2001 were considered for inclusion in CGEMS.  Because of    our interest in the clinically more significant, but less common aggressive form of prostate cancer, we increased the fraction    of aggressive cases in the CGEMS case series by extending eligibility for cases diagnosed with aggressive prostate cancer through    the end of FY2003.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Lead Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Stephen J. Chanock</AttrName><Institution>Laboratory of Translational Genomics, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute and Core Genotyping Facility, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics (DCEG), National Cancer Institute (NCI), National Institutes of Health, Department (NIH), Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS), Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Meredith Yeager</AttrName><Institution>SAIC-Frederick, National Cancer Institute (NCI)-Frederick Cancer Research and Development Center, Frederick, MD, USA and Core Genotyping Facility, DCEG, NCI, NIH, DHHS, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigators"><AttrName>David J. Hunter</AttrName><Institution>Channing Laboratory, Department of Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Margaret Tucker</AttrName><Institution>DCEG, NCI, NIH, DHHS, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Daniela S. Gerhard</AttrName><Institution>Office of Cancer Genomics, NCI, NIH, DHHS, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Joseph F. Fraumeni</AttrName><Institution>DCEG, NCI, NIH, DHHS, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Robert Hoover</AttrName><Institution>DCEG, NCI, NIH, DHHS, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Principal Investigators"><AttrName>Gilles Thomas</AttrName><Institution>DCEG, NCI, NIH, DHHS, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><StudyURLs><Url name="Cancer Genetic Markers of Susceptibility (CGEMS)" url="http://cgems.cancer.gov/"/></StudyURLs><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="17401363"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>Z01 SC010083-11</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="0010114442" aid="1" auth="cit" login="chanocks" fname="Stephen" mname="J" lname="Chanock" email="chanocks@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011217741" aid="1" auth="cit" login="tobiasg" fname="Geoffrey" mname="Scott" lname="Tobias" email="tobiasg@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS:  This study has not provided a suggested acknowledgement statement. However, Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_old_cert" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution responded that the study is not sensitive without submitting a new Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="80" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Research related to adult diseases and methods" name="CADM" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>The informed consent document signed by the CGEMS prostate cancer study participants allows use of these data by investigators for discovery and hypothesis generation in the investigation of the genetic contributions to cancer and other adult diseases as well as development of novel analytical approaches for GWAS.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>