<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="5776" whole_study_id="5776" phs="000272" v="1" p="1" createDate="2009-11-19T11:29:22-05:00" modDate="2020-07-08T08:49:53-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-07-08T08:49:53-05:00" handle="NIAMS_Behcet" num_participants="2527"><StudyInfo accession="phs000272.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000272.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75609" entrez_id="75609" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75611" entrez_id="75611" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>Genome-wide association study of Behcet's disease in the Turkish population</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Beh&amp;#231;et&amp;#39;s disease (BD) is a genetically complex multisystem disease of unknown etiology,   characterized by recurrent inflammatory attacks affecting orogenital mucosa, eyes, skin, joints, blood vessels, and less   frequently, the central nervous system and gastrointestinal tract.  Family studies suggest a genetically complex contribution   to BD.  With the exception of HLA-B51, which explains less than 20% of the genetic risk, the identities of alleles that are   responsible for the complex inheritance of this disease have remained unclear.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Aim&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To identify genes that contribute to BD susceptibility.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Methods&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A genome-wide association study was undertaken with 311,459 informative and high quality SNPs in a   collection of 1215 BD patients and 1278 healthy controls from Turkey using a beadchip microarray assay (Infinium SNP   genotype assay, Illumina).  HLA-B types were determined with a reverse sequence-specific oligonucleotide method (One Lambda).   Regions with evidence for association were fine-mapped using Sequenom iPLEX gold assays.  Disease-associated SNPs were   genotyped in additional ethnically matched case/control collections from diverse genetic backgrounds, including a total   of 2430 cases and 2660 controls, using TaqMan SNP genotype assays.  Association data were combined in a meta-analysis   of all the collections.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Results&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We confirmed the known association with HLA-B51 and found evidence for a second, independent   susceptibility locus in the Class I region of the MHC. In addition, we identified one SNP with genome-wide evidence for   disease association (P &amp;lt; 5.0 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-8&lt;/sup&gt;) within the gene encoding the immunoregulatory cytokine, interleukin-10 (IL10). A   meta-analysis of the data from all the collections established associations with the IL10 variant (rs1518111,   P = 3.54 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-18&lt;/sup&gt;, odds ratio 1.45 with 95% confidence interval 1.34 to 1.58) and with a variant located between the   interleukin-23 receptor (IL23R) and interleukin 12 receptor &amp;#946;2 (IL12RB2) genes (rs924080, P = 6.69 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-9&lt;/sup&gt;, odds   ratio 1.28 with 95% confidence interval 1.18 to 1.39). The disease-associated IL10 variant was associated with diminished   mRNA expression and low protein production by cells obtained from healthy blood donors.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These data suggest that genetically encoded low production of IL-10 increases risk of BD and   suggest novel interventional targets in the IL-10 and IL-23 pathways.&lt;/p&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Note: The submitted data are the genotypes of the 311,459 SNPs in 1215 cases and 1278 controls.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Elaine F. Remmers, PhD</AttrName><Institution>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Ahmet Gul, MD</AttrName><Institution>Faculty of Medicine-Division of Rheumatology, Istanbul University, Istanbul, Turkey</Institution></Header><Header title="Co-Investigators"><AttrName>Daniel L. Kastner, MD, PhD</AttrName><Institution>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="1970380"/></Publication><Publication><Pubmed pmid="20622878"/></Publication></Publications><Funding>Z01 AR041139-05</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="18" name="NIAMS" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="0010056446" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kastnerd" fname="Daniel" mname="Lindsley" lname="Kastner" email="kastnerd@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011562422" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wangy1" fname="Yan" mname="" lname="Wang" email="wangy1@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001435773" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kirilushaag" fname="Anthony" mname="G" lname="Kirilusha" email="anthony.kirilusha@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>The data used for the analyses described in this paper were obtained from the database of Genotypes and Phenotypes (dbGaP), at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap. Genotype and phenotype data for the Genome-wide Association Study of Beh&#231;et&#8217;s Disease in the Turkish Population (dbGaP accession number phs000272) were provided by Daniel L. Kastner and Elaine F. Remmers. Funding support for the original study was provided by the Intramural Research Program of the National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases of the US National Institutes of Health, by the Istanbul University Research Fund, by the UK Beh&#231;et&#8217;s Syndrome Society, and by other sources as detailed in Nature Genetics 2010 Aug;42(8):698-702. Genome-wide association study identifies variants in the MHC class I, IL10, and IL23R-IL12RB2 regions associated with Beh&#231;et's disease. Remmers EF, Cosan F, Kirino Y, Ombrello MJ, Abaci N, Satorius C, Le JM, Yang B, Korman BD, Cakiris A, Aglar O, Emrence Z, Azakli H, Ustek D, Tugal-Tutkun I, Akman-Demir G, Chen W, Amos CI, Dizon MB, Kose AA, Azizlerli G, Erer B, Brand OJ, Kaklamani VG, Kaklamanis P, Ben-Chetrit E, Stanford M, Fortune F, Ghabra M, Ollier WE, Cho YH, Bang D, O'Shea J, Wallace GR, Gadina M, Kastner DL, G&#252;l A.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="143" CGType="cg_class_other" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="61" dac_name="NIAMS" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>This dataset may be used for any type of biomedical research.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>