<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="7163" whole_study_id="7163" phs="000385" v="1" p="1" createDate="2011-07-20T09:50:52-05:00" modDate="2021-07-13T22:01:39-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2021-07-13T22:01:39-05:00" handle="EpigeneticColorectalCancer" num_participants="100"><StudyInfo accession="phs000385.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000385.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75343" entrez_id="75343" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75345" entrez_id="75345" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>Epigenetic Profiling of Human Colorectal Cancer</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="geo"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>geo</StudyType><StudyType>trace</StudyType><StudyType>analysis</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages><SraStorage location="NCBI"/></SraStorages><Description>
&lt;p&gt;DNA methylation, together with chromatin modifications, constitute the epigenome that functions to regulate gene expression      and genome integrity. DNA methylation alterations are ubiquitous in human cancers, as many genes acquire DNA methylation in a      cancer-specific manner. DNA methylation at these sites in the genome of cancer cells not only serves as a marker for tumor      identification, but together with gene mutation and gene expression data, can also be used to describe subsets of tumors of      the same organ source. We have previously shown distinct human colorectal cancer subtypes based on DNA methylation differences.      Correlating these DNA methylation differences with clinical co-variates will serve to further understand how these distinct      subtypes are generated. We have collected 100 colorectal tumor tissues (for which clinical information is known) and have      obtained (unprotected) genome-wide DNA methylation and chromatin modification information for each sample for the purposes      of identifying and classifying unique tumor subtypes of colorectal cancers. In addition, we have determined mutations of      key genes relevant to colorectal cancer as well as gene expression profiles. We will use the clinical data for each      de-identified sample to correlate with the DNA methylation, mutation and gene expression information so as to      understand the driving forces behind these distinct colorectal subtypes.&lt;/p&gt;     &lt;p&gt;We have selected the most promising tumors for whole-genome bisulfite sequencing using next-generation sequencing technology      to obtain complete maps of colon cancer methylomes. Researchers will be unable to identify the subjects because the samples      and associated information have been de-identified and anonymized by the tissue source site. In addition, upon receipt by      the USC Epigenome Center, we have assigned new random identifiers for each sample. The data generated using these new codes      are not traceable to the patient identity.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;December 2007: Received approval of USC Health Sciences Institutional Review Board to use Ontario Tumor Bank      colorectal tumor samples for DNA methylation and gene expression profiling.&lt;/p&gt;     &lt;p&gt;March 2009: Received approval of Ontario Cancer Research Ethics Board to sequence individual samples using      Whole-genome bisulfite-seq and deposit data in dbGaP.&lt;/p&gt;     &lt;p&gt;April 2011: Received approval of Ontario Cancer Research Ethics Board and USC Health Sciences Institutional Review Board      to continue Bisulfite-sequencing until March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>Peter W. Laird, PhD</AttrName><Institution>University of Southern California</Institution></Header></Attributions><StudyURLs><Url name="USC Epigenome Center" url="http://epigenome.usc.edu"/></StudyURLs><Publications><Publication><Pubmed pmid="21659424"/></Publication></Publications></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="PETER_W_LAIRD" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="PETER_W_LAIRD" fname="Peter" mname="W" lname="Laird" email="peter.laird@vai.org"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>VAN ANDEL RESEARCH INSTITUTEUNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001203526" aid="1" auth="cit" login="cagaananef" fname="Emilie" mname="Charlisse F" lname="Caga-Anan" email="charlisse.caga-anan@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for the Epigenetic Profiling of Human Colorectal Cancer (EPHCC) was provided by a generous private donation from the Kenneth T. and Eileen L. Norris Foundation. Collection and de-identification of patient samples was conducted by the Ontario Institute for Cancer Research and approved by the Ontario Cancer Research Ethics Board.</acknowledgement_statement><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="523" CGType="" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>The data will only be used for research purposes.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>