<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="6146" whole_study_id="6146" phs="000305" v="1" p="1" createDate="2010-04-26T15:42:31-05:00" modDate="2019-05-08T13:06:49-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-05-08T13:06:49-05:00" handle="MayoBC_Ingle" num_participants=""><StudyInfo accession="phs000305.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000305.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75693" entrez_id="75693" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75695" entrez_id="75695" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>PGRN-RIKEN Mayo-NSABP Prevention Study</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><Description>
&lt;p&gt;The primary aim of this study is to identify genes related to the occurrence of breast events, defined as occurrence  of invasive breast cancer or ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS), in women at high risk of developing breast cancer  who have received a Selective Estrogen Receptor Modulator (SERM - tamoxifen or raloxifene) on the  National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP) P-1 or P-2 trials. Cases and controls were selected  from the tamoxifen arm in the P-1 and from the tamixifen and raloxifene arms in the P-2 trial. For the P-1 trial,  cases and controls were required to be 50 years of age or older at time of entry.  Cases were females who  experienced an invasive breast cancer or DCIS on P-1 or P-2. Controls were females who did not experience an invasive  breast cancer or DCIS.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;A nested matched case-control design was used, with matching on the following factors:  1) trial and treatment  arm (P-1 tamoxifen, P-2 tamoxifen, P-2 raloxifene); 2) age at trial entry (when controls could not be exactly matched  on age, we incremented the age of matching by +/- 1 year, in sequence until a match was obtained without exceeding +/- 5  years);  5-year predicted breast cancer risk based on the Gail model ( &amp;lt;2.00%, 2.01-3.00, 3.01-5.00, &amp;gt;5.01), 3) history  of lobular carcinoma in situ (yes vs. no); 4) history of atypical hyperplasia in breast (yes vs. no); 5) time on  study (controls must be on study at least as long as the time to diagnosis of the breast event for the case).  Because 94.2% of the participants on P-1 and P-2 treated with tamoxifen or raloxifene were Caucasian, this study  was restricted to only Caucasians.&lt;/p&gt;     &lt;p&gt;Two cases and two controls were randomly chosen as duplicates for quality control of genotype concordance. The  DNA samples were plated into 96-well plates, with cases and controls randomly distributed across the plates. A  Caucasian parent-child CEPH trio from the HapMap project was included to check for Mendelian transmission of alleles.  Genotypes were determined by the RIKEN Center for Genomic Medicine with the Illumina Human610-Quad.&lt;/p&gt;
 </Description><StudyHistory>
&lt;p&gt;March 17, 2009: Protocol approved by the Cancer Prevention and Control Protocol Review Committee, Division  of Cancer Prevention, Community Oncology and Prevention Trials Research Group, National Cancer Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
 </StudyHistory><Attributions><Header title="Principal Investigator"><AttrName>James N. Ingle, MD</AttrName><Institution>Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution></Header><Header title="Funding Source"><AttrName>GM 61388</AttrName><Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution></Header></Attributions><Funding>U01 GM061388-09</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="1" name="NIGMS" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="WEINSHILBOUM1" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="WEINSHILBOUM1" fname="Richard" mname="M" lname="Weinshilboum" email="weinshilboum.richard@mayo.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>MAYO CLINIC ROCHESTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010070749" aid="1" auth="cit" login="longr" fname="Rochelle" mname="" lname="Long" email="longr@nigms.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011559580" aid="1" auth="cit" login="stefanov" fname="Stefan" mname="Alexandrov" lname="Stefanov" email="stefanov@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010150228" aid="1" auth="cit" login="dkras" fname="Donna" mname="M" lname="Krasnewich-Vostal" email="dkras@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="12 months"><acknowledgement_statement>Samples and associated genotype and phenotype data used in this study were provided by the Mayo Clinic.  Funding support for the Mayo Clinic was provided through a cooperative agreement with the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS), Grant U01 GM61388.  The datasets used for analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number [phs000305.v1.p1].  Dr. James Ingle and his collaborators request that publications resulting from this data cite their original publication.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_old_cert" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution responded that the study is not sensitive without submitting a new Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="316" CGType="cg_class_other" title="For use in the future research to learn about, prevent or treat cancer" name="APTC" dac_uid="58" dac_name="NIGMS" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Mayo Clinic data may be used only for genetic studies to learn about, prevent or treat cancer.  Investigators must state in the DAR their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from their study with the scientific community.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>