<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="6738" whole_study_id="6738" phs="000393" v="1" p="1" createDate="2011-02-14T17:24:31-05:00" modDate="2019-05-22T23:32:03-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-05-22T23:32:03-05:00" handle="DeCODE_NicotineDependence" num_participants="2500"><StudyInfo accession="phs000393.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000393.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA75873" entrez_id="75873" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA75875" entrez_id="75875" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>DeCODE Genetics of Nicotine Dependence</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>analysis</StudyType></StudyTypes><Funding>DA017932</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="17" name="NIDA" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="KARI_STEF" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="KARI_STEF" fname="Kari" lname="Stefansson" email="kari.stefansson@decode.is"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>DECODE GENETICS, EHFDECODE GENETICS, INC.</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010045556" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jpollock" fname="Jonathan" mname="D" lname="Pollock" email="jpollock@ngmsmtp.nida.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010045556" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jpollock" fname="Jonathan" mname="D" lname="Pollock" email="jpollock@ngmsmtp.nida.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>&#8220;The authors acknowledge the contribution of data from Genes Contributing to Nicotine Dependence in Humans supported by R01DA17932 and accessed through dbGAP to the analysis presented in this communication, i.e. publication, presentation, or grant application.&#8221;</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>Three Methods for Accessing deCODE data for Genetics of Nicotine Dependence:
There are three methods for gaining access:
I) Predefined summary data is distributed to dbGAP. These summary data can be subsequently combined with other summary data.   
II) Ad-hoc capability for scientists to define new summary statistics through the deCODE secure remote Disease Miner interface.  These data can be combined with dbGAP primary data by uploading dbGAP data to the deCODE server to generate new summary statistics. 
III) Full access to the project data within the data enclave in Iceland, with the support of deCODE staff.  Under this circumstance project data can be analyzed together with dbGAP data by uploading dbGAP data to the deCODE server.   
Data Access. 

Investigators approved by the dbGAP Joint Addiction, Aging, and Mental Health Data Access committee (JAAMH-DAC) will have immediate access the descriptive and summary data for GWAS results in dbGAP from the previously funded by 1R01DA17932-01A1.  Remote access to individual genotype and phenotype data generated by 1R01DA17932-01A1 through a secure password protected web interface (through a secure VPN connection) through the internet will be made accessible as soon as the site is ready but no later than June 30, 2012.    Researchers approved by the JAAMH-DAC may also gain immediate access to genotype and phenotype data generated by 1R01DA17932-01A1 through the data enclave model, where interested researchers will be able to analyze data on the deCODE site in Reykjavik, Iceland, starting July 1, 2011. 

Process for Data Access

An investigator wishing access to deCODE data shall request access to the deCODE data through NIH dbGAP Joint Addiction, Aging, and Mental Health Data Access committee (JAAMH-DAC).  Once granted access by the JAAMH-DAC, investigators may retrieve the summary data directly from dbGAP, or they could go to a stand-alone firewalled deCODE server and request an analysis of the data to create an unidentifiable summary statistic data set to be downloaded from the deCODE server.  No individual level data from Icelandic research participants shall be deposited outside deCODE as specified by Icelandic law and all handling of personal data and use of samples shall adhere to Iceland laws. Researchers approved by the JAAMH-DAC will have access to data on the data described above through a secure password protected web interface (through a secure VPN connection) through the internet on servers located at deCODE headquarters in Iceland.  The following informatics and statistical algorithms will be made available based on deCODE&#8217;s Disease Miner Professional package without licensing fees.

&#8226; Clinical data &#8211; phenotypes: Import, manage, and query large datasets (including the phenotypeSDL query algorithm for defining phenotype datasets).
&#8226; Family data: Import data, cluster subfamilies and analyse pedigrees for extended families
&#8226; Genetic Analysis: Genome-wide association (Fishers-Exact, TDT, S-TDT, CNV, LD, Clark&#8217;s inference algorithm
&#8226; Genome browser: High speed visualization and browsing with multiple analyses results in one view
&#8226; Marker and gene data base: Database of over 30,000 known genes and 9 million SNPs.


This interface will be flexible and allow inclusion of other algorithms upon request that may implemented by deCODE&#8217;s statistics and informatics departments. The remote Disease Miner web interface does however not provide unrestricted access to primary data during the analysis stage and prevents data inference by applying a dynamic k-anonymization approach.  The main principle is to defer modification of the personal primary data until statistical results are delivered to the end-user. 

The dynamic k-anonymization approach differs from regular k-anonymization approaches that are used to protect privacy, by preventing data inference, typically bin data values into buckets or perturb then in some other way. This is because these approaches work on the entire data set that is to be released at any given time. Under the dynamic k-anonymization approach scientists can define patient sets (or control sets or inputs for QTL analysis) based on all the variables that are captured for each subject in the Disease Miner database.  Behind the scenes (on deCODE&#8216;s servers), these patient sets will be evaluated based on the actual primary data. However, if a scientist wants for instance to see the distribution of BMI in his patient set, the system ensures that no BMI value (range) is returned unless it applies to at least k-individuals. (The size and cardinality of the data set will be taken into consideration when determining the size of k, but it will be no larger than 10,)  Similarly, when the deCODE servers calculate summary statistics such as odds-ratios (per marker or haplotype) or perform regression in QTL, deCODE servers use the actual primary data, while the actual data table for the primary data (or a subset of it) is never returned. The main benefit of this approach is that it applies to any data sets, regardless of their cardinality, while the conventional approaches would limit the number of data attributes one can capture or work with per subject.

Thus, investigators given remote access will not be able to modify the algorithms used to analyze the data.  Nor will  the user be able to see any of the typical primary data tables. The investigator will however have an easy way of exploring the entire data set, e.g. define patient sets and analyze the distribution of one or more variables within these sets. This should provide scientists with an easy way, and full capacity, to define the statistical analysis remotely without any support or intervention from deCODE staff, which results files they will be able to download or view in the deCODE built-in genome browser.

Full access to primary data (with all its flexibility to modify algorithms) is only possible within the data enclave in Iceland.

Researchers approved by the JAAMH-DAC may also access data through the data enclave model, where interested researchers will be able to analyze data on site in Iceland.  This Data Enclave would be a secure database associated with power processors but with no connections to the outside, therefore requiring access locally rather than remotely.  Office space and efficient informatics assistance would be available to researchers visiting Iceland.  Certain types of analysis may not be possible through remote access in a timely fashion, or would in some case require modification of software that need to be approved by the Data Protection Authority and the Scientific Ethics Board of Iceland.  

Research access to the requested deCODE dataset is granted for a period of one (1) year.

An Investigator wishing to combine dbGAP data with summary deCODE data shall request access to the deCODE data through dbGAP.  Once granted access by JAAMH-DAC, investigators may retrieve the summary data from dbGAP directly, or go to the deCODE server directly (see above) and request an analysis of the data to create an unidentifiable summary statistics dataset to be downloaded from the deCODE server to their own servers and combine with dbGAP data and any other data (as is typical of most meta-analyses through large consortia); or 

An investigator wishing to combine primary sequence or genotype data from dbGAP with primary data from deCODE shall apply for access to download dbGAP data.  At the same time, deCODE will apply for access to the same requested datasets as the investigator so that those data sets can be downloaded directly to the deCODE server without going through the 3rd party (investigator).  The analysis will be done on the deCODE server.  The dbGAP data will only temporarily reside on deCODE&#8217;s server, for the limited time to conduct analyses approved by the access committee, and this period will be typically no longer than 3 months unless specifically approved by the access committee.  While on DeCODE&#8217;s data servers, dbGAP data shall be safeguarded to the same extent as the data being shared by deCODE.  Summary data will be returned to the investigator.

An Investigator wishing to work and view directly deCODE primary sequence or genotype data generated with the support of R01DA17932 and combine with dbGAP data shall request access to dbGAP.  In this case the investigator must travel to deCODE.  Once granted access by the JAAMH-DAC, the investigator may travel to deCODE to work inside the deCODE data enclave.  At the same time, deCODE will also need to apply for access to the same requested datasets as the investigator so those data sets can be download directly to the deCODE server without going through the 3rd party (investigator).   The analysis will be done on the deCODE server.  The dbGAP data will only temporarily reside on deCODE servers, for the limited time required to conduct the analyses approved by the access committee, and this period will typically be no longer than 3 months unless specifically approved by the access committee. While on deCODE&#8217;s servers, dbGAP data would be safeguarded to the same extent as the data being shared by deCODE. 
</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="632" CGType="cg_class_other" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="57" dac_name="JAAMH" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>The DeCODE Genetics of Nicotine Dependence study summary data accessed from dbGAP or summary data generated through remote access to the data from  DeCODE Genetics of Nicotine Dependence study on the deCODE server may be used for general research purposes.  The consents do not limit the types of studies that can be performed.  
 
In addition,  Investigators granted on site access to the deCODE enclave in Iceland may also use the data for general research purposes, i.e. the consent do not limit use,  with the following caveats:   No individual level data from Icelandic research participants shall be deposited outside deCODE as specified by Icelandic law AND All handling of personal data and use of personal data shall adhere to Icelandic laws, including but not limited to the The Act on Patients rights No. 74/1997 and Government Regulation No. 286/2008 on Medical  Research, The Data Protection Act No. 77/2000 based on the European Data Protective Directive, and various rules and government regulations promulgated there under the Minister of Justice and the Icelandic Data Protection authority.  These include &#8220;Rules on the Obligation to Notify and Processing which Requires a Permit&#8221; No. 698/2004, and the The Act on biobanks, No. 110/2000 and Government Regulation No. 134/2001.  For English translations contact the NIH dbGAP Joint Addiction, Aging, and Mental Health Data Access committee.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><AdditionalEmails><Email>jpollock@mail.nih.gov</Email></AdditionalEmails></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>