<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="7050" whole_study_id="7050" phs="000459" v="1" p="1" createDate="2011-06-06T16:42:03-05:00" completedByGPADate="2015-05-14T11:37:04-05:00" modDate="2019-09-25T09:01:34-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-09-25T09:01:34-05:00" handle="CIDR_OralCleftSeq" num_participants="115"><StudyInfo accession="phs000459.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000459.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA85093" entrez_id="85093" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA85095" entrez_id="85095" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>Whole Exome Sequencing of Multiplex Cleft Families: CIDR</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/><StudyType22 name="whole_targ_exome"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="germline"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>germline</StudyType><StudyType>whole_exome</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages/><Funding>R01 DE014581-09</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="10" name="NIDCR" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="TBEATY" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="TBEATY" fname="Terri" mname="H" lname="Beaty" email="tbeaty1@jhu.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0012498942" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wanglu" fname="Lu" mname="" lname="Wang" email="wanglu@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Jackie" lname="Bidinger" email="jackie.bidinger@jhu.edu"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011943984" aid="1" auth="cit" login="steink" fname="Kathryn" mname="Kreimborg" lname="Stein" email="steink@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support this study was provided from several previous grants from the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR) to different research groups. Whole exome sequencing was supported by X01-HG-006177, where distant affected relatives were drawn from large multiplex families from several studies were used. Data and samples were drawn from several studies, where funding supported original data collection, previous genotyping and analysis. Funding for individual investigators include: R21-DE-013707 and R01-DE-014581 (Beaty); R37-DE-08559 and P50-DE-016215 (Murray, Marazita); the Iowa Comprehensive Program to Investigate Craniofacial and Dental Anomalies (Murray); R01-DE-09886 (Marazita), R01-DE-012472 (Marazita), R01-DE-014677 (Marazita), R01-DE-016148 (Marazita), R21-DE-016930 (Marazita); R01-DE-013939 (Scott). Parts of this research were supported in part by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (Wilcox, Lie). Additional recruitment was supported by the Smile Train Foundation for recruitment in China (Jabs, Beaty, Shi) and a grant from the Korean government (Jee). Sequencing services were provided by the Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR). CIDR is fully funded through a federal contract from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) to the Johns Hopkins University (contract number HHSN268200782096C). Funds for sequencing were provided by the NIDCR through CIDR&#8217;s NIH contract. We sincerely thank all of the patients and families at each recruitment site for participating in this study, and we gratefully acknowledge the invaluable assistance of clinical, field and laboratory staff who contributed to this effort over the years.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>Please see the data use limitations for each of the five consent groups.</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (GSR are sensitive according to the Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="1232" CGType="" title="Oral Clefts, IRB, COL, GSO, BeatyT" name="OC-IRB-COL-GSO-BEATY" dac_uid="78" dac_name="NIDCR" irb-approval-required="Yes" collaboration-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Oral Clefts.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s).
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.
Data may be used for genetic research on oral clefts, including methodologic research to improve knowledge of how genetic factors play a role in the etiology of oral clefts. Documentation of a collaborative agreement with Dr. Terri Beaty at Johns Hopkins University must be provided; please contact Dr. Beaty by email (tbeaty@jhsph.edu).
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1233" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Craniofacial Disorders, GSO)" name="DS-CFD-GSO" dac_uid="78" dac_name="NIDCR" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Craniofacial Disorders.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

Data may be used for genetic research on cleft lip/palate or craniofacial anomalies, including methodologic research to improve knowledge of how genetic factors play a role in the etiology of craniofacial anomalies.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1234" CGType="" title="Oral Clefts, IRB, COL, GSO, Bailey-WilsonJ" name="OC-IRB-COL-GSO-BAILEYWILSON" dac_uid="78" dac_name="NIDCR" irb-approval-required="Yes" collaboration-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Oral Clefts.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s).
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.
Data may be used for genetic research on oral clefts, including methodologic research to improve knowledge of how genetic factors play a role in the etiology of oral clefts. Documentation of a collaborative agreement with investigators in the Syrian Arab Republic must be provided. Please contact Dr. Joan Bailey-Wilson at NHGRI by e-mail for more information (jebw@mail.nih.gov).
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1235" CGType="" title="Oral Clefts, IRB, COL, GSO, MangoldE-NothenM" name="OC-IRB-COL-GSO-MANGOLD-NOTHEN" dac_uid="78" dac_name="NIDCR" irb-approval-required="Yes" collaboration-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Oral Clefts.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s).
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.
Data may be used for genetic research on oral clefts, including methodologic research to improve knowledge of how genetic factors play a role in the etiology of oral clefts. Documentation of a collaborative agreement with Dr. Elisabeth Mangold or Dr. Markus M. N&#8003;then from the University of Bonn must be provided; please contact Dr. Mangold (e.mangold@uni-bonn.de) or Dr. N&#8003;then (markus.noethen@uni-bonn.de) via e-mail.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1236" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Orofacial Cleft)" name="DS-OFC" dac_uid="78" dac_name="NIDCR" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Orofacial Cleft.

Data may be used for studies investigating oral-facial clefts and related subclinical phenotypes, including methodologic research to improve knowledge of how genetic factors play a role in the etiology of oral clefts.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>