<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="9418" whole_study_id="9418" phs="000618" v="1" p="1" createDate="2013-04-25T14:24:50-05:00" modDate="2022-01-25T16:16:08-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-01-25T16:16:08-05:00" handle="Hypertriglyceridemia_Mexican " num_participants="4350"><StudyInfo accession="phs000618.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000618.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA202274" entrez_id="202274" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA202275" entrez_id="202275" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>Genetics of high serum triglycerides and related metabolic traits in Mexicans</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>analysis</StudyType></StudyTypes><Funding>R01 HL095056</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="12" name="NHLBI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="PAJUKANTA2" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="PAJUKANTA2" fname="Paivi" lname="Pajukanta" email="ppajukanta@mednet.ucla.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA LOS ANGELES</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013043239" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pretels" fname="Renate" mname="S" lname="Pretel" email="pretels@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011552437" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jawang" fname="Zhen" mname="Yuan" lname="Wang" email="zhen.wang@nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001545300" aid="1" auth="cit" login="lic17" fname="Chengyuan" mname="" lname="Press" email="chanel.press@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>The suggested Acknowledgement Statement to accompany the dataset is:
This Mexican hypertriglyceridemia GWAS study sponsored as an RO1 project by NHLBI aimed to identify genetic variants contributing to serum lipid levels in Mexicans. The study was conducted by the Study Investigators at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) (Paivi Pajukanta, Daphna Weissglas-Volkov, Rita Cantor, and Janet Sinsheimer) and Instituto Nacional de Ciencias M&#233;dicas y Nutrici&#243;n (INCMN) (Teresa Tusie-Luna, Carlos Aguilar-Salinas, and Laura Riba). In addition to de-identified genome wide genotypic data, a selected list of de-identified phenotypic data related to hypertriglyceridemia and related metabolic traits are also available in dbGaP. A summary of this GWAS can be found in Weissglas-Volkov et al. 2013 Journal of Medical Genetics.

The Approved Users agree to acknowledge the contribution of NHLBI and the Investigators (Paivi Pajukanta, Daphna Weissglas-Volkov, Rita Cantor, Janet Sinsheimer, Teresa Tusie-Luna, Carlos Aguilar-Salinas, Laura Riba) of this Mexican Hypertriglyceridemia GWAS Study entitled &#8220;Genetics of high serum triglycerides and related metabolic traits in Mexicans&#8221; (described in detail in Weissglass-Volkov et al. 2013 Journal of Medical Genetics) in any and all oral and written presentations, disclosures, and publications resulting from any and all analyses of such genetic analysis data.

If the Research Project involves collaboration with the Study Investigators, then the Approved Users will acknowledge the Mexican Hypertriglyceridemia GWAS Study Investigators as co-authors, as appropriate, on any publication.

If the Research Project does not involved collaboration with the Study Investigators, then the manuscript shall include the acknowledgement below.
&#8220;The Mexican Hypertriglyceridemia GWAS Study entitled &#8220;Genetics of high serum triglycerides and related metabolic traits in Mexicans&#8221; (described in detail in Weissglass-Volkov et al. 2013 Journal of Medical Genetics) was conducted by the Study Investigators at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) (Paivi Pajukanta, Daphna Weissglas-Volkov, Rita Cantor, and Janet Sinsheimer) and the Instituto Nacional de Ciencias M&#233;dicas y Nutrici&#243;n (INCMN) (Teresa Tusie-Luna, Carlos Aguilar-Salinas, and Laura Riba) and supported by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI). This manuscript was not prepared in collaboration with investigators of the Mexican Hypertriglyceridemia GWAS study and does not necessarily reflect the opinions or views of the Mexican GWAS study Investigators, UCLA, INCMN and the NHLBI.
</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>Use of the dataset is limited to hypertriglyceridemia and related metabolic disorders research purposes. Based on the informed consent, these coded data may be used by other investigators for the study of hypertriglyceridemia and related metabolic disorders. In addition to hypertriglyceridemia, appropriate uses of the submitted data regarding related metabolic disorders include obesity and dyslipidemias influencing HDL-cholesterol levels. Additional data use limitations were not stated in the informed consent.</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access_timeout_extend" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (institution requested additional time)"/><ConsentGroup uid="989" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Hypertriglyceridemia, MDS, RD)" name="DS-HTG-MDS-RD" dac_uid="56" dac_name="NHLBI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Hypertriglyceridemia and related disorders.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

Use of the dataset is limited to hypertriglyceridemia and related metabolic disorders research purposes. Based on the informed consent, these coded data may be used by other investigators for the study of hypertriglyceridemia and related metabolic disorders. In addition to hypertriglyceridemia, appropriate uses of the submitted data regarding related metabolic disorders include obesity and dyslipidemias influencing HDL-cholesterol levels. Additional data use limitations were not stated in the informed consent.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>