<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="11979" whole_study_id="11979" phs="000812" v="1" p="1" createDate="2014-08-04T17:20:07-05:00" completedByGPADate="2014-08-12T17:26:00-05:00" modDate="2019-05-07T16:40:17-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-05-07T16:40:17-05:00" handle="BreastProstateCancer" num_participants="5000"><StudyInfo accession="phs000812.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs000812.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA263216" entrez_id="263216" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA263217" entrez_id="263217" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>Characterizing Genetic Susceptibility to Breast and Prostate Cancer - BPC3</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="germline"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>germline</StudyType><StudyType>analysis</StudyType></StudyTypes></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="PKRAFT1" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="PKRAFT1" fname="PETER" mname="" lname="KRAFT" email="pkraft@hsph.harvard.edu"><Role>PI</Role><Organization>HARVARD SCHOOL OF PUBLIC HEALTH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010119676" aid="1" auth="cit" login="lgilland" fname="Elizabeth" mname="Mary" lname="Gillanders" email="lgilland@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Constance" lname="Chen" email="cjchen@hsph.harvard.edu"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011552437" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jawang" fname="Zhen" mname="Yuan" lname="Wang" email="zhen.wang@nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001203526" aid="1" auth="cit" login="cagaananef" fname="Emilie" mname="Charlisse F" lname="Caga-Anan" email="charlisse.caga-anan@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>The Breast and Prostate Cancer Cohort Consortium (BPC3) genome-wide association studies of advanced prostate cancer and estrogen-receptor negative breast cancer was supported by the National Cancer Institute under cooperative agreements U01-CA98233, U01-CA98710, U01-CA98216, and U01-CA98758 and the Intramural Research Program of  the National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics. The BPC3 investigators request that publications resulting from the use of these data cite their original publications, as relevant:

Schumacher FR, Berndt SI, Siddiq A, Jacobs KB, Wang Z, Lindstrom S, Stevens VL, Chen C, Mondul AM, Travis RC, Stram DO, Eeles RA, Easton DF, Giles G, Hopper JL, Neal DE, Hamdy FC, Donovan JL, Muir K, Al Olama AA, Kote-Jarai Z, Guy M, Severi G, Gr&#246;nberg H, Isaacs WB, Karlsson R, Wiklund F, Xu J, Allen NE, Andriole GL, Barricarte A, Boeing H, Bueno-de-Mesquita HB, Crawford ED, Diver WR, Gonzalez CA, Gaziano JM, Giovannucci EL, Johansson M, Le Marchand L, Ma J, Sieri S, Stattin P, Stampfer MJ, Tjonneland A, Vineis P, Virtamo J, Vogel U, Weinstein SJ, Yeager M, Thun MJ, Kolonel LN, Henderson BE, Albanes D, Hayes RB, Feigelson HS, Riboli E, Hunter DJ, Chanock SJ, Haiman CA, Kraft P. Genome-wide association study identifies new prostate cancer susceptibility loci. Hum Mol Genet. 2011 Oct 1;20(19):3867-75.

Siddiq A, Couch FJ, Chen GK, Lindstr&#246;m S, Eccles D, Millikan RC, Michailidou K, Stram DO, Beckmann L, Rhie SK, Ambrosone CB, Aittom&#228;ki K, Amiano P, Apicella C; Australian Breast Cancer Tissue Bank Investigators, Baglietto L, Bandera EV, Beckmann MW, Berg CD, Bernstein L, Blomqvist C, Brauch H, Brinton L, Bui QM, Buring JE, Buys SS, Campa D, Carpenter JE, Chasman DI, Chang-Claude J, Chen C, Clavel-Chapelon F, Cox A, Cross SS, Czene K, Deming SL, Diasio RB, Diver WR, Dunning AM, Durcan L, Ekici AB, Fasching PA; Familial Breast Cancer Study, Feigelson HS, Fejerman L, Figueroa JD, Fletcher O, Flesch-Janys D, Gaudet MM; GENICA Consortium, Gerty SM, Rodriguez-Gil JL, Giles GG, van Gils CH, Godwin AK, Graham N, Greco D, Hall P, Hankinson SE, Hartmann A, Hein R, Heinz J, Hoover RN, Hopper JL, Hu JJ, Huntsman S, Ingles SA, Irwanto A, Isaacs C, Jacobs KB, John EM, Justenhoven C, Kaaks R, Kolonel LN, Coetzee GA, Lathrop M, Le Marchand L, Lee AM, Lee IM, Lesnick T, Lichtner P, Liu J, Lund E, Makalic E, Martin NG, McLean CA, Meijers-Heijboer H, Meindl A, Miron P, Monroe KR, Montgomery GW, M&#252;ller-Myhsok B, Nickels S, Nyante SJ, Olswold C, Overvad K, Palli D, Park DJ, Palmer JR, Pathak H, Peto J, Pharoah P, Rahman N, Rivadeneira F, Schmidt DF, Schmutzler RK, Slager S, Southey MC, Stevens KN, Sinn HP, Press MF, Ross E, Riboli E, Ridker PM, Schumacher FR, Severi G, Dos Santos Silva I, Stone J, Sund M, Tapper WJ, Thun MJ, Travis RC, Turnbull C, Uitterlinden AG, Waisfisz Q, Wang X, Wang Z, Weaver J, Schulz-Wendtland R, Wilkens LR, Van Den Berg D, Zheng W, Ziegler RG, Ziv E, Nevanlinna H, Easton DF, Hunter DJ, Henderson BE, Chanock SJ, Garcia-Closas M, Kraft P, Haiman CA, Vachon CM. A meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies of breast cancer identifies two novel susceptibility loci at 6q14 and 20q11. Hum Mol Genet. 2012 Dec 15;21(24):5373-84.
</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="1319" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (MDS)" name="GRU-MDS" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1320" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (PUB, MDS)" name="HMB-PUB-MDS" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1322" CGType="" title="Cancer in all age groups, other disease in adults only and methods " name="CADM" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>The informed consent document signed by the study participants allows use of these data by investigators for discovery and hypothesis generation in the investigation of the genetic contributions to cancer in all age groups and other diseases in adults only, as well as development of novel analytical approaches for GWAS.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1325" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Breast, Ovarian, or Endometrial Disease, MDS)" name="DS-BOED-MDS" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Breast, Ovarian, or Endometrial Disease.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="1348" CGType="" title="Exchange Area" name="EA" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Pre-release exchange area for use by study investigators only.
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>