<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="22088" whole_study_id="22088" phs="001315" v="1" p="1" createDate="2016-11-09T12:20:22-05:00" completedByGPADate="2016-11-15T17:52:16-05:00" modDate="2019-05-06T11:04:21-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2019-05-06T11:04:21-05:00" handle="CIDR_ColorectalCancerGxEinteractions" num_participants="9000"><StudyInfo accession="phs001315.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs001315.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA377381" entrez_id="377381" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA377382" entrez_id="377382" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>CIDR: Detecting Common and Rare Genetic Loci and GxE Interactions in Colorectal Cancer</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="germline"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>germline</StudyType></StudyTypes><Funding>X01 HG007585</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="UPETERS" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="UPETERS" fname="ULRIKE" mname="" lname="PETERS" email="upeters@fredhutch.org"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>FRED HUTCHINSON CANCER RESEARCH CENTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011073207" aid="1" auth="cit" login="mechanil" fname="Leah" mname="E" lname="Mechanic" email="mechanil@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="JHUYGHE" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="JHUYGHE" fname="Jeroen" mname="" lname="Huyghe" email="jhuyghe@fredhutch.org"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGANFRED HUTCHINSON CANCER RESEARCH CENTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010579723" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wewu" fname="Wenyu" mname="" lname="Wu" email="wwu@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014190168" aid="1" auth="cit" login="sharopon" fname="Nataliya" mname="Rashidovna" lname="Sharopova" email="sharopon@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001203526" aid="1" auth="cit" login="cagaananef" fname="Emilie" mname="Charlisse F" lname="Caga-Anan" email="charlisse.caga-anan@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for Genetics &amp; Epidemiology of Colorectal Cancer Consortium (GECCO) was provided by the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (X01 HG007585-01; U01 CA164930). Funding support for studies participating in the Genetics &amp; Epidemiology of Colorectal Cancer Consortium and included in the Common Variant GWAS are as follows:

COLON: The COLON study is sponsored by Wereld Kanker Onderzoek Fonds, including funds from grant 2014/1179 as part of the World Cancer Research Fund International Regular Grant Programme, by Alpe d&#8217;Huzes and the Dutch Cancer Society (UM 2012&#8211;5653, UW 2013-5927, UW2015-7946), and by TRANSCAN (JTC2012-MetaboCCC, JTC2013-FOCUS). 

DACHS: German Research Council (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, BR 1704/6-1, BR 1704/6-3, BR 1704/6-4 and CH 117/1-1), and the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (01KH0404 and 01ER0814).

EPIC: The coordination of EPIC is financially supported by the European Commission (DG-SANCO) and the International Agency for Research on Cancer. The national cohorts are supported by Danish Cancer Society (Denmark); Ligue Contre le Cancer, Institut Gustave Roussy, Mutuelle G&#233;n&#233;rale de l&#8217;Education Nationale, Institut National de la Sant&#233; et de la Recherche M&#233;dicale (INSERM) (France); German Cancer Aid, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF), Deutsche Krebshilfe, Deutsches Krebsforschungszentrum and Federal Ministry of Education and Research (Germany); the Hellenic Health Foundation (Greece); Associazione Italiana per la Ricerca sul Cancro-AIRC-Italy and National Research Council (Italy); Dutch Ministry of Public Health, Welfare and Sports (VWS), Netherlands Cancer Registry (NKR), LK Research Funds, Dutch Prevention Funds, Dutch ZON (Zorg Onderzoek Nederland), World Cancer Research Fund (WCRF), Statistics Netherlands (The Netherlands); ERC-2009-AdG 232997 and Nordforsk, Nordic Centre of Excellence programme on Food, Nutrition and Health (Norway); Health Research Fund (FIS), PI13/00061 to Granada, PI13/01162 to EPIC-Murcia, Regional Governments of Andaluc&#237;a, Asturias, Basque Country, Murcia and Navarra, ISCIII RETIC (RD06/0020) (Spain); Swedish Cancer Society, Swedish Research Council and County Councils of Sk&#229;ne and V&#228;sterbotten (Sweden); Cancer Research UK (14136 to EPIC-Norfolk; C570/A16491 and C8221/A19170 to EPIC-Oxford), Medical Research Council (1000143 to EPIC-Norfolk, MR/M012190/1 to EPIC-Oxford) (United Kingdom).

HPFS: National Institutes of Health (P01 CA055075, UM1 CA167552, R01 CA137178, R01 CA151993, R35 CA197735, K07 CA190673, and P50 CA127003).

NHS: National Institutes of Health (R01 CA137178, P01 CA087969, UM1 CA186107, R01 CA151993, R35 CA197735, K07 CA190673, and P50 CA127003).

NQplus: The NQplus study is sponsored by a ZonMW investment grant (98-10030); by PREVIEW, the project PREVention of diabetes through lifestyle intervention and population studies in Europe and around the World (PREVIEW) project which received funding from the European Union Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007&#8211;2013) under grant no. 312057; by funds from TI Food and Nutrition (cardiovascular health theme), a public&#8211;private partnership on pre-competitive research in food and nutrition; and by FOODBALL, the Food Biomarker Alliance, a project from JPI Healthy Diet for a Healthy Life.

We request that publications resulting from these data cite the following:

Peters U, Jiao S, Schumacher FR, Hutter CM, Aragaki AK, Baron JA, Berndt SI, B&#233;zieau S, Brenner H, Butterbach K, Caan BJ, Campbell PT, Carlson CS, Casey G, Chan AT, Chang-Claude J, Chanock SJ, Chen LS, Coetzee GA, Coetzee SG, Conti DV, Curtis KR, Duggan D, Edwards T, Fuchs CS, Gallinger S, Giovannucci EL, Gogarten SM, Gruber SB, Haile RW, Harrison TA, Hayes RB, Henderson BE, Hoffmeister M, Hopper JL, Hudson TJ, Hunter DJ, Jackson RD, Jee SH, Jenkins MA, Jia WH, Kolonel LN, Kooperberg C, K&#252;ry S, Lacroix AZ, Laurie CC, Laurie CA, Le Marchand L, Lemire M, Levine D, Lindor NM, Liu Y, Ma J, Makar KW, Matsuo K, Newcomb PA, Potter JD, Prentice RL, Qu C, Rohan T, Rosse SA, Schoen RE, Seminara D, Shrubsole M, Shu XO, Slattery ML, Taverna D, Thibodeau SN, Ulrich CM, White E, Xiang Y, Zanke BW, Zeng YX, Zhang B, Zheng W, Hsu L; Colon Cancer Family Registry and the Genetics and Epidemiology of Colorectal Cancer Consortium (2013) Identification of Genetic Susceptibility Loci for Colorectal Tumors in a Genome-Wide Meta-analysis. Gastroenterology  144:799-807. PMID: 23266556
</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_old_cert" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution responded that the study is not sensitive without submitting a new Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="2294" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="2295" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Colorectal Cancer, NPU, GSO)" name="DS-CC-NPU-GSO" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Colorectal Cancer.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

General methods development research is NOT permitted.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="2296" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Colorectal Cancer, PUB, NPU)" name="DS-CC-PUB-NPU" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Colorectal Cancer.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.

General methods development research is NOT permitted.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="2297" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (PUB)" name="HMB-PUB" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>