<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="36162" whole_study_id="28967" phs="001584" v="2" p="2" createDate="2019-09-11T17:08:35-05:00" completedByGPADate="2019-09-12T09:25:49-05:00" modDate="2021-03-05T11:58:41-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2021-03-05T11:58:41-05:00" handle="eMERGE_III_HRC" num_participants="83717"><StudyInfo accession="phs001584.v2.p2" parentAccession="phs001584.v2.p2"><BioProject id="PRJNA453657" entrez_id="453657" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA453658" entrez_id="453658" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>eMERGE Network Phase III: HRC Imputed Array Data of 85,000+ Participants</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="array_multi_sample_gen"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="dna"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>dna</StudyType><StudyType>snp_array</StudyType></StudyTypes></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="false" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="RCHISHOLM" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="RCHISHOLM" fname="Rex" mname="L" lname="Chisholm" email="r-chisholm@northwestern.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY AT CHICAGO</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2002367725" aid="1" auth="cit" login="rowleyrk" fname="Robb" mname="Kenneth" lname="Rowley" email="robb.rowley@nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Kayla" lname="Howell" email="kayla.m.howell@vumc.org"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="GORDONWADE" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GORDONWADE" fname="Gordon" mname="" lname="Wade" email="gwade@broadinstitute.org"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>BROAD INSTITUTE, INC.</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014190168" aid="1" auth="cit" login="sharopon" fname="Nataliya" mname="Rashidovna" lname="Sharopova" email="sharopon@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Cincinnati Children&#8217;s Hospital Medical Center (CCHMC) &#8211; Acknowledgement Text: CCHMC is a participating pediatric institution for Phase III of the eMERGE network, a national consortium selected to expand best practices and knowledge in effective implementation of genomic medicine to pursue a broad-based program sufficiently large to define health outcomes associated with rare variants in ~100 clinically relevant genes. CCHMC Principal Investigators (PIs) have contributed sequencing data generated from the following cohorts: (1) Better Outcomes for Children (BOfC). Since January, 2011, the Cincinnati Biobank has managed the sample repository developed through the BOfC protocol (PI: John Harley), an institution-wide broad based consent project to utilize remnant clinical samples for biomedical research from participants consented at registration. This project is made possible by institutional resources. To date, over 261,000 participants have consented to BOfC and DNA samples are stored from more than 84,000 unique patients. Through an IRB approved protocol led by Dr. Bahram Namjou (2015-7778), 2,800 samples were selected for sequencing on the eMERGE sequencing panel representing &gt;15 primary phenotypes including Arrhythmia, Asthma, Cardiomyopathy, Chronic kidney disease, Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome, Hyperlipidemia, Autistic behavior, and Tuberous Sclerosis 1. This project is made possible by the support of U01HG008666 (PI: John Harley). (2) Return of eMERGE III Genomic Results. Through an IRB approved protocol led by Dr. Melanie Myers (2016-3361), 200 adolescent patients and their parents were consented to examine (1) their choices about results to be returned on the eMERGE sequencing panel, (2) their responses to learning negative genetic test results, and (3) the parents&#8217; responses after learning their children&#8217;s positive results. All 200 participants provided blood samples. Extracted DNA samples were sequenced on the eMERGE sequencing panel. Results are to be returned to participants. This project is made possible by the support of U01HG008666 (PI: John Harley). Patients of interest were identified using anthropometric measurements, clinical data and ICD codes extracted from the EPIC electronic medical record (EMR). The extraction of data from the EMR into the de-identified data warehouse, i2b2, was made possible by institutional resources and UL1RR026314/UL1TR001425, the Cincinnati Center for Clinical and Translational Sciences and Training Grant (PI: James Heubi). Children&#8217;s Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP) Center for Applied Genomics, The Children&#8217;s Hospital of Philadelphia Samples and associated genomic and phenotype data used in this study were provided by the Center for Applied Genomics at the Children&#8217;s Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP). Support for genotyping was provided by an Institutional Development Award from CHOP. Support for sequencing was provided by the National Institutes of Health through an award from the National Human Genome Research Institute&#8217;s Electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE) program (U01HG008684). Columbia University Samples and data used in this study were provided by the Center for Glomerular Diseases at Columbia University, the Columbia Transplant Programs, the DataBase Shared Resource at the Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, and the Institute for Genomic Medicine at Columbia University. Funding support for the Columbia eMERGE III research study was provided by a U01 grant from the National Human Genome Research Institute (U01HG008680; PIs &#8211; Chunhua Weng, PhD; George Hripcsak, MD; Ali Gharavi, MD). Geisinger Funding for the MyCode&#174; sample and data collection was provided by grants from Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, the Clinic Research Fund of Geisinger Clinic, and the Regeneron Genetics Center. Partners Health Care (Harvard University) Samples and data used in this study were provided by the Partners Health Care Biobank (https://biobank.partners.org/). Funding support for the Partners Biobank was provided by Partners Health Care and Partners Personalized Medicine. Assistance with phenotype harmonization was provided by the eMERGE Coordinating Center (Grant number U01HG04603). Additional support was provided by the NIH, NHGRI eMERGE Network (U01HG 5U01HG008685-03). Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at the Translational Genomics Core, Partners Personalized Medicine and funded by Partners Personalized Medicine. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center (U01HG004603) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number; phs000944.v1.p1. Kaiser Washington/University of Washington Funding support for Alzheimer's Disease Patient Registry (ADPR) and Adult Changes in Thought (ACT) study was provided by a U01 from the National Institute on Aging (Eric B. Larson, PI, U01AG006781). A gift from the 3M Corporation was used to expand the ACT cohort. DNA aliquots sufficient for GWAS from ADPR Probable AD cases, who had been enrolled in Genetic Differences in Alzheimer's Cases and Controls (Walter Kukull, PI, R01 AG007584) and obtained under that grant, were made available to eMERGE without charge. Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at Johns Hopkins University, was provided by the NIH (U01HG004438). Genome-wide association analyses were supported through a Cooperative Agreement from the National Human Genome Research Institute, U01HG004610 (Eric B. Larson, PI). Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center (U01HG004603) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number phs000234.v1.p1. Mayo Clinic Samples and associated genotype and phenotype data used in this study were provided by the Mayo Clinic. Funding support for the Mayo Clinic was provided through a cooperative agreement with the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI), Grant #: UOIHG004599, UOIHG006379; and the Mayo Center for Individualized Medicine. Funding support for sequencing, which was performed at The Baylor Human Genomics Sequencing Center, was provided by the NIH. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). Northwestern University Samples and data used in this study were obtained from patients of Northwestern Medicine, Chicago, IL, who were recruited for the eMERGE II Pharmacogenomics Study and the eMERGE III Your Genes and Your Health Study. The Pharmacogenomics Study, a supplement to the Northwestern eMERGE II Project (U01HG006388) and the Your Genes and Your Health Study (U01HG008673) were funded through the NIH, NHGRI eMERGE Network. Vanderbilt University Funding support for the Vanderbilt Genome-Electronic Records (VGER) project was provided through a cooperative agreement (U01HG008672) with the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI) with additional funding from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS). The dataset(s) used for the analyses described were obtained from Vanderbilt University Medical Center. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center (U01HG004603) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number phs000188.v1.p1.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>None.</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="3365" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3366" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (IRB, PUB, GSO)" name="GRU-IRB-PUB-GSO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3367" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (IRB, NPU)" name="GRU-IRB-NPU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3368" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical" name="HMB" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3369" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (MDS)" name="HMB-MDS" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3370" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Childhood Diseases)" name="DS-CHILDD" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Childhood Diseases.

Approved use for studies of the genetic and environmental factors that contribute to childhood health, development and disease.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3371" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Dementia)" name="DS-DEM" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Dementia.

Use of the data must be related to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. For example, studies of conditions like cataract, diabetes, and psoriasis might be appropriate, while conditions like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and neuroblastoma might not be appropriate. Studies of conditions that are common in both children and the elderly, such as schizophrenia or depression, would not be appropriate if they focused on children and young adults. Studies focused primarily on pediatric populations are not permitted.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3372" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (PUB, GSO)" name="HMB-PUB-GSO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3373" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (IRB, PUB)" name="GRU-IRB-PUB" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3427" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (GSO)" name="HMB-GSO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

No permitted use: Insurance companies.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study><Study uid="28967" whole_study_id="28967" phs="001584" v="1" p="1" createDate="2018-04-11T21:45:03-05:00" completedByGPADate="2018-04-11T23:21:45-05:00" modDate="2020-09-01T11:27:02-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-09-01T11:27:02-05:00" handle="eMERGE_III_HRC" num_participants="83717"><StudyInfo accession="phs001584.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs001584.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA453657" entrez_id="453657" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA453658" entrez_id="453658" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>eMERGE Network Phase III: HRC Imputed Array Data of 85,000+ Participants</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="array_multi_sample_gen"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="dna"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>dna</StudyType><StudyType>snp_array</StudyType></StudyTypes></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="RCHISHOLM" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="RCHISHOLM" fname="Rex" mname="L" lname="Chisholm" email="r-chisholm@northwestern.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY AT CHICAGO</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010046557" aid="1" auth="cit" login="jyotig" fname="Jyoti" mname="Gupta" lname="Dayal" email="jyotig@nhgri.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Kayla" lname="Howell" email="kayla.m.howell@vumc.org"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="0013269007" aid="1" auth="cit" login="kianga" fname="Anne" mname="" lname="Sturcke" email="kianga@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014190168" aid="1" auth="cit" login="sharopon" fname="Nataliya" mname="Rashidovna" lname="Sharopova" email="sharopon@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010170421" aid="1" auth="cit" login="strasbuj" fname="Jennifer" mname="A" lname="Strasburger" email="strasbuj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Cincinnati Children&#8217;s Hospital Medical Center (CCHMC) &#8211; Acknowledgement Text: 
CCHMC is a participating pediatric institution for Phase III of the eMERGE network, a national consortium selected to expand best practices and knowledge in effective implementation of genomic medicine to pursue a broad-based program sufficiently large to define health outcomes associated with rare variants in ~100 clinically relevant genes.  CCHMC Principal Investigators (PIs) have contributed sequencing data generated from the following cohorts: 
 
(1) Better Outcomes for Children (BOfC).  Since January, 2011, the Cincinnati Biobank has managed the sample repository developed through the BOfC protocol (PI: John Harley), an institution-wide broad based consent project to utilize remnant clinical samples for biomedical research from participants consented at registration.  This project is made possible by institutional resources.  To date, over 261,000 participants have consented to BOfC and DNA samples are stored from more than 84,000 unique patients.  Through an IRB approved protocol led by Dr. Bahram Namjou (2015-7778), 2,800 samples were selected for sequencing on the eMERGE sequencing panel representing &gt;15 primary phenotypes including Arrhythmia, Asthma, Cardiomyopathy, Chronic kidney disease, Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome, Hyperlipidemia, Autistic behavior, and Tuberous Sclerosis 1.  This project is made possible by the support of U01HG008666 (PI: John Harley).

(2) Return of eMERGE III Genomic Results.  Through an IRB approved protocol led by Dr. Melanie Myers (2016-3361), 200 adolescent patients and their parents were consented to examine (1) their choices about results to be returned on the eMERGE sequencing panel, (2) their responses to learning negative genetic test results, and (3) the parents&#8217; responses after learning their children&#8217;s positive results.  All 200 participants provided blood samples.  Extracted DNA samples were sequenced on the eMERGE sequencing panel.  Results are to be returned to participants.  This project is made possible by the support of U01HG008666 (PI: John Harley). 
Patients of interest were identified using anthropometric measurements, clinical data and ICD codes extracted from the EPIC electronic medical record (EMR). The extraction of data from the EMR into the de-identified data warehouse, i2b2, was made possible by institutional resources and UL1RR026314/UL1TR001425, the Cincinnati Center for Clinical and Translational Sciences and Training Grant (PI: James Heubi). 

Children&#8217;s Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP) 
Center for Applied Genomics, The Children&#8217;s Hospital of Philadelphia 
Samples and associated genomic and phenotype data used in this study were provided by the Center for Applied Genomics at the Children&#8217;s Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP). Support for genotyping was provided by an Institutional Development Award from CHOP. Support for sequencing was provided by the National Institutes of Health through an award from the National Human Genome Research Institute&#8217;s Electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE) program (U01HG008684). 

Columbia University
Samples and data used in this study were provided by the Center for Glomerular Diseases at Columbia University, the Columbia Transplant Programs, the DataBase Shared Resource at the Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, and the Institute for Genomic Medicine at Columbia University. Funding support for the Columbia eMERGE III research study was provided by a U01 grant from the National Human Genome Research Institute (U01HG008680; PIs &#8211; Chunhua Weng, PhD; George Hripcsak, MD; Ali Gharavi, MD). 

Geisinger
Funding for the MyCode&#174; sample and data collection was provided by grants from Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, the Clinic Research Fund of Geisinger Clinic, and the Regeneron Genetics Center.

Partners Health Care (Harvard University)
Samples and data used in this study were provided by the Partners Health Care Biobank (https://biobank.partners.org/). Funding support for the Partners Biobank was provided by Partners Health Care and Partners Personalized Medicine. Assistance with phenotype harmonization was provided by the eMERGE Coordinating Center (Grant number U01HG04603). Additional support was provided by the NIH, NHGRI eMERGE Network (U01HG 5U01HG008685-03). Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at the Translational Genomics Core, Partners Personalized Medicine and funded by Partners Personalized Medicine. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center (U01HG004603) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number; phs000944.v1.p1.

Kaiser Washington/University of Washington 
Funding support for Alzheimer's Disease Patient Registry (ADPR) and Adult Changes in Thought (ACT) study was provided by a U01 from the National Institute on Aging (Eric B. Larson, PI, U01AG006781).  A gift from the 3M Corporation was used to expand the ACT cohort.  DNA aliquots sufficient for GWAS from ADPR Probable AD cases, who had been enrolled in Genetic Differences in Alzheimer's Cases and Controls (Walter Kukull, PI, R01 AG007584) and obtained under that grant, were made available to eMERGE without charge. Funding support for genotyping, which was performed at Johns Hopkins University, was provided by the NIH (U01HG004438). Genome-wide association analyses were supported through a Cooperative Agreement from the National Human Genome Research Institute, U01HG004610 (Eric B. Larson, PI). Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center (U01HG004603) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number phs000234.v1.p1.
Mayo Clinic
Samples and associated genotype and phenotype data used in this study were provided by the Mayo Clinic. Funding support for the Mayo Clinic was provided through a cooperative agreement with the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI), Grant #: UOIHG004599, UOIHG006379; and the Mayo Center for Individualized Medicine. Funding support for sequencing, which was performed at The Baylor Human Genomics Sequencing Center, was provided by the NIH. Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI).

Meharry Medical College
Funding support to Meharry Medical College for samples and data was provided by the National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD) grant MD007593 to the Meharry Translational Research Center (MeTRC). Funding for sequencing, which was performed at the Baylor College of Medicine, was provided by the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI) grant U01HG008664.

Northwestern University
Samples and data used in this study were obtained from patients of Northwestern Medicine, Chicago, IL, who were recruited for the eMERGE II Pharmacogenomics Study and the eMERGE III Your Genes and Your Health Study. The Pharmacogenomics Study, a supplement to the Northwestern eMERGE II Project (U01HG006388) and the Your Genes and Your Health Study (U01HG008673) were funded through the NIH, NHGRI eMERGE Network.  

Vanderbilt University
Funding support for the Vanderbilt Genome-Electronic Records (VGER) project was provided through a cooperative agreement (U01HG008672) with the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI) with additional funding from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS). The dataset(s) used for the analyses described were obtained from Vanderbilt University Medical Center.  Assistance with phenotype harmonization and genotype data cleaning was provided by the eMERGE Administrative Coordinating Center (U01HG004603) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The datasets used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained from dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gap through dbGaP accession number phs000188.v1.p1.</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>None.</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access_by_timeout" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access (institution did not respond within six months)"/><ConsentGroup uid="3365" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3366" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (IRB, PUB, GSO)" name="GRU-IRB-PUB-GSO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3367" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (IRB, COL, NPU)" name="GRU-IRB-COL-NPU" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="Yes" collaboration-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s).
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3368" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical" name="HMB" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3369" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (MDS)" name="HMB-MDS" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3370" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Childhood Diseases)" name="DS-CHILDD" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Childhood Diseases.

Approved use for studies of the genetic and environmental factors that contribute to childhood health, development and disease.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3371" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Dementia)" name="DS-DEM" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Dementia.

Use of the data must be related to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. For example, studies of conditions like cataract, diabetes, and psoriasis might be appropriate, while conditions like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and neuroblastoma might not be appropriate. Studies of conditions that are common in both children and the elderly, such as schizophrenia or depression, would not be appropriate if they focused on children and young adults. Studies focused primarily on pediatric populations are not permitted.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3372" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (PUB, GSO)" name="HMB-PUB-GSO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3373" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (IRB, PUB)" name="GRU-IRB-PUB" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3427" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (GSO)" name="HMB-GSO" dac_uid="54" dac_name="NHGRI" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

No permitted use: Insurance companies.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>