<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="31134" whole_study_id="31134" phs="001905" v="1" p="1" createDate="2018-09-05T11:56:07-05:00" completedByGPADate="2018-09-06T15:14:59-05:00" modDate="2022-04-14T22:04:38-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-04-14T22:04:38-05:00" handle="CIDR_CRC" num_participants="4518"><StudyInfo accession="phs001905.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs001905.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA574684" entrez_id="574684" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA574685" entrez_id="574685" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>CIDR: Molecular Pathological Epidemiology of Colorectal Cancer</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="ncbi_for_sequence"/><StudyType22 name="whole_targ_exome"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="somatic_snv"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="tumor_normal"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>individual_sequencing</StudyType><StudyType>supporting_documents</StudyType><StudyType>tumor_normal</StudyType><StudyType>somatic_snv</StudyType><StudyType>targeted_exome</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages><SraStorage location="NCBI"/></SraStorages><Funding>U01CA137088</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="15" name="NHGRI" is_funding_ic="false" is_admin_ic="true"/><IC id="4" name="NCI" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="UPETERS" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="UPETERS" fname="ULRIKE" mname="" lname="PETERS" email="upeters@fredhutch.org"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>FRED HUTCHINSON CANCER RESEARCH CENTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011073207" aid="1" auth="cit" login="mechanil" fname="Leah" mname="E" lname="Mechanic" email="mechanil@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Tabitha" lname="Harrison" email="tharriso@fhcrc.org"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="0012988688" aid="1" auth="cit" login="popovan" fname="Natalia" mname="V" lname="Popova" email="popovan@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014190168" aid="1" auth="cit" login="sharopon" fname="Nataliya" mname="Rashidovna" lname="Sharopova" email="sharopon@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001203526" aid="1" auth="cit" login="cagaananef" fname="Emilie" mname="Charlisse F" lname="Caga-Anan" email="charlisse.caga-anan@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>Funding support for Genetics &amp; Epidemiology of Colorectal Cancer Consortium (GECCO) was provided by the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (U01 CA137088). Funding support for studies participating in the Genetics &amp; Epidemiology of Colorectal Cancer Consortium and included in this study are as follows:
&#8226; ACCFR: Australasian Colorectal Cancer Family Registry (NCI/NIH grant numbers U01 CA167551, U01 CA074778 and U01/U24 CA097735)
&#8226; CRA: This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grant R01 CA68535.
&#8226; Colonomics: This study was supported by the Instituto de Salud Carlos III grants (FIS PI09-01037, PI11-01439, and PIE13-00022), CIBERESP CB07/02/2005, Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness (SAF2012-38885), the Spanish Association Against Cancer (AECC) Scientific Foundation, the Catalan Government DURSI grant 2014SGR647, and NIH grant U19CA148107 (CORECT). Sample collection was supported by the Xarxa de Bancs de Tumors de Catalunya sponsored by Pla Director d'Oncolog&#237;a de Catalunya (XBTC) and ICOBiobanc, sponsored by the Catalan Institute of Oncology.
&#8226; CRCGEN: Colorectal Cancer Genetics &amp; Genomics, Spanish study was supported by Instituto de Salud Carlos III, co-funded by FEDER funds &#8211;a way to build Europe&#8211; (grants PI14-613 and PI09-1286), Agency for Management of University and Research Grants (AGAUR) of the Catalan Government (grant 2017SGR723), and Junta de Castilla y Le&#243;n (grant LE22A10-2). Sample collection of this work was supported by the Xarxa de Bancs de Tumors de Catalunya sponsored by Pla Director d&#8217;Oncolog&#237;a de Catalunya (XBTC), Plataforma Biobancos PT13/0010/0013 and ICOBIOBANC, sponsored by the Catalan Institute of Oncology.
&#8226; EPIC-Heidelberg: The coordination of EPIC is financially supported by the European Commission (DG-SANCO) and the International Agency for Research on Cancer. The national cohorts are supported by Danish Cancer Society (Denmark); Ligue Contre le Cancer, Institut Gustave Roussy, Mutuelle G&#233;n&#233;rale de l&#8217;Education Nationale, Institut National de la Sant&#233; et de la Recherche M&#233;dicale (INSERM) (France); German Cancer Aid, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF), Deutsche Krebshilfe, Deutsches Krebsforschungszentrum and Federal Ministry of Education and Research (Germany); the Hellenic Health Foundation (Greece); Associazione Italiana per la Ricerca sul Cancro-AIRC-Italy and National Research Council (Italy); Dutch Ministry of Public Health, Welfare and Sports (VWS), Netherlands Cancer Registry (NKR), LK Research Funds, Dutch Prevention Funds, Dutch ZON (Zorg Onderzoek Nederland), World Cancer Research Fund (WCRF), Statistics Netherlands (The Netherlands); ERC-2009-AdG 232997 and Nordforsk, Nordic Centre of Excellence programme on Food, Nutrition and Health (Norway); Health Research Fund (FIS), PI13/00061 to Granada, PI13/01162 to EPIC-Murcia, Regional Governments of Andaluc&#237;a, Asturias, Basque Country, Murcia and Navarra, ISCIII RETIC (RD06/0020) (Spain); Swedish Cancer Society, Swedish Research Council and County Councils of Sk&#229;ne and V&#228;sterbotten (Sweden); Cancer Research UK (14136 to EPIC-Norfolk; C570/A16491 and C8221/A19170 to EPIC-Oxford), Medical Research Council (1000143 to EPIC-Norfolk, MR/M012190/1 to EPIC-Oxford) (United Kingdom).
&#8226; EPIC-Norfolk: The EPIC-Norfolk study (DOI 10.22025/2019.10.105.00004) has received funding from the Medical Research Council (MR/N003284/1 MC-UU_12015/1 and MC_UU_00006/1) and Cancer Research UK (C864/A14136).
&#8226; HCCS:This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health (grant numbers R01 CA155101, U01 HG004726, R01 CA140561, T32 ES013678, U19 CA148107, P30 CA014089)
&#8226; HPFS: HPFS is supported by the National Institutes of Health (P01 CA055075, UM1 CA167552, R01 CA137178, R01 CA151993, R35 CA197735, K07 CA190673, and P50 CA127003), NHS by the National Institutes of Health (R01 CA137178, P01 CA087969, UM1 CA186107, R01 CA151993, R35 CA197735, K07 CA190673, and P50 CA127003,). We would like to thank the participants and staff of the HPFS for their valuable contributions as well as the following state cancer registries for their help: AL, AZ, AR, CA, CO, CT, DE, FL, GA, ID, IL, IN, IA, KY, LA, ME, MD, MA, MI, NE, NH, NJ, NY, NC, ND, OH, OK, OR, PA, RI, SC, TN, TX, VA, WA, WY. The authors assume full responsibility for analyses and interpretation of these data.
&#8226; IWHS: This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health (R01CA039742).
&#8226; MCCS: MCCS cohort recruitment was funded by VicHealth and Cancer Council Victoria. The MCCS was further supported by Australian NHMRC grants 509348, 209057, 251553 and 504711 and by infrastructure provided by Cancer Council Victoria. Cases and their vital status were ascertained through the Victorian Cancer Registry (VCR) and the Australian Institute of Health and Welfare (AIHW), including the National Death Index and the Australian Cancer Database
&#8226; NHS: NHS is supported by the National Institutes of Health (R01 CA137178, P01 CA087969, UM1 CA186107, R01 CA151993, R35 CA197735, K07 CA190673, and P50 CA127003,). We would like to thank the participants and staff of the NHS for their valuable contributions as well as the following state cancer registries for their help: AL, AZ, AR, CA, CO, CT, DE, FL, GA, ID, IL, IN, IA, KY, LA, ME, MD, MA, MI, NE, NH, NJ, NY, NC, ND, OH, OK, OR, PA, RI, SC, TN, TX, VA, WA, WY. The authors assume full responsibility for analyses and interpretation of these data.
&#8226; PLCO: Intramural Research Program of the Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics and supported by contracts from the Division of Cancer Prevention, National Cancer Institute, NIH, DHHS. Funding was provided by National Institutes of Health (NIH), Genes, Environment and Health Initiative (GEI) Z01 CP 010200, NIH U01 HG004446, and NIH GEI U01 HG 004438. The authors thank the PLCO Cancer Screening Trial screening center investigators and the staff from Information Management Services Inc and Westat Inc. Most importantly, we thank the study participants for their contributions that made this study possible. 

We request that publications resulting from these data cite the following:
&lt;&lt;We hope to publish a manuscript that can be cited once data are ready for uploading to dbGaP&gt;&gt;</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (GSR are sensitive according to the Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="3208" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (PUB)" name="HMB-PUB" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3209" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use" name="GRU" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3210" CGType="cg_class_other" title="Cancer in all age groups, other diseases in adults only, and methods" name="CADM" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>The informed consent document signed by the study participants allows use of these data by investigators for discovery and hypothesis generation in the investigation of the genetic contributions to cancer in all age groups and other diseases in adults only, as well as development of novel analytical approaches for GWAS.
Use of Aggregate Data for GRU: NO</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3211" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Cancer, MDS)" name="DS-CA-MDS" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Cancer.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3212" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical" name="HMB" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="3214" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Colon Cancer, MDS)" name="DS-COC-MDS" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Colon Cancer.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="4291" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (IRB, NPU, GSO)" name="HMB-IRB-NPU-GSO" dac_uid="59" dac_name="NCI DAC" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><AdditionalEmails><Email>CDSHelpDesk@mail.nih.gov</Email></AdditionalEmails></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>