<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="38242" whole_study_id="38242" phs="002195" v="1" p="1" createDate="2020-04-14T13:13:00-05:00" completedByGPADate="2020-04-14T13:31:12-05:00" modDate="2020-10-23T16:08:56-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2020-10-23T16:08:56-05:00" num_participants="562"><StudyInfo accession="phs002195.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs002195.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA671431" entrez_id="671431" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA671432" entrez_id="671432" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>Whole Genome Sequencing of PHACS AMP Cohort</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="whole_targ_genome"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="genotype_calls_from_sequence"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="dna"/><StudyType22 name="from_repository"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>supporting_documents</StudyType><StudyType>dna</StudyType><StudyType>from_repository</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_calls_from_sequence</StudyType><StudyType>whole_genome</StudyType></StudyTypes></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="23" name="NICHD" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="GSEAGE" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GSEAGE" fname="George" mname="" lname="Seage" email="gseage@hsph.harvard.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>HARVARD SCHOOL OF PUBLIC HEALTH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Sean" lname="Brummel" email="sbrummel@sdac.harvard.edu"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="0010147703" aid="1" auth="cit" login="ilekisj" fname="John" mname="Vytautas" lname="Ilekis" email="ilekisj@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>INSTRUCTIONS: Approved Users are expected to acknowledge the Submitting Investigator(s) who submitted data from the original study to an NIH-designated data repository, the primary funding organization that supported the Submitting Investigator(s), and the NIH-designated data repository (e.g., dbGaP).  The acknowledgment statement should include the dbGaP accession number to the specific version of the dataset(s) analyzed.

The study was supported by the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development with co-funding from the National Institute on Drug Abuse, the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, the National Institute of Mental Health, the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, the National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders, the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research, the National Cancer Institute, the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, the Office of AIDS Research, and the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute through cooperative agreements with the Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health (HD052102) (Principal Investigator: George R Seage III; Program Director: Liz Salomon) and the Tulane University School of Medicine (HD052104) (Principal Investigator: Russell Van Dyke; Co-Principal Investigator: Ellen Chadwick; Project Director: Patrick Davis). Data management services were provided by Frontier Science and Technology Research Foundation (PI: Suzanne Siminski), and regulatory services and logistical support were provided by Westat, Inc (PI: Julie Davidson).

The following institutions, clinical site investigators and staff participated in conducting PHACS AMP and AMP Up in 2019, in alphabetical order: Ann &amp; Robert H. Lurie Children&#8217;s Hospital of Chicago: Ellen Chadwick, Margaret Ann Sanders, Kathleen Malee, Yoonsun Pyun; Baylor College of Medicine:, Mary Paul, Shelley Buschur, Chivon McMullen-Jackson, , Lynnette Harris; Bronx Lebanon Hospital Center: Murli Purswani, Mahboobullah Mirza Baig, Alma Villegas; Children's Diagnostic &amp; Treatment Center: Lisa- Gaye Robinson, Sandra Navarro, Patricia Garvie; Boston Children&#8217;s Hospital: Sandra K. Burchett, Rebecca Pinsky , Adam R. Cassidy; Jacobi Medical Center: Andrew Wiznia, Marlene Burey, Ray Shaw,; Rutgers - New Jersey Medical School: Arry Dieudonne, Linda Bettica, Juliette Johnson, Karen Surowiec; St. Christopher&#8217;s Hospital for Children: Janet S. Chen, Taesha White, Mitzie Grant; St. Jude Children's Research Hospital: Katherine Knapp, Jamie Russell-Bell, Megan Wilkins, Erick Odero; San Juan Hospital Research Unit/Department of Pediatrics, San Juan Puerto Rico: Midnela Acevedo-Flores, Heida Rios, Vivian Olivera; Tulane University School of Medicine: Margarita Silio, Medea Gabriel, Patricia Sirois; University of California, San Diego: Stephen A. Spector, Megan Loughran, Veronica Figueroa, Sharon Nichols; University of Colorado Denver Health Sciences Center: Elizabeth McFarland, Carrie Chambers, Emily Barr, Mary Glidden; University of Miami: Gwendolyn Scott, Grace Alvarez, Juan Caffroni, Anai Cuadra

Note: The conclusions and opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of the National Institutes of Health or U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. 

</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (GSR are sensitive according to the Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="3940" CGType="cg_class_HMB" title="Health/Medical/Biomedical (IRB, PUB, NPU, MDS)" name="HMB-IRB-PUB-NPU-MDS" dac_uid="64" dac_name="NICHD" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="14" name="completed_by_gpa" title="Completed by GPA"/></Study></dbgapss>