<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="40513" whole_study_id="40513" phs="002339" v="1" p="1" createDate="2021-02-03T10:27:06-05:00" completedByGPADate="2021-02-03T10:43:18-05:00" modDate="2022-01-25T16:16:24-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2022-01-25T16:16:24-05:00" num_participants="4341"><StudyInfo accession="phs002339.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs002339.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA699343" entrez_id="699343" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA699344" entrez_id="699344" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>NHLBI TOPMed: Nulliparous Pregnancy Outcomes Study: Monitoring Mothers-to-be Heart Health Study (nuMoM2b Heart Health Study)</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="cloud_for_sequence"/><StudyType22 name="whole_targ_genome"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="dna"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>individual_sequencing</StudyType><StudyType>supporting_documents</StudyType><StudyType>dna</StudyType><StudyType>whole_genome</StudyType><StudyType>analysis</StudyType><StudyType>sra</StudyType></StudyTypes><SraStorages><SraStorage location="Google Cloud"><Person email="tblackw@umich.edu"><Role>Cloud Service Administrator</Role></Person><Person email="gccbiost@uw.edu "><Role>Data steward</Role></Person></SraStorage></SraStorages><Funding>U01HL145358</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="12" name="NHLBI" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/><IC id="23" name="NICHD" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="false"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="DAHAAS" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="DAHAAS" fname="DAVID" mname="" lname="HAAS" email="dahaas@iupui.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>INDIANA UNIV-PURDUE UNIV AT INDIANAPOLIS</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011664335" aid="1" auth="cit" login="pembertonv" fname="Victoria" mname="Lee" lname="Pemberton" email="pembertonv@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="RMCNEIL" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="RMCNEIL" fname="Rebecca" mname="" lname="McNeil" email="rmcneil@rti.org"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization>RESEARCH TRIANGLE INSTITUTEMAYO CLINIC  JACKSONVILLEDURHAM VA MEDICAL CENTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="RMCNEIL" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="RMCNEIL" fname="Rebecca" mname="" lname="McNeil" email="rmcneil@rti.org"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>RESEARCH TRIANGLE INSTITUTEMAYO CLINIC  JACKSONVILLEDURHAM VA MEDICAL CENTER</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011276160" aid="1" auth="cit" login="thomsonal" fname="Alastair" mname="Alexander" lname="Thomson" email="alastair.thomson@nih.gov"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0014418323" aid="1" auth="cit" login="dzakpasuns" fname="Noble" mname="Senyo" lname="Dzakpasu" email="dzakpasuns@mail.nih.gov"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="GROSSMANR" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="GROSSMANR" fname="ROBERT" mname="" lname="GROSSMAN" email="rgrossman1@uchicago.edu"><Role>PI_AA_DELEG</Role><Organization>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS AT CHICAGOUNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</Organization></Person><Person nedid="2001545300" aid="1" auth="cit" login="lic17" fname="Chengyuan" mname="" lname="Press" email="chanel.press@nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>The TOPMed acknowledgement statement can be found at: https://topmed.nhlbi.nih.gov/acknowledgements. In addition, please include: &#8220;The original nuMoM2b study, during which the DNA samples were collected, was initiated October 10, 2010 and supported by the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD): U10 HD063036, Research Triangle Institute; U10 HD063072, Case Western Reserve University; U10 HD063047, Columbia University; U10 HD063037, Indiana University; U10 HD063041, Magee-Womens Hospital of the University of Pittsburgh; U10 HD063020, Northwestern University; U10 HD063046, University of California Irvine; U10 HD063048, University of Pennsylvania; and U10 HD063053, University of Utah. 

The follow-on nuMoM2b Heart Health Study (nuMoM2b-HHS1), active from August 24, 2014 through October 30, 2020, was supported the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) and the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD): U10-HL119991, Research Triangle Institute; U10-HL119989, Case Western Reserve University; U10-HL120034, Columbia University; U10-HL119990, Indiana University; U10-HL120006, Magee-Womens Hospital of the University of Pittsburgh; U10-HL119992, Northwestern University; U10-HL120019, University of California Irvine; U10-HL119993, University of Pennsylvania; and U10-HL120018, University of Utah.  In addition, support was provided by the National Center for Research Resources and the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences,NIH to Clinical and Translational Science Institutes at Indiana University (UL1TR001108) and University of California Irvine (UL1TR000153). 

A Continuation of the nuMoM2b Heart Health Study (nuMoM2b-HHS2) began February 15, 2020 and is supported by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI): U01HL145358, Research Triangle Institute.

Clinical sites with principal investigators (PIs) providing access to study participants and samples include: Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio (Brian M. Mercer); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Columbia University, New York, New York (Ronald J. Wapner); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Christiana Care, Wilmington, Delaware subsite of the Columbia University site (Matthew K. Hoffman); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, School of Medicine, Indiana University, Indianapolis, Indiana (David M. Haas); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Magee-Womens Hospital of the University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (Hyagriv N. Simhan); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Northwestern University, Chicago, Illinois (William A. Grobman); Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Northwestern University, Chicago, Illinois (Philip Greenland, multiple PI for nuMoM2b-HHS2); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of California, Irvine, Irvine, California (Deborah A. Wing &#8211; PI for nuMoM2b and initial years of the nuMom2b-HHS1, Judith Chung &#8211; PI for part of nuMoM2b-HHS1 and nuMoM2b-HHS2); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Samuel Parry &#8211; PI for nuMoM2b and nuMoM2b-HHS1, Lisa Levine &#8211; PI for nuMoM2b-HHS2); Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Utah and Intermountain Healthcare, Salt Lake City, Utah (Robert M. Silver);

Independent Steering Committee Chair: George R. Saade, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Texas Medical Branch, University of Texas, Galveston, Texas. 
Data Coordination and Analysis Center, which tracked all specimens and managed and analyzed study data: Research Triangle Institute, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina (Corette B. Parker, PI &#8211; 2010-2021, Rebecca McNeil, incoming PI in 2021). 

Biospecimen Repository for the nuMoM2b Heart Health Studies: Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, California (C. Noel Bairey Merz). 

The following NIH Program Officers provided support and input to study activities through the cooperative agreement mechanism: National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, Bethesda, Maryland (Victoria L. Pemberton, Dale R. Burwen) and the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, Bethesda, Maryland (Uma M. Reddy).

NuMoM2b and nuMoM2b-HHS1 are described in the following publications:
Haas DM, Parker CB, Wing DA, Parry S, Grobman WA, Mercer BM, Simhan HN, Hoffman MK, Silver RM, Wadhwa P, Iams JD, Koch MA, Caritis SN, Wapner RJ, Esplin MS, Elovitz MA, Foroud T, Peaceman AM, Saade GR, Willinger M, Reddy UM; for the NuMoM2b study. A Description of the Methods of the Nulliparous Pregnancy Outcomes Study: monitoring mothers-to-be (nuMoM2b). Am J Obstet Gynecol 2015 Apr 212(4): 539.e1-539.e24. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2015.01.019. Epub 2015 Jan 31. PMCID: PMC4387083

Haas DM, Ehrenthal DB, Koch MA, Catov JM, Barnes SE, Facco F, Parker CB, Mercer BM, Bairey-Merz CN, Silver RM, Wapner RJ, Simhan HN, Hoffman MK, Grobman WA, Greenland P, Wing DA, Saade GR, Parry S, Zee PC, Reddy UM, Pemberton VL, Burwen DR; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute nuMoM2b Heart Health Study Network (2016). Pregnancy as a Window to Future Cardiovascular Health: Design and Implementation of the nuMoM2b Heart Health Study. Am J Epidemiol, 2016 Mar 15;183(6):519-30. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwv309. Epub 2016 Jan 28. PMCID: PMC4782765. 

De-identified data for nuMoM2b participants who agreed to public release of their de-identified data is available through the NICHD Data and Specimen Hub (DASH). Public release of the nuMoM2b-HHS1 data, which will include nuMoM2b data, is pending."</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term>There is one consent group for this study: GRU-IRB.
Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval (please note that only full or expedited IRB approvals will be accepted).</ic_specific_access_term><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="contr_access" gsr_mode_label="Controlled-access (GSR are sensitive according to the Institutional Certification)"/><ConsentGroup uid="4355" CGType="cg_class_GRU" title="General Research Use (IRB)" name="GRU-IRB" dac_uid="56" dac_name="NHLBI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.

Please note that only full or expedited IRB approvals will be accepted.</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><ConsentGroup uid="4356" CGType="cg_class_EA" title="Exchange Area (IRB)" name="EA-IRB" dac_uid="56" dac_name="NHLBI" irb-approval-required="Yes"><Use-Restriction>Use by NHLBI WGS study investigators only.
There is one consent group for this study: GRU-IRB.
Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval (please note that only full or expedited IRB approvals will be accepted).
</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup><TrustedPartners><TrustedPartner trp_id="11" trp_db_name="NHLBI BioData Catalyst" trp_download_url="https://biodatacatalyst.nhlbi.nih.gov/resources/data" trp_help_url="https://biodatacatalyst.nhlbi.nih.gov/contact"><StudyFlags sam_with_min_meta="Yes" seq_data_to_ncbi="Yes" gen_phen_to_ncbi="Yes" has_out_ncbi_data="Yes"/></TrustedPartner></TrustedPartners></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="14" name="completed_by_gpa" title="Completed by GPA"/></Study></dbgapss>