<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><dbgapss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbgapssws.1.0.xsd"><Study uid="40124" whole_study_id="40124" phs="002328" v="1" p="1" createDate="2020-12-14T12:12:29-05:00" completedByGPADate="2020-12-16T09:11:07-05:00" modDate="2021-03-19T22:22:20-05:00" maxParentChildStudyModDate="2021-03-19T22:22:20-05:00" handle="EPIPARK_HBS2" num_participants="268"><StudyInfo accession="phs002328.v1.p1" parentAccession="phs002328.v1.p1"><BioProject id="PRJNA691646" entrez_id="691646" type="bp_admin_access"/><BioProject id="PRJNA691647" entrez_id="691647" type="bp_data_submission"/><StudyNameEntrez>EPIPARK and HBS2 Cohorts</StudyNameEntrez><StudyTypes2 calculated="Yes"><StudyType21 name="phenotype_data" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="analysis" chosen="Yes"/><StudyType21 name="individual_sequencing" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="supporting_documents" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="images" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="molecular" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="array_multi_sample_gen"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="subject_samples" chosen="Yes"><StudyType22 name="dna"/></StudyType21><StudyType21 name="links_to_ncbi_dbs" chosen="No"/><StudyType21 name="other_general" chosen="No"/></StudyTypes2><StudyTypes><StudyType>phenotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>genotype_data</StudyType><StudyType>dna</StudyType><StudyType>snp_array</StudyType><StudyType>array_derived_genotypes</StudyType><StudyType>analysis</StudyType></StudyTypes><Funding> R01NS115144</Funding></StudyInfo><Authority><ICs><IC id="7" name="NINDS" is_funding_ic="true" is_admin_ic="true" primary="true"/></ICs><Persons><Person nedid="CSR123" aid="2" auth="eRA" login="CSR123" fname="CLEMENS" mname="" lname="SCHERZER" email="cscherzer@rics.bwh.harvard.edu"><Role allow_direct_access="true">PI</Role><Organization>BRIGHAM AND WOMEN'S HOSPITAL</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010798151" aid="1" auth="cit" login="dbabcock" fname="Debra" mname="J" lname="Babcock" email="dbabcock@ninds.nih.gov"><Role>PO</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person aid="8" auth="virtual" fname="Xianjun" lname="Dong" email="xdong@rics.bwh.harvard.edu"><Role>PI_ASSIST</Role><Organization/></Person><Person nedid="0010579723" aid="1" auth="cit" login="wewu" fname="Wenyu" mname="" lname="Wu" email="wwu@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"><Role>PHENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0011559580" aid="1" auth="cit" login="stefanov" fname="Stefan" mname="Alexandrov" lname="Stefanov" email="stefanov@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GENO_CURATOR</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person><Person nedid="0010146585" aid="1" auth="cit" login="zhangr" fname="Ran" mname="" lname="Zhang" email="zhangr@mail.nih.gov"><Role>GPA</Role><Organization>NIH</Organization></Person></Persons></Authority><Policy display-research-statement="true" display-public-summary="true" years-until-renewal="1" weeks-to-cancel-request="8" pub-embargo="none"><acknowledgement_statement>These data were generated and made available through the International Genetics of Parkinson Progression (IGPP) Consortium (Coordinating PI, Clemens R. Scherzer, MD). Genotyping for cohorts EPIPARK and HBS2 was funded by NINDS and NIA R01NS115144 (to Clemens R. Scherzer, MD. The clinical cohorts were recruited and assessed by the EPIPARK and the HBS study coordination teams, including the following investigators:

EPIPARK: Study Directors: Meike Kasten, MD, Institute of Neurogenetics, University of L&#252;beck, University Hospital of Schleswig-Holstein, L&#252;beck, 23562, Germany, Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University of L&#252;beck, 23562, Germany; and Christine Klein, MD, Institute of Neurogenetics, University of L&#252;beck, University Hospital of Schleswig-Holstein, L&#252;beck, 23562, Germany. We would like to acknowledge Katja Lohmann, Eva Juliane Vollstedt, Norbert Brueggemann and the EPIPARK team, Grants KA3179/2-1 and FOR 2488 (to M.K.). We also acknowledge Annika Klee, who helped to extract the data needed for this work and parts of the clinical data used here will be part of her doctoral thesis.

Harvard Biomarkers Study (HBS2 subset). Co-Directors: Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital: Clemens R. Scherzer, Massachusetts General Hospital: Bradley T. Hyman; Investigators and Study Coordinators: Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital: Yuliya Kuras, Karbi Choudhury, Nada Laroussi, Michael T. Hayes, Aleksandar Videnovic, Nutan Sharma, Vikram Khurana, Claudio Melo De Gusmao, Reisa Sperling; Massachusetts General Hospital: John H. Growdon, Michael A. Schwarzschild, Albert Y. Hung, Alice W. Flaherty, Deborah Blacker, Anne-Marie Wills, Steven E. Arnold, Ann L. Hunt, Nicte I. Mejia, Anand Viswanathan, Stephen N. Gomperts, Mark W. Albers, Maria Allora-Palli, David Hsu, Alexandra Kimball, Scott McGinnis, John Becker, Randy Buckner, Thomas Byrne, Maura Copeland, Bradford Dickerson, Matthew Frosch, Theresa Gomez-Isla, Steven Greenberg, Julius Hedden, Elizabeth Hedley-Whyte, Keith Johnson, Raymond Kelleher, Aaron Koenig, Maria Marquis-Sayagues, Gad Marshall, Sergi Martinez-Ramirez, Donald McLaren, Olivia Okereke, Elena Ratti, Christopher William, Koene Van Dij, Shuko Takeda, Anat Stemmer-Rachaminov, Jessica Kloppenburg, Catherine Munro, Rachel Schmid, Sarah Wigman, Sara Wlodarcsyk; Data Coordination: Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital: Thomas Yi; Biobank Management Staff: Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital: Idil Tuncali. We thank all study participants and their families for their invaluable contributions. HBS is made possible by generous support from the Harvard NeuroDiscovery Center, with additional contributions from the Michael J Fox Foundation, NINDS U01NS082157, U01NS100603, and the Massachusetts Alzheimer&#8217;s Disease Research Center NIA P50AG005134.

Reference this publication for using these data sets:
Liu et al., under review for Nature Genetics, 2020
</acknowledgement_statement><ic_specific_access_term/><DUC universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC><DUC_PDF universal_duc="Yes"><File full_url="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/docs/Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" filename="Static_DUC_20190419.pdf" content-type="application/pdf"/></DUC_PDF><GSR_Access gsr_mode="unrest_access" gsr_mode_label="Unrestricted access"/><ConsentGroup uid="4288" CGType="cg_class_DS" title="Disease-Specific (Neurological and Related Disorders)" name="DS-NDRD" dac_uid="53" dac_name="NINDS" irb-approval-required="No"><Use-Restriction>Use of the data must be related to Neurological and Related Disorders.

</Use-Restriction></ConsentGroup></Policy><SRA/><Documents/><Status uid="1" name="released" title="Released"/></Study></dbgapss>